The MIT Press

Cambridge, Massachusetts

London, England

http://mitpress.mit.edu/books/panpsychism-west

Panpsychism in the West

revised edition

David F. Skrbina

dedicated to all those who seek alternatives to the mechanistic worldview

© 2017 Massachusetts Institute of Technology

All rights reserved. No part of this book may be reproduced in any form by any electronic or mechanical means (including photocopying, recording, or information storage and retrieval) without permission in writing from the publisher.

Set in ITC Stone Sans Std and ITC Stone Serif Std by Toppan Best-set Premedia Limited. Printed and bound in the United States of America.

Library of Congress Cataloging-in-Publication Data

Names: Skrbina, David, author.

Title: Panpsychism in the West / David Skrbina.

Description: Revised edition. | Cambridge, MA : The MIT Press, 2017. | Includes bibliographical references and index.

Identifiers: LCCN 2016059702 | ISBN 9780262534062 (pbk. : alk. paper)

Subjects: LCSH: Panpsychism--History.

Classification: LCC BD560 .P35 2017 | DDC 141--dc23 LC record available at https://lccn.loc.gov/2016059702

3 Developments in the Renaissance: Sixteenth- and Seventeenth-Century Europe

3.1 Transition to the Renaissance

From about the third century AD onward, Christian monotheism grew steadily in power and influence. Stoic, Roman, and other Greek influences were gradually buried beneath a growing orthodox theology. The faith-based Christian worldview first competed with and then surpassed the older Greek worldview, which was based primarily on reason and logic. Monotheism was in direct conflict with panpsychism, and thus it effectively suppressed any advances in panpsychist philosophy. The Christian worldview, along with select aspects of Aristotelian natural philosophy, dominated Western intellectual thought for about 1,300 years.

A new worldview emerged at the time of the Renaissance. The religious worldview had reached its peak, and its position as the leading social influence began to wane. The newly emerging worldview was a system based not on divine scripture but on empirical observations of nature and on rationalist introspection of reality. It saw the world once again as regular, rational, and knowable. It applied new techniques in mathematics to natural phenomena, and perceived a new kind of order in the universe. The regularity and predictability led to a new phenomenon: mankind’s inclination to control and manipulate nature. This new vision of the cosmos has come to be known as the Mechanistic Worldview. Its central metaphor was the cosmos as a clockwork mechanism, a machine—consistent, predictable, comprehensible, and controllable, even though (perhaps) constructed by a Supreme Creator whose nature was necessarily of an entirely different sort.

Throughout the emergence and rise to power of this new worldview, there was a persistent countercurrent of thought that was non-mechanistic. That line of thinking saw the universe as animated—as possessing mind, sensitivity, and awareness. It was explored, developed, and promoted by some of the greatest thinkers of the time. Empirical science did nothing to dissuade panpsychist philosophers from that view, and more often served to support it. Even some of the founders of mechanistic philosophy—the thinkers we most associate with advancing this new worldview—harbored doubts about viewing matter as inherently lifeless, inert, and insensate.

In the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries, several major philosophers advocated or were strongly sympathetic to panpsychism, including Paracelsus, Cardano, Telesio, Patrizi, Bruno, Campanella, Henry More, Margaret Cavendish, Spinoza, and Leibniz. In that era, when the dominant worldview was moving from Christianity to mechanism, panpsychism found sympathy in neither sphere. To the leading theologians it was heresy, and to the founders of mechanism it was largely irrelevant. Advocating views that were fundamentally opposed to mechanism and (especially) to Christianity was hazardous; it could mean anything from a sullied reputation to personal ruin, imprisonment, or death. Thus a panpsychist position had to be well thought out and deeply held. Only those most committed to it dared to speak out.

The Renaissance was both a rebirth and a reawakening of philosophy. The religious worldview had begun to play itself out as the dominant interpretation of the universe, even as the new mechanical philosophy was emerging. While still important in personal, cultural, and governmental matters, religion was proving increasingly unable to explain the events of the natural world. Marsilio Ficino kept God in his hierarchical system, but placed soul at the center and described it as radiating out into all aspects of reality. Similarly, other central thinkers, especially in the sixteenth century, denied not God but rather religion’s claim to be the sole purveyor of truth.

This was particularly true of Ficino’s star pupil, Giovanni Pico della Mirandola (1463–1494). For Pico, nature was an interconnected whole, living and ensouled. Cassirer (1942: 338) calls this system “universal vitalism”; it is a view in which a world-soul inhabits, moves, and even constitutes all matter. Thus Cassirer adds that “for Pico therefore it is certain … that nature can be regarded and interpreted only as the first stage of spirit,” a kind of unconscious mentality. Commenting on Pico’s system, Dulles (1941: 88) notes that “if the lower forms of life are material, it must be true, conversely, that all matter is, in a sense, alive.” In his Conclusiones, Pico writes: “Nothing in the world is devoid of life. … Wherever there is life, there is soul; wherever there is soul, there is a mind.”^1 We may therefore count Pico as among the earliest panpsychists of the Renaissance, even though his natural philosophy assumed a secondary role in his larger system.

Though working from faulty premises, the alchemists of the fourteenth and fifteenth centuries made considerable progress in revealing the capabilities and powers of material substances. While not denying God, they relied primarily on new empirical procedures that demonstrated the potency and energy inherent in elemental matter itself. Of particular note is the work of Paracelsus (1493–1541). Equal parts alchemist, physician, and philosopher, his view of the macrocosm-microcosm analogy imputed all properties of the one to the other. Mankind, having life and intelligence, was thus seen as reflected in the larger natural world. Paracelsus seems to have held to a form of spirit-matter parallelism in which all things possessed a life spirit that was connected with elemental air:

None can deny that the air gives life to all corporeal and substantial things. … The life of things is none other than a spiritual essence, an invisible and impalpable thing, a spirit and a spiritual thing. On this account there is nothing corporeal but has latent within itself a spirit and life. (1894: 135)

Paracelsus’ panpsychist or hylozoist view accounted for variations in spirit by the corresponding variations in physical nature: “it is evident that there are different kinds of spirits, just as there are different kinds of bodies.” These different spirits accounted for the differing “lives” of material substances. He gives a lengthy account of the life of various things, including salts, gems, metals, minerals, roots, “aromatic substances,” “sweet things,” resins, fruits, herbs, wood, bones, and water (136–137). Walter Pagel elaborates on precisely this point:

Life to Paracelsus is “virtue” and function. At the same time it is … something not merely spiritual but of finest corporeality. It comes to us from and through the air—for “air gives all things their life.” There is nothing corporeal that has not a “spiritual thing” hidden in itself. Hence to Paracelsus, all things are alive … . (1982: 117)

Here again we find an explicit form of hylozoism.

This kind of spiritual empiricism established the background for the emerging philosophy of the Italian Renaissance, typically referred to as Renaissance naturalism. The first five panpsychist philosophers of that era—Cardano, Telesio, Patrizi, Bruno, and Campanella—were Italians. All were born in the sixteenth century, and all were among the leading intellectual figures of their time. All disdained the standard theology, all opposed the dominance of Aristotelianism and scholasticism, and all looked to nature for insights into reality.

3.2 Four Italian Naturalists: Cardano, Telesio, Patrizi, and Bruno

Girolamo Cardano (1501–1576) was the first of the Italian naturalists to put forth an unambiguous panpsychist philosophy. Spending most of his life in Milan and northern Italy, he was a renowned mathematician and physician, a prolific writer and inventor, and a diligent student of ancient philosophy. Stoicism affected both his metaphysical and his ethical beliefs. He studied Plato and Aristotle, ultimately siding with the Platonists in rejecting the Aristotelian picture of the universe.

Cardano’s conception of panpsychism is spelled out primarily in De natura (On Nature) and De subtilitate (On Subtlety), works in which he describes his theory of soul and its central role of maintaining the unity of all bodies. Soul is one of five universal qualities: “There are five principles of natural things: matter or ‘hyle,’ form, soul, place, and motion.” (1560/2013: 53) But soul clearly has a central role: “[Bodies] come into being from matter and form. But they are controlled by the soul, which in the more noble beings is mind … ; in bodies it is the principle of life.” (54) Here we see the Aristotelian influence both in the emphasis on form and in the distinction between mind and soul; all things have soul, but only the higher forms—such as humans—have mind. Cardano furthermore takes pains to emphasize the universality of soul: “Matter is everywhere, but cannot exist without a form, hence form too must be everywhere. But also a soul, whether because there is to be generation everywhere, or … because in every body there is evidently a principle of motion.” (27)

Cardano’s other Greek influences also reveal themselves in his writings. First there is his theory of the “active” (heat) and the “passive” (prime matter in De natura, and moisture in De subtilitate), which recalls the Stoic system. Stoic influence is also found in his reference to the pneuma, the “vital spirit” that circulates in the animal body and gives it life. Empedocles’ two forces of Love and Strife are reflected in Cardano’s “sympathy” and “antipathy.” According to Fierz (1983: xvii), “the main principle underlying [hidden] relationships is the sympathy and antipathy of all things, which partake in a common life.” Cardano does make a slight break with the Greeks in arguing against the designation of fire as an element. To him fire is heat, the active principle, which acts on the passive—matter and moisture—to produce form. This is a general ontological principle, and hence for Cardano “all permanent bodies, including stones, are always slightly moist and warm and of necessity animate” (66).

The animation of inorganic objects covers a striking list of properties, such that the usual distinctions are blurred. In De subtilitate Cardano writes extensively about compound or “mixed” substances—that is, things that are not pure elements. Such things are intrinsically alive:

The basis of growth and nutrition—and indeed of generation—is almost the same; there processes take place from the soul. In fact it is a task for the soul alone to be capable in this fashion of thinning out and then uniting and transmuting. If indeed there is anything devoid of life that could do this, it would above all be fire … yet it cannot. … And so all mixed things must be alive or have been so. (292)

Later he recaps this point: “We have shown previously that things that are mixed are alive; this is especially appropriate for stones. They are not simply alive, but also undergo diseases, old age, and later also death.” (366) Near the end of the work, he adds this:

Then it should be said, on comparable reasoning, that while a stone is in motion, it moves sideways by violence, and towards the center by nature, and thus on a middle line, because this would occur through recognition by the stone thus deliberating (deliberantis). (741)

Apparently a stone set in motion, subject to both impulsive and gravitational forces, is able to calculate, or deliberate on, the net force and to move in that direction.

Cardano seems not to have left much of an immediate philosophical legacy. His contributions are acknowledged today; however, Renaissance philosophers don’t appear to have been directly influenced by him, as we see little citation of his work. Such was not the case with Bernardino Telesio (1509–1588). Born eight years after Cardano, Telesio left a lasting imprint on Western philosophy, primarily through Bruno, Campanella, Bacon, and Hobbes. Hoeffding (1908: 92) called Telesio’s work “the greatest task undertaken by thought in the sixteenth century,” in large part because it forcefully struck out against the dominance of Aristotle and the Scholastics. Even more so than Cardano, Telesio relied on insights from nature to form his philosophy. Experience became a crucial aspect of inquiry and the cornerstone of all true knowledge.

Telesio’s philosophy is encapsulated in his magnum opus, the nine-volume De rerum natura (“On the Nature of Things”). The first edition, published in 1565 under a slightly different title, was revised in 1570 and then enlarged for a third and final release in 1586. In it Telesio overthrew the Aristotelian emphasis on matter and form, replacing it with an Empedoclean (and modern) conception of matter and force. Like Empedocles, Telesio saw two fundamental and opposing forces at work in the universe: Heat (an expanding and motive principle) and Cold (a contracting principle). These forces act on and shape the “third principle”: passive matter, which is associated with the earth. Thus, for Telesio all things consist of an active energy component, in the heat principle, and a mass component, in the passive matter of the earth: “All things [are] made of earth by the sun; and that in the constitution of all things, the earth and the sun enter respectively as mother and father.” (1586/1967: 309)

In addition to acting as material forces, Heat and Cold have the remarkable quality of perception. They necessarily tend to preserve themselves, particularly in the face of the other. Heat, insofar as it tends to stay hot, must somehow sense and know Cold, and repel it. And likewise with Cold. Ultimately we find a kind of balance or stalemate between the two principles, each existing in a state of dynamic tension (antiperistasis). Heat and Cold must possess the power to sense, to perceive, or else they simply could not exist. “It is quite evident that nature is propelled by self-interest.” (304) Self-preservation demands sensation (sensus). More than this, as an active principle of self-awareness, heat combines with matter to create a spiritual entity, a universitas spiritus that pervades the cosmos. This cosmic spirit is not only universally present, it is fully self-aware and thus aware of everything—a true spiritus omniscius omnino. It is a kind of world-soul, but one that derives from the inner nature of reality rather than as installed from without by some Demiurge.

In sum, all material objects embody the active principles of Heat and Cold. Therefore, all things must contain the power of perception. This is the basis for Telesio’s panpsychism. More properly, we refer to his position as pansensism—the view that everything is capable of sensation. As Giglioni says, “We can therefore say that Telesio understands sensus as the primordial sense of “being affected” pervading the entire universe. … [It] is an undivided and seamless process in which feeling, appetite, and motion mutate into each other.” Sensus is necessarily self-awareness, “and nature is accordingly conscious nature” (2010: 72–73).

Telesio effectively used the Non-Emergence argument to support his pansensist view. He claimed that it was inconceivable that mind should emerge from within matter unless it already had been there to some degree. Hoeffding (1908: 97) informs us that Telesio maintains “the impossibility of explaining the genesis of consciousness out of matter, unless we suppose matter to be originally endowed with consciousness.” Emergence is impossible, and therefore mind or soul is seen as inevitably present in the very structure of the cosmos—and in particular, in the fundamental active principles of Heat and Cold.

Telesio, like Cardano, was strongly influenced by Stoicism. Giglioni writes that “Stoic themes and their role in shaping his thought cannot be downplayed” (71). In addition to the active/passive distinction, his conception of the soul has many affinities to the Stoic pneuma. Like the pneuma, Telesio’s soul is corporeal, existing as a substance of “extreme tenuity and subtlety” (1586/1967: 305). Soul, like the pneuma, pervades all things, and both are embodiments of the active principle. That both Telesio and the Stoics should have reached a panpsychist conclusion, then, is not surprising.

But there is one important difference: Soul “possesses, besides sensation, the faculty of memory or retention” (Kristeller 1964: 100). This is significant because it is the first instance of memory playing a role in a metaphysical system—thus setting the stage for the later developments of Hobbes, Bergson, Russell, Bohm, and others. Unfortunately it is unclear how Telesio intends us to take his conception of memory: as merely a kind of persistent record of past experiences or, in a stronger sense, as an ability to recall past experiences. Regardless, it is an important milestone in panpsychist thinking.

Telesio’s heat and cold principles furthermore seem to find confirmation in modern physics. On some readings of cosmology, as the early universe began to cool after the Big Bang, a temperature differential emerged between radiation and matter. This thermal gradient supplies the universe with free energy that allows it to create order and structure in matter—everything from stars and planets to plants, animals, and people. In a sense, all material objects embody this thermal gradient, and owe their very existence to it. In the present context, we may note that the gradient occurs between the relatively hot radiation and relatively cool matter. Telesio’s “heat” and “cold,” understood as relative concepts, closely align with this modern conception. So conceived, heat and cold do in fact account for the existence of all order in the universe. And if we allow that our minds also emerged by this process of natural evolution, heat and cold also account for our sentience, self-awareness, and consciousness. Telesio seems to have been not far from the mark.^2

Francesco Patrizi (1529–1597), like the other Italian naturalists, professed a deep dislike of Aristotelian philosophy and sought to place Platonism on at least an equal footing. In 1578, in recognition of his efforts, he was appointed to the world’s first chair of Platonic philosophy, at Ferrara. Patrizi, also a humanist and a poet, exchanged several philosophical letters with Telesio. His lyrical view of the world is reflected in his most important philosophical work, Nova de universis philosophia (New Philosophy of the Universe), in which he introduced the term ‘panpsychism’ (pampsychia) into the vocabulary of Western philosophy.

The Nova philosophia is a wide-ranging metaphysical treatise that lays out Patrizi’s theories of light, the soul, and the first principles of the cosmos. It is organized in four sections: Panaugia (“The All-Light”), Panarchia (“The All-Principles”), Pampsychia (“The All-Souls”), and Pancosmia (“The All-Cosmos”). The third section is of primary interest here, as it focuses on his interpretation of the world-soul and its particular manifestations in the natural world. In Patrizi’s cosmological hierarchy there are nine levels or grades of being; from highest to lowest: unity, essence, life, intelligence, soul, nature, quality, form, and body. Soul, notably, takes the middle and thus central role in the scheme, much as it did for Cardano. Furthermore, the nine levels of being are all fundamentally interconnected in what Brickman (1941: 34) describes as a deeply participatory process:

These nine grades are linked by a process of “partaking of one another”—participatio. This “partaking” Patrizi describes as an “inter-illumination,” through which beings are illuminated, come into existence, and are known. … Every grade partakes of each of those above it … and is also partaken of by each grade below it according to the capacity of the latter. Each grade … is [at once] a “partaker” (particeps), and is “partaken of” (participatus).

Patrizi echoes the language of participation as found in Neo-Platonism, especially in the work of Proclus and Pseudo-Dionysius. Such terminology builds on Plato’s original use of the concept as the means by which the phenomenal world interacts with the Forms.^3

Soul, at the center of this participatory hierarchy, plays a major role in mediating between the upper spiritual grades and the lower earthly realms. At a minimum, it is clear that soul, in the form of the world-soul, penetrates all levels of being. The question, as before, is whether the individual objects of the world possess souls in themselves—i.e., true panpsychism—or whether they are merely extensions of the one world-soul. Patrizi clearly opted for the pluralistic view. He saw soul as a manifold entity, present both as distinct individuals and as united in the comprehensive world-soul. Kristeller (1964: 122) writes that “Patrizi does not treat the individual souls as [mere] parts of the world soul, but believes, rather, that their relation to their bodies is analogous to that of the world soul to the universe as a whole.” In the words of Brickman (1941: 41), soul is “both [unity and plurality], with the many contained in the one.”

Patrizi was the first to directly attack Aristotle’s logic regarding panpsychism, a position that would be reiterated later by both Bruno and Gilbert. All three men focused their criticism on Aristotle’s definition of psyche; and they all seem to have been unaware of his broader theory of the pneuma. As I noted, Aristotle believed the stars and heavenly bodies were animate, but he granted psyche to nothing in the earthly realm save plants and animals. Patrizi saw this as a logical inconsistency. On the one hand, the Peripatetics defined soul as the motive force behind a living, organic body. On the other, Aristotle himself stated that stars were ensouled even though they were not organic. One of the two positions must be wrong. Taking Aristotle’s implicit definition, Patrizi argues that an organic structure is not a prerequisite for having a soul, and so it is certainly possible that the cosmos as a whole, as well as the basic elements of matter that constitute it, also have souls.

Patrizi then runs through a series of brief arguments in support of his panpsychism: (1) How do we know that the elements do not have organs of some sort, and thus are “organic”? If they do, then this is a further argument on behalf of their souls (Design argument). (2) The cosmos is clearly the most perfect thing there is, and any perfect thing must have a soul or it would be less than perfect; therefore the world-soul exists (Design argument). (3) The elements give life and soul to all beings which have it, and nothing can be in the effect that is not in the cause; therefore, the elements must have souls (Non-Emergence). (4) All parts of the world experience birth, change, and destruction, yet they still have the power to hold together and persist; this cannot happen without soul (Indwelling Powers). These themes were developed by later philosophers, and Patrizi’s participatory ontology thus set the stage for the advances made by his immediate successors.^4

Apart from Telesio, the other great philosopher of southern Italy was Giordano Bruno (1548–1600). Bruno’s philosophical system was rooted in his cosmology. The standard picture of the cosmos in the sixteenth century was essentially the same that Aristotle developed nearly 2,000 years earlier, and the same that Ptolemy had formalized in the second century AD: The universe was a finite space with the Earth at the center, and the stars and other heavenly bodies circulated around us on the celestial spheres. Throughout the centuries, a few thinkers had speculated otherwise, namely that the universe might actually be infinite. As early as 300 BC, Epicurus reasoned that the universe must be limitless: “The totality of things is unlimited … and having no limit, it must be infinite and without boundaries.” (Letter to Herodotus, 41–42) In the first century BC, Lucretius wrote:

The All that Is, wherever its paths may lead, is boundless. … There can be no end to anything without something beyond to mark that end. … Nor does it matter at which point one may stand: whatever position a man takes up, he finds the All still endless alike in all directions. (1977: 23; book I, 957–967)

Closer to Bruno’s time, the neo-Platonist philosopher Nicholas of Cusa (1401–1464) also discussed the possibility and significance of an infinite cosmos. Then came Copernicus’ De revolutionibus, published upon his death in 1543, which placed the sun at the center of the cosmos and the Earth in orbit around it. But Copernicus still maintained that the universe was finite, and that the celestial spheres circled around the solar system; in that sense he was less revolutionary than is commonly believed.

Bruno gathered these insights from Epicurus, Cusa, and Copernicus and pieced together a strikingly modern picture of the cosmos. His universe was an infinite space composed of infinitely many solar systems like our own. He was one of the first to use modern terminology, reserving ‘world’ for the Earth and other planets and using ‘universe’ to mean the whole infinite cosmos. Bruno saw neither the Earth nor the sun as the center of the universe; like Lucretius, he realized that, in an infinite cosmos, every place would appear as the center. Bruno said: “The Earth no more than any other world is at the center … . The Earth is not in the center of the universe; it is central only to our own surrounding space.”^5

From this cosmology he drew important philosophical and metaphysical implications. First, he realized that there was an aspect of relativity to the cosmos. If the universe was, in a sense, the same throughout, then the same rules must apply everywhere. Hoeffding stated that, in Bruno’s cosmology,

every determination of place must be relative … . From the relativity of [place and] motion follows the relativity of time … . Nor have the concepts of heaviness and lightness any … absolute significance … . Nature is everywhere essentially the same [and] the same force is everywhere in operation. (1908: 124–126)

This “universality” of the universe meant that any physical or metaphysical conclusions arrived at here on Earth must of necessity apply throughout all existence.

Bruno’s panpsychism followed directly from his metaphysics. Nature has two internal constituent principles: form and matter. He takes this Aristotelian orthodoxy and interprets it in a Platonic or Plotinian manner. In particular, form is to be considered as produced by soul, i.e., the world-soul: “Bruno asserts that … every form is produced by a soul. For all things are animated by the world soul, and all matter is everywhere permeated by soul and spirit.” (Kristeller 1964: 133)

Bruno develops his panpsychism primarily in De la causa, principio, et uno (Cause, Principle, and Unity) and in De l’infinito universo et mondi (On the Infinite Universe and Worlds). Both were published in 1584, just after his visit to Oxford. Both were written in dialogue form, in the fashion of Plato.

It is in De la causa that Bruno states his view most clearly. In the second dialogue, the characters are elaborating on the animated nature of the cosmos. Adopting the language and concepts of his opponents, Bruno notes that, even within the old paradigm, the universe was ensouled: “There is no philosopher enjoying some reputation … who does not hold that the world and its spheres are animated in some way.” (1584a/1998: 42) Perhaps this is an exaggeration, yet he rightly acknowledges that panpsychism runs deep in Western philosophy. He then emphasizes the central aspect of ancient and medieval panpsychism: It is not only the world-soul that is animate, but all things individually are animate too. This view is reiterated in De magia (On Magic), in which the souls of individual things are at once distinct yet connected to the universal soul:

It is manifest … that every soul and spirit hath a certain continuity with the spirit of the universe. … The power of each soul is itself somehow present afar in the universe [and is] exceedingly connected and attached thereto. (in Singer 1950: 90–91)

In De la causa Bruno explicitly and concisely summarizes his view that “not only the form of the universe, but also all the forms of natural things are souls” (1584a/1998: 42). Thus he generalizes Aristotle’s idea—that soul is the form of living bodies—to all physical bodies.

Interestingly, Bruno then acknowledges the unconventionality of this view. The character Dicsono says “Common sense tells us that not everything is alive. … Who will agree with you?” Teofilo, speaking for the author, replies “But who could reasonably refute it?” In the manner of Patrizi’s criticism, Bruno offers a “proof” that focuses on the world-soul and the parts of the universe that are possessed by it. Again, Aristotle attributes soul to the stars and other heavenly bodies. Bruno, like Patrizi, considered it terribly inconsistent to hold that certain parts of the cosmos are privileged to have a soul and others are not. Thus, in keeping with his rule that the same laws apply throughout the universe, he logically concludes that all things, all “parts,” must be animated: “There is nothing that does not possess a soul and that has no vital principle.” (43)^6

A skeptical Polinnio retorts “Then a dead body has a soul? So, my clogs, my slippers, my boots … are supposedly animated?” Teofilo (Bruno) clarifies his position by explaining that such “dead” things are not necessarily to be considered animate in themselves, but rather as containing elements that either are themselves animate or have the innate power of animation:

I say, then, that the table is not animated as a table, nor are the clothes as clothes … but that, as natural things and composites, they have within them matter and form [i.e. soul]. All things, no matter how small and minuscule, have in them part of that spiritual substance. … For in all things there is spirit, and there is not the least corpuscle that does not contain within itself some portion that may animate it. (44)

This distinction anticipates the views of both Leibniz and the twentieth-century process philosophers—Whitehead, Hartshorne, Griffin, et al.—who also deny mind to inanimate material objects but grant it to atoms, molecules, cells, and other so-called “true individuals.”^7

Bruno’s line of thinking hints at the Indwelling Powers argument of Plato and the pre-Socratics. Matter either is animate outright or has the power of animation. We get a further indication of this standpoint when Bruno speaks of “the spirit, the soul, the life which penetrates all, is in all, and moves all matter.” As with the Greeks, soul has the power not only of animation but also of motion. This power is visible in the motion of the Earth, the stars, and other worlds, which have souls and are moved by them. In pressing his case that the Earth is ensouled, he even makes a passing reference to a version of the Continuity argument when he compares the structure of the Earth to that of a human being: “it is evident that waters exist within the earth’s viscera even as within us are humors and blood” (1584b/1950: 315).

Two other aspects of Bruno’s thought are relevant here. The first is his concept of the monad. He clearly was an atomist, and he believed that there existed some ultimately small and simple element of matter; he referred to these variously as atoms, minima, or monads. Unfortunately, he was not entirely clear or consistent in his definitions of these ultimates. Sometimes the monads are material entities (“the substance for the building of all bodies is the minimum body or the atom”—De minimo, in Singer 1950: 74). Other times they are something more ephemeral and mysterious; Singer describes them as “a philosophical rather than a material conception” and says that they “have in them some of the qualities of the whole” (72). Hoeffding (1908: 138) states that monads are “also active force, soul, and will.” The monad is not only an ultimate element of smallness; it is more generally a unity, and may equally apply to large-scale objects. Hoeffding elaborates: “[T]he sun with its whole planetary system is a minimum in relation to the universe. Indeed, even the whole universe is called a monad. … The world-soul too, even God himself, is called a monad.” (138–139) Bruno is sometimes credited with creating the concept of the monad, but the philosophical usage of the term goes back at least to Plato—‘monad’ derives from monas (“unity”). Plato’s younger contemporary Xenocrates made the monad a first principle of metaphysics, and identified it with a self-contemplating intellect or nous.^8

The other important topic is Bruno’s theory of matter. He saw matter as a single substance that exhibited two modes: potenza (“power”) and soggetto (“subjectivity”). The power aspect of matter is revealed in its potential to act—that is, to exist or to be. Being is power, and power is the material aspect of matter—a clear connection to the concept of energy. Bruno’s other mode, subjectivity, can be seen as a manifestation of the soul in matter. Subjectivity determines the inherent nature of a thing, and distinguishes it uniquely from all other things. In short, potenza and soggetto represent the physical and mental modes of matter, respectively. Such a dual-aspect ontology is again a form of dualistic panpsychism, and it anticipates the later developments of Campanella, Spinoza, Schopenhauer, and others.

Bruno had a substantial influence on subsequent philosophers. Leibniz is a clear successor, particularly with his own conception of monads that so closely resembles Bruno’s.^9 Spinoza, Goethe, Herder, and Schelling all were influenced by Bruno’s system.^10 Even his implication of the will as an aspect of the monad anticipated the important advances of Campanella, Leibniz, Schopenhauer, Hartmann, and Nietzsche.

3.3 Gilbert and the Soul of the Magnet

Renaissance naturalism was not the only development in panpsychist philosophy in sixteenth-century Europe. Also of significance was De magnete (On the Magnet), by William Gilbert (1540–1603). Often deemed the first modern scientific work, De magnete is a detailed and technical study of magnets and their properties. In it he sought to summarize and clarify all previous knowledge of lodestones, from the time of Thales on. He introduced the concept of magnetic poles and showed how they align with the poles of the Earth. Most of Gilbert’s experiments were performed on a spherical lodestone that he called a Terella, or “little Earth.” He demonstrated that this little Earth duplicated the properties of the real Earth, and he correctly argued that the lodestone was given its power by the Earth—the natural field of the Earth magnetizes certain iron ores in the crust. Galileo was much impressed by Gilbert’s work, calling it “great to a degree that is enviable.”^11

From a panpsychist point of view, the most striking thing about De magnete is Gilbert’s Thalesian attribution of soul and other mental traits to magnets. Writing on the attractive power, he refers to the “friendship of iron for the lodestone” (1600/1958: 50). In noting that a magnet can magnetize a neutral piece of iron—in fact, limitless pieces—by mere contact, Gilbert refers to it as an awakening: “the dormant power of one is awakened by the other’s without expenditure” (62). He sees the powers of the magnet as evidence of “reason” in a stone, just as the Greeks saw reason as guiding the movements of planets and stars. In possessing reason, the magnet is something akin to the human being:

[I]f among [material] bodies one sees [anything whatsoever] that moves and breathes and has senses and is governed and impelled by reason, will he not, knowing and seeing this, say that here is a man, or something more like man than a stone or a stalk? (66)

Near the end of De magnete, Gilbert makes his view clear: “the magnetic force is animate, or imitates a soul; in many respects it surpasses the human soul” (308). Furthermore, just as the magnetic force is transferrable, he believed that soul was likewise given by one body to another—that the soul of the Earth was transferred to all earthly objects, whether animal, plant, or mineral. In the end, he characterizes the magnetic force as the single clear piece of scientific evidence that all objects, especially planets and stars, have souls and minds: “we deem the whole world [universe] animate, and all globes, all stars, and this glorious earth, too” (309). For this reason, Gilbert, like Bruno and Patrizi, assailed the logical inconsistency of Aristotle. The Aristotelian cosmology was a “monstrous creation, in which all [celestial] things are perfect, vigorous, animate, while the earth alone, luckless small fraction, is imperfect, dead, inanimate, and subject to decay.”

Gilbert doesn’t provide much more in the way of philosophical argumentation for his view, evidently believing that the amazing powers of magnets and the magnetic force are sufficient proof. But he does briefly touch on some of the standard arguments. He cites the ancient notion that “not without a divine and animate nature could movements [of stars and planets] so diverse be produced.” He claims that the celestial bodies are perfect and must therefore necessarily have souls because “nothing is excellent, nor precious, nor eminent, that hath not a soul.” He notes that the Earth and the sun can give their magnetic soul power to other objects, and consequently “it is not likely that they can do that which is not in themselves; but they awaken souls, and consequently are themselves possessed of souls” (Non-Emergence). And the mere fact that one magnet has the power to magnetize and thus ensoul another piece of metal is a form of the Indwelling Powers argument. It is significant that Gilbert, acknowledged as one of the first modern scientists, relied on panpsychist ideas in formulating his explanation of empirical phenomena.^12

3.4 Campanella and the Seventeenth Century

Moving into thought that is more representative of the 1600s, we find an emerging scientific and objectivist worldview competing with the naturalistic and panpsychic theories of the Renaissance. The early rationalism and empiricism led the departure from Scholasticism and Church orthodoxy. This new rationalism of the sixteenth century was still open to panpsychist interpretations of the cosmos. But by the seventeenth century it began to harden into an objectivist and mechanistic worldview.

With respect to philosophy of mind, the 1600s were dominated by two of the most notable panpsychist philosophers in history, Spinoza and Leibniz. Additionally, I will examine the question of pansensism as discussed by Bacon and Hobbes. Also of note are the ideas of some lesser-known yet important figures, including Margaret Cavendish and Henry More. Even Locke and Newton made some interesting statements along panpsychist lines. The beginning of the seventeenth century was marked, though, by the culmination of Renaissance naturalism in the philosophy of Tommaso Campanella.

Campanella (1568–1639) was perhaps the last great Renaissance philosopher. His philosophy was marked by a strong opposition to Aristotle and an equally strong embrace of Telesio. His two major works—De sensu rerum et magia (On the Sense in Things and Magic), written in 1590 but not published until 1620, and Metafisica, published in 1638—both contained detailed and explicit arguments for panpsychism. Like the other Renaissance naturalists, Campanella emphasized an empirical approach to knowledge, but not in the restricted sense of the British empiricists. Rather, he combined experiential knowledge of nature with metaphysical first principles to form a complete philosophical system that was centered on his theory of the three “primalities” that were at the core of his panpsychism. That doctrine, one of the more original elements of his philosophy, pervades his entire system of thought. It claims that the essence of being consists of three fundamental principles: power, wisdom (or knowledge, or sense), and love (or will). Such characteristics had long been attributed to God—in the form of omnipotence, omniscience, and omni-benevolence. Campanella was the first to make them universally applicable. For him, they are aspects of all things, from God on down to the humblest bit of stone.

Power (potentia) has three connotations: the power to be (potentia essendi), the power to act (potentia activa), and the power to be acted upon (potentia passiva). The power to be is the first and the foremost of these, as it is the source of all existence. Without the potentia essendi a thing simply would not exist. Furthermore, existence demands the ongoing presence of this power in order to allow persistence through time. The powers to act and to be acted upon are related to Campanella’s theory of knowledge, and involve the ability to communicate the likeness of one thing to another, as will be discussed below.

The notion that power is the preeminent principle of existence is an advance from the Telesian conception of Heat and Cold, but it retains the essential reference to the idea of energy. And energy and power were virtually synonymous in the sixteenth century, long before power was defined as the rate of change of energy over time. Also, the potentia essendi anticipates certain very recent aspects of systems theory, particularly the idea of a “dissipative structure” as an entity that requires power, or energy expenditure, to maintain its existence.

The second primality, wisdom or knowledge, is explicitly mental. Campanella argues that, because all things sense, they can be said to know, and consequently to possess a kind of wisdom. First and foremost, things know themselves. Each thing knows of its own existence and its own persistence over time: “All things have the sensation of their own being and of their conservation. They exist, are conserved, operate, and act because they know.”^13 Hoeffding (1908: 153) explains it this way: “Every individual being has an ‘original hidden thought’ of itself, which is one with its nature.” The same idea is explicit in the lengthy subtitle of Campanella’s De sensu rerum:

A remarkable tract of occult philosophy in which the world is shown to be a living and truly conscious image of God, and all its parts and particles thereof to be endowed with sense perception, some more clearly, some more obscurely, to the extent required for the preservation of themselves and of the whole in which they share sensation. (1620; in Bonansea 1969: 156)

This “remarkable” subtitle captures many aspects of his philosophy in a single sentence.

Campanella offered a number of arguments in support of his primality of wisdom and the attendant panpsychism. Several tend to take the form of definitional arguments or an appeal to first principles—for example, that knowledge is required for self-preservation, and hence all things must have active power—but he also employed the ancient Non-Emergence argument:

[I]f the animals are sentient … and sense does not come from nothing, the elements whereby they and everything else are brought into being must be said to be sentient, because what the result has the cause must have. Therefore the heavens are sentient, and so [too] the earth … . (1620; in Dooley 1995: 39)

Campanella did, however, introduce a new form of the Design argument for panpsychism, one that explicitly incorporates theology. He claims that, in the words of Bonansea,

all beings … carry within themselves the image or vestige of God and are essentially related to one another … . [God clearly possesses sensation and wisdom, and so] sensation is therefore to be extended to all beings. (1969: 157)

It is significant that Campanella saw all things as participating in God, and thus sharing his qualities. In fact, the theological argument applies to all three primalities: “Campanella holds that God … in effusing Himself into creatures, communicates to them power, knowledge [wisdom], and love, so that they may exist.” (145) It is interesting that Campanella, a devout Christian, looked to God as justification for his panpsychism. Perhaps he thought this would placate the Inquisition. Unfortunately for him, it did not. The Church was beginning to feel the pressure of the new naturalist philosophy, and so it struck back hard. At about the same time that Bruno was burned alive, Campanella, at the age of 32, was imprisoned by church authorities; he served 27 years for his beliefs. Fortunately he was able to continue writing, and even to smuggle out some complete manuscripts.

Campanella’s third primality, love, is a consequence of the primality of wisdom; things love existence, and such love follows naturally from self-knowledge. He explains it in Metafisica:

Beings exist not only because they have the power to be and know that they are, but also because they love [their own] being. Did they not love [it], they would not be so anxious to defend it … . All things would either be chaos or they would be entirely destroyed. Therefore love, not otherwise than power and wisdom, seems to be a principle of being … . (1638, in Bonansea, 162)

Thus it is clear that the three primalities are intimately linked. The primality of knowledge, for example, acts through the primality of power. The power to be acted upon represents the reception of an essence, the transfer of something from the object to the knower. The object is able to surrender this essence by its power to act. This essence is captured by the knower, is incorporated into its being, and is thereby changed. It is this change that constitutes knowledge. “Every sense,” says Campanella, “is a change in the sentient body” (1620, in Dooley 1995: 49). This change is not arbitrary. By incorporating an essence of the object, the knower becomes like the object. Assimilation occurs. Thus, knower and known merge, at least in part. To know something is to become like it.

Cassirer (1927/1963: 148) noted that such an epistemology entails a joint sharing of a common essence, and that furthermore a panpsychist theory of mind naturally follows:

[T]his unity [of knower and known] is only possible if the subject and object, the knower and known, are of the same nature; they must be members and parts of one and the same vital complex. Every sensory perception is an act of fusion and reunification. We perceive the object, we grasp it in its proper, genuine being only when we feel in it the same life, the same kind of movement and animation that is immediately given and present to us in the experiencing of our own Ego. From this, Panpsychism emerges as a simple corollary to [Campanella’s] theory of knowledge … .

Campanella has been revered throughout history as a man of powerful intellect and insight. In his own time he was acknowledged for his depth of thought. Battaglino called him “one of the rarest geniuses of Italy,” and Brancadoro exclaimed that “in him all fiery and most subtle powers are glowing and excel in the utmost degree.” Leibniz ranked him with Bacon, Hobbes, and Descartes.^14 He remains, along with Bruno, an outstanding exemplar of Renaissance naturalism, and together they mark the turning point from a medieval, dogmatic, theological worldview to that of modern science and rationalism.^15

3.5 The Early Scientific Philosophers

Campanella lived at precisely the time when scientific philosophy was first being formulated. Nearly the same age as Bacon (b. 1561) and Galileo (b. 1564), he created his naturalistic vision contemporaneously with their materialist and objectivist philosophy. Some intellectuals were able to accommodate both. Gilbert, as I have shown, integrated science and panpsychism. Johannes Kepler (1571–1630) saw soul as the force behind the movements of the celestial bodies, at least for the better part of his life. His first substantial work, Mysterium cosmographicum (1596), held to “the traditional conception of force as a soul animating the celestial bodies” (Jammer 1957: 82). The somewhat later De stella nova (1606) includes this comment:

Those motive powers of the stars share in some way in the capacity of thought, so that, as it were, they understand, imagine, and aim at their path—not of course by means of ratiocination like us human beings but by an innate impulse implanted in them from the beginning of Creation. (in Jung and Pauli 1952/1955: 173)

In 1609, Kepler published Astronomia nova, in which he discussed the “true doctrine of gravity” and noted that, wherever the Earth moved in space, heavy objects were always attracted to the Earth’s center “thanks to the faculty animating it” (85). He likened this animating force of gravity, which he called a species immateriata, to the animate force of magnets. In 1610 he claimed that gravity was identical to the magnetic force: “The planets are magnets and are driven around by the sun by magnetic force.” (89)

These themes continued in Kepler’s Harmonies of the World (1618). The epilogue (section 10) contains passages relating to the solar mind. He believed that the periodic and rational movements of the planets were “the object of some mind” (1618/1995: 240). He noted that “it is not easy for dwellers on the Earth to conjecture … what mind there is in the sun” (240–241). Yet, he asserted, mind in the sun followed as a necessary explanation of the “solar harmonies of movements”:

For as the sun rotating into itself moves all the planets by means of the form emitted from itself, so too … mind, by understanding itself and in itself all things, stirs up ratiocinations, and by dispersing and unrolling its simplicity into them, makes everything to be understood. (244)

The solar mind is the source of the harmonies: “there dwells in the sun simple intellect, pyr noeron, or nous, the source, whatsoever it may be, of every harmony.”

In 1621, at the age of 50, Kepler changed his mind. He decided that ‘force’ was a better term than ‘soul’. He concluded that gravitational attraction was something physical rather than supernatural:

Formerly I believed that the cause of the planetary motion is a soul. … But when I realized that these motive causes attenuate with the distance from the sun, I came to the conclusion that this force is something corporeal, if not so properly, at least in a certain sense. (90)

This is a remarkably frank and revealing admission. Because gravity decreases (regularly but non-linearly) with distance, it is a function of spatial dimension, and therefore it is of the physical world—hence, it cannot be soul. There is a deep implication here: Any entity that exhibits regularity in space or time must be physical in nature, and therefore cannot be mental or spiritual. In Kepler’s day, soul and mind were by definition mysterious and immaterial, lacking all tangibility and regularity. Any phenomenon that would admit to mathematization must necessarily be natural, physical, corporeal. This is in striking contrast to the view of the ancient Greeks. They saw regularity of motion as a clear indication of reason at work, and hence of soul in the cosmos. Kepler took the very same empirical phenomenon and came to the opposite conclusion: that mechanistic forces were the causal factors.

This, then, was the beginning of the mechanistic worldview—the mathematization of natural phenomena. Galileo took this up in earnest, and greatly advanced scientific philosophy. The natural philosophers, emboldened by their successes, soon sought mathematical descriptions everywhere. As a consequence, they began to push spiritual explanations to the sidelines. Materialist and mechanistic philosophy began to dominate Western thinking.

Two of the first materialist philosophers of the modern era were Francis Bacon (1561–1626) and Thomas Hobbes (1588–1679). Both lived during the transition from naturalistic panpsychism to scientific materialism. Both were born in the sixteenth century, but their writing and thinking were more allied to the seventeenth. Bacon was seven years younger than Campanella and was certainly aware of the panpsychist and pansensist philosophies that were circulating on the Continent, and of Gilbert’s De magnete.

Bacon could not abide the view that all things sense. For him, that ability was something that only livings things possessed. However, he was willing to admit that everything had some ability to perceive the local environment and to feel (though he did not use that word) temperature and force. Perception was, for him, a quality that all material objects possessed. Such a pan-perceptivist philosophy comes notably close to pansensism, and Bacon took care in spelling out his view in his Natural History (also called Silva Silvarum). In the early 1620s, near the end of his life, he wrote the following in introducing section IX of the aforementioned work:

It is certain that all bodies whatsoever, though they have no sense, yet they have perception; for when one body is applied to another, there is a kind of election to embrace that which is agreeable, and to exclude or expel that which is ingrate; and whether the body be alterant or altered, evermore a perception precedeth operation; for else all bodies would be alike one to another.

And sometimes this perception, in some kind of bodies, is far more subtle than the [human] sense; so that the sense is but a dull thing in comparison of it: we see a weatherglass will find the least difference of the weather in heat or cold, when men find it not. And this perception is sometimes at distance … as when the lodestone draweth iron. … It is therefore a subject of very noble inquiry, to inquire of the more subtle perceptions; for it is another key to open nature, as well as the [human] sense; and sometimes better. … It serveth to discover that which is hid.

Clearly, perception is a quality that is comparable to human sense, though “more subtle” and more mysterious. It clearly merits study, but Bacon seems not to know how to tackle the issue. He is not so bold as to predict that all phenomena will yield to materialist interpretations.

Hobbes, also aware of the pansensist philosophers, takes up their challenge in his 1655 work De corpore (On the Body).^16 He first defines sense as “motion in some of the internal parts of the sentient; and the parts so moved are parts of the organs of sense.” This is a relatively accurate description of some sort of stimulus, such as light or sound, impinging on a sense organ and generating a nerve signal that moves through the body to the brain. He then confines sensation to living organisms: “The subject of sense is the sentient itself, namely, some living creature.” Then in section 5 he writes:

But though all sense, as I have said, be made by reaction, nevertheless it is not necessary that everything that reacteth should have sense. I know that there have been philosophers, and those learned men, who have maintained that all bodies are endued with sense. Nor do I see how they can be refuted, if the nature of sense be placed in reaction only. And, though by the reaction of bodies inanimate a phantasm [sensation] might be made, it would nevertheless cease, as soon as ever the object [causing the sensation] were removed. For unless those bodies had organs, as living creatures have, fit for the retaining of such motion as is made in them, their sense would be such, as that they should never remember the same … . For by ‘sense’, we [mean] … the comparing and distinguishing [of] phantasms. … Wherefore sense … hath necessarily some memory adhering to it.

Thus, like Bacon, Hobbes confronted the doctrine of pansensism that was associated with Telesio and Campanella.

Not uncoincidentally, it was also in De corpore that Hobbes first used the concept of conatus, meaning “striving” or “endeavor,” to refer to “all motion in general” (Herbert 1989: 64). If conatus is taken as an intentional quantity, then something mind-like inheres in all motion, and thus in all matter. But the degree to which Hobbes held that view is unclear.^17

Hobbes recognized that the validity of pansensism hinges on the definition of “sense.” If sensing means only reaction, then he concedes that all things sense—this much is obvious. But he adds an additional condition: To sense requires memory, something only living organisms are presumably capable of. That qualification recalls Telesio’s claim that memory, along with sensation, is central to a proper conception of the soul.

However, the concept of memory may not be as transparent as Hobbes suggests. He seems to refer to a humanistic conception of memory, but there is no logical reason why the concept cannot be extended to general physical systems. A generalized conception of memory has at least two components: the ability to record experiences and the ability to replay or project them into the future. Humans record experiences through morphological changes in the brain, and then are able to replay them internally and to relate them externally via muscular action and language. Generalized memory requires, first of all, a permanent—or at least temporally persistent—change in the sensing body. That such a change occurs to all physical objects seems clear. Everything degrades and wears down to some extent, depending on the forces experienced. Ancient documents, fossils, rocks, and even planetary fragments can be dated with reasonable precision because of the permanent, cumulative record that all things acquire. This is a form of memory.

Furthermore, since physical objects do not communicate in the human sense, one may say that a form of memory exists if the record of experiences is present and available to an outside observer. Humans clearly can detect and measure physical changes over eons, and thus in this way the record of experience is replayed. Many changes are more subtle and may not be detectable with present technology. But this doesn’t alter the fact that all experiences are recorded and can theoretically be recovered.

Other thinkers have observed that inanimate objects can in fact display a kind of memory. William James, commenting on Fechner’s analysis of natural events, wrote:

[T]he event works back upon the background, as the wavelet works upon the waves, or as the leaf’s movements work upon the sap inside the branch. The whole sea and the whole tree are registers of what has happened, and are different for the wave’s and the leaf’s action having occurred. (1909: 171–172)

Henry David Thoreau’s book Wild Fruits contains a similar observation of the apple:

It will have some red stains, commemorating the mornings and evenings it has witnessed; some dark and rusty blotches, in memory of the clouds and foggy, mildewy days that have passed over it; and a spacious field of green reflecting the general face of Nature … . (2000: 87)

Bertrand Russell made comparable remarks in his Outline of Philosophy (1927b). After stating that memory is “the most essential characteristic of mind” (153), he cited an example of memory in “inorganic matter”:

A watercourse which at most times is dry gradually wears a channel down a gully at the times when it flows, and subsequent rains follow [the same] course. … You may say, if you like, that the river bed “remembers” previous occasions when it experienced cooling streams … . (155)

Logically, even other, more subtle perceptions—such as a gentle breeze, or the shadow of a hand on a leaf—also affect the system of a tree permanently, though such changes may be utterly undetectable. Henri Bergson further elaborated the philosophy of memory, defining it as the decisive factor in the graded transition from matter to mind; for an extended discussion, see his Matiere et Memoire (1896). Given a generalized conception of memory, then, it seems that a Hobbesian argument could support a pansensist or panpsychist view.

A final clue to Hobbes’ beliefs comes from the autobiographical essay The Prose Life (1677). Recalling an earlier episode in which he was challenged about the nature of sensation, he remarks: “From that time, [I] devoted [myself] to determining the nature of the senses, disputing whether corporeal body and all its parts were inert, or in a state of continuous movement, and (in consequence) totally sensate.”^18 The passage is ambiguous but suggests that sensation is an intrinsic property of motion. But again, if the sensation is lost because of a lack of memory, it can have no functional value.

The last great philosophical figure born in the sixteenth century was René Descartes (b. 1596). His ontological dualism of mind and body, arising from his technique of methodical doubt, set the emerging scientific, mechanistic worldview on a track that it would follow for the next 400 years and beyond. The Cartesian system was rationalist to the core and pragmatic in intent. The non-human world was utterly aspiritual, without mind and without reason. Humanity was radically different from the other objects of the material universe, and stood alone in an isolated sphere, privileged in the eyes of God. Nothing close to panpsychism was conceivable in such a world.

Henry More (1614–1687) is perhaps the best-known of the “Cambridge Platonists,” a group that included Ralph Cudworth. A theist and an idealist, More came of age just as Cartesianism and the scientific philosophy began to implicitly threaten the philosophical standing of Christian theology. He was concerned that Descartes’ dualism implied a mechanistic universe that could operate without any intervention from God. At the same time, the pantheistic philosophy of Spinoza arose—a radical monism in which a non-Christian, non-personal God was immediately present everywhere. Neither of these options was acceptable to More.

More’s response was to suppose the existence of an intermediary force, the “Spirit of Nature,” that animated all matter on behalf of God.^19 Matter in itself was inert, but the universal presence of the Spirit of Nature—which More described as “the vicarious Power of God upon Matter”—endowed all things with an internal animating principle. “The primordials of the world are not mechanical but spermatical or vital … , which some moderns call the Spirit of Nature.” Following Aristotle, this Spirit was seen to give form to all material things. It relieved God from the burden of continuous intervention and it saved the cosmos from an atheistic mechanism. It had numerous powers, including “self-penetration, self-motion, self-contraction and -dilation, and indivisibility,”^20 but the power of thought or reason was not among them.

Hence, More’s position qualifies as a quasi-panpsychism. It is interesting and relevant because it served as a direct spiritual response to the emerging materialist worldview and because More relied on theological arguments to support his view of spirit in matter, in a way comparable to Campanella. It also reflected the continuing influence of Plato and the concept of the world-soul.

Ultimately, More’s theory failed, largely because it attempted to defeat science on its own terms. As Greene says (1962: 461), “it becomes increasingly obvious that More’s attribution of function to the Spirit of Nature is highly arbitrary, and that it is a catch-all for the inexplicable.” Robert Boyle, famous for his attacks on the Cambridge school’s fuzzy metaphysical notions, complained that

[such agents] as the soul of the world, the universal spirit, the plastic power … tell us nothing that will satisfy the curiosity of an inquisitive person, who seeks to know … by what means, and after what manner, the phaenomenon is produced. (1674, in Bonifazi 1978: 68)

Finally, two of More’s contemporaries merit brief discussion. One of them is the physician Francis Glisson (1599–1677). Though most of his work was on medicine and human physiology, Glisson wrote a significant philosophical monograph, Treatise on the Energetic Nature of Substance, in 1672. Henry (1987: 16) calls it “one of the most original systems of philosophy” of the time and “one of the most profound attempts to develop a monistic solution to the mind-body problem.” And for present purposes, it makes the case for a strongly panpsychist ontology.

Glisson developed a theory of matter as composed of atom-like particles called minima naturalia. When coming together to form large-scale objects, these minima “communicate with each other” in a deliberate and conative manner; they “strive to adhere to each other due to a certain intrinsic property.” Employing explicitly panpsychist language, Glisson writes:

The particles, by perceiving the utility through which they enjoy their communion amongst themselves, love and desire this communion, and consequently they strive to maintain it—that is, they strive to adhere to each other in such a way that internal cohesion itself is nothing other than a movement or striving resulting from continuity, through which nature strives to conserve itself. Therefore, by means of natural perception and appetite, the cohesion is firstly based on continuity. (in Giglioni 2002: 250–252)

The various parts of objects thus seek to retain their connection and wholeness: “Here again we see nature perceiving the usefulness of its own parts, and loving them and striving (conatur) to defend them with all its strength.” As Giglioni sees it, this is a more modern and sophisticated form of panpsychism; for Glisson,

Substance is alive because it is capable of perceiving … . Therefore, if substance is essentially activity, activity is essentially perception, but natural perception … . Natural perception … founds the life of nature (vita naturae) without falling back again into the traditional aporias of animism and anthropocentrism. (2002: 254)

There is no divine Spirit of Nature at work here; matter is intrinsically perceptive and aware. God plays no role at all. It is a fundamentally naturalistic panpsychism.

The other person of note for purposes of the present discussion is Margaret Cavendish, Duchess of Newcastle (1623–1673). A poet and playwright, Cavendish also produced three major works on natural philosophy: Philosophical Letters, Observations upon Experimental Philosophy, and Grounds of Natural Philosophy. She advocated a form of materialism in which the cosmos was an organic whole composed of organic and animate parts. Her organicist materialism was offered in response to purely mechanistic materialism of the sort that Hobbes and Descartes had articulated.

Cavendish followed the thinking of the Stoics and the Renaissance naturalists in arguing that all of nature was alive and intelligent: “there is life and knowledge in all parts of nature, … and this life and knowledge is sense and reason” (Letter 30, 1664/1994: 26). She distinguished between two types of matter, the animate and the inanimate, which were mixed together in all material objects: “my opinion is, that all matter is partly animate, and partly inanimate, … and that there is no part of nature that hath not life and knowledge, for there is no part that has not a commixture of animate and inanimate matter” (25). Such properties were to be extended to the smallest portions of matter. As Perry recounts (1968: 185–186), Cavendish “felt that the world could not be made of atoms unless each one had life and knowledge.”

Animate matter was distinct from the inanimate in its capability for self-motion. It moved itself, and by physical connection it in turn moved the inanimate matter: “the animate moves of itself, and the inanimate moves by the help of the animate” (Letter 30: 26). Thus the motion of all physical objects was to be explained by reference to their animate portion. The intelligence in both forms of matter was realized as a kind of knowledge, initially in terms of self-knowledge and, ultimately, as a knowledge of God:

All parts of Nature, even the inanimate, have an innate and fixt self-knowledge, [and] it is probable that they may also have an interior self-knowledge of the existency of the Eternal and Omnipotent God, as the Author of Nature. (1655/1991: 8)

Cavendish’s metaphysical system was more poetic than analytic, but she established new standards for intellectual women of the seventeenth century. Her depiction of a compassionate and animate world provided inspiration to later feminist philosophers^21 and complemented the work of her male contemporaries.^22

3.6 Spinoza

Baruch Spinoza (1632–1677) sought a holistic interpretation of the cosmos. He created a unified ontology in which all phenomena, including the mental and the physical, are bound together in a single comprehensive picture. In this sense he reflected the inclinations of the Renaissance naturalists Cardano and Bruno. However, he lived in an era of new rationalism, led by Descartes—who was 36 years his senior—and in an era of emerging scientific materialist philosophy, led by Bacon, Galileo, and Hobbes. In addition, the religious theology of the day still held considerable influence and affected the thinking and writing of many intellectuals. Spinoza’s approach to unity took on aspects of all these influences; in Ethics (1677),^23 he built a logical, even mathematical case for the unity of God and nature, and of mind and matter—a case that incorporated the concept of the universal law.

Spinoza’s approach in Ethics was “geometrical” in the sense that it relied on a system of arguments patterned after mathematical formalism. Such a methodology was novel in philosophy, largely owing to the influence of Cartesian thinking.^24 But beyond pure methodology, Spinoza believed that mathematics could lead to true insight into the nature of reality. Mathematical formalism, he believed, reflected ontological formalism.

In his view, all of reality consists of a single substance, called “God” or “Nature” depending on the context and circumstances. Resurrecting the ancient pantheism of Plato and the Stoics, Spinoza saw God as the sum total of physical reality, the universe and everything in it constituting the substance of God. God was not a transcendent being, not a personal being, not a moral being, but simply the totality of existence.

This radical monism has to account for the apparent plurality of things in the world, and especially for the classes of things that we commonly call mental and physical. Spinoza proposes that the one substance, God/Nature, possesses infinitely many attributes. As limited beings, humans can perceive only the two primary attributes—those that he labels ‘extension’ (physical) and ‘thought’ (mental). Individual physical or mental entities, then, are considered modes or modifications of these attributes. A particular physical thing, such as an apple, is a “mode of extension,” and any specific mental event, such as a feeling of pain, is a “mode of thought.” The one substance God/Nature reveals itself to us through these two aspects. Hence Spinoza’s theory is appropriately described as a dual-aspect monism.

The two knowable attributes of extension and thought are distinct yet intimately related, as is to be expected in view of the underlying monism. They have, in fact, a very specific and fundamental connection: Every physical thing has a corresponding mental aspect, which Spinoza calls an “idea.” Conversely, every mental idea has a corresponding object, or thing. This is his unique brand of unity, known as psycho-physical parallelism: To every physical thing or event there corresponds an idea of that thing or event.^25

As the chain of physical events progresses in the world, there exists a parallel chain of mental events. These two chains of events track each other identically, one to one, and run forever in parallel. “The order and connection of ideas is the same as the order and connection of things.” (IIP7) Why? Because the thing and the corresponding idea are really the same thing—there is only one substance, after all:

[T]he thinking substance and the extended substance are one and the same substance, which is now comprehended under this attribute, now under that. So also a mode of extension [i.e. a particular thing] and the idea of that mode are one and the same thing, but expressed in two ways. (IIP7S)

It is incorrect to say that the chain of physical events causes the chain of ideas, or that the ideas cause changes in the physical events. There in fact is no causal connection between the two series at all. Causality is not even possible, because they are only two aspects of a single substance. There is no interaction, and hence no Cartesian interaction problem. This is a virtue of any monistic system.

Consider the special case of the human body. It is a particular physical thing, and thus a mode of extension. Corresponding to this mode, as to all modes, is an idea. The idea of the human body is not just some arbitrary mental entity; it is in fact the mind of that person: “The [physical] object of the idea constituting the human mind is the [human] body, or a certain mode of extension which actually exists, and nothing else.” (IIP13) Mind is the idea of body, and body is the object of mind.

Since the two aspects have no causal relationship, mind cannot affect body and body cannot affect mind. This is clearly stated in IIIP2: “The body cannot determine the mind to thinking, and the mind cannot determine the body to motion, to rest, or to anything else.” Yet for every body there is an associated mind. As the body changes, the mind changes in a corresponding way. They change together without causal interaction: “the mind and the body, are one and the same individual, which is conceived now under the attribute of thought, now under the attribute of extension” (IIP21S). So we see in Spinoza a metaphysical system in which we have a new way of comprehending the two realms of physical and mental. Each physical thing has an idea associated with it; conversely, every idea has a corresponding physical thing.

It is natural to think in terms of human beings, but Spinoza tells us that his method is “completely general.” His use of ‘body’, in fact, refers not just to a human body but to any physical object whatsoever. Hence the idea of any physical thing at all is in reality the mind of that thing. Every mode of extension has its corresponding mode of thought—or, in the simplest terms, every thing has a corresponding mind. Thus we arrive at Spinoza’s panpsychism. This is spelled out explicitly in the Scholium of proposition 13 in part II:

From these [propositions] we understand not only that the human mind is united to the body, but also what should be understood by the union of mind and body … . For the things we have shown so far are completely general and do not pertain more to man than to other individuals, all of which, though in different degrees, are nevertheless animate.

He then goes on to explain what he means by “different degrees”:

I say this in general, that in proportion as a body is more capable than others of doing many things at once, or being acted on in many ways at once, so its mind is more capable than others of perceiving many things at once.

Spinoza’s argument for panpsychism is often seen to rest solely on the Scholium of proposition 13, but this is not the case. There are at least three other claims for it. First, it is a logical consequence of propositions 3 and 11. Proposition 3 states that “in God there is necessarily an idea … of everything which necessarily follows from his essence,” i.e., all extant things. Hence all real things have ideas. Proposition 11 tells us that these ideas are minds. It does so not in general but by reference to the specific case of the human mind. Our mind is “nothing but the idea of a singular thing which actually exists,” i.e., some extant thing. (Proposition 13 informs us that this thing is nothing other than our body.) But it doesn’t matter what the particular singular thing is; what is relevant is that mind is the idea of some real thing. If minds are ideas, and all real things have ideas, then all real things have minds.

Further evidence can be found in proposition 1 of part III (“On the Affects”), where we find not so much an argument as a simple recognition that other things beside humans possess minds. Spinoza elaborates on the fact that humans have both “adequate” and “inadequate” ideas in their minds, and that either kind of idea is, however, adequate in God/Nature because “he also contains in himself, at the same time, the minds of other things.” Clearly the “other things” are non-human objects, and without reason to limit them, one must conclude that this covers all extant things.

Finally there is Spinoza’s doctrine of conatus, or striving. Part III observes that all things display a kind of effort or power toward maintaining existence—much along the line of Campanella’s potentia essendi. Like Campanella, Spinoza saw this striving as evidence of a vital or animate energy in things. The definitive passage is proposition 6: “Each thing, as far as it can by its own power, strives to persevere in its being.” Proposition 7 adds that this striving “is nothing but the actual essence of the thing.” And proposition 8 says that it is not merely occasional or sporadic but exists for “an indefinite time”; thus, striving is an eternal and essential aspect of any existing thing. In an earlier work—Descartes’ “Principles of Philosophy”—Spinoza defined life as “the force through which things persevere in their being.” Assuming that he maintained such a view through the Ethics, one can read the conatus doctrine as a form of hylozoism. This again would be consistent with a generally panpsychic outlook.

One further passage from Spinoza is worth mentioning here, though its status as a basis for panpsychism is unclear. In his 1674 letter to G. H. Schuller (letter 58), he elaborates on his theory of free will and determinism. By way of example, he cites the case of a stone that is “set in motion” through the air, as when thrown by someone. A stone set in motion is not unlike, say, a human set in motion; each moves through the world, reacting to various impulses and forces. Spinoza writes:

Next, conceive now, if you will that while the stone continues to move, it thinks, and knows that as far as it can, it strives to continue to move. Of course since the stone is conscious only of its striving, and not at all indifferent, it will believe itself to be free, and to persevere in motion for no other cause than because it wills to. And this is that famous human freedom which everyone brags of having … . (1674/1994: 267–268)

It is not clear whether he means to say that the stone does think and is conscious or whether this is merely a hypothetical example. His point here, of course, is to refute the notion of free will, not to examine the mind of a stone. But it is a suggestive passage nonetheless.^26

In view of the controversial status of panpsychism, it is perhaps unsurprising that many scholars have denied that Spinoza’s view is panpsychist. This is particularly true of commentaries published in the early and the middle years of the twentieth century. Of the early commentators, Joachim (1901) is the most neutral. But we find clearly hostile readings in Wolfson 1937 (ideas are really just “forms,” not minds), in Fuller 1945 (“ideas can scarcely be regarded as individual psychical entities, like souls or minds”), in Hampshire 1951 (“only humans have minds”), in Parkinson 1953 (that all things are animate is merely an inconsequential “curiosity”), and in Curley 1969 (ideas are just “true propositions”). Interestingly, though, later commentaries display a clear trend toward greater sympathy for the panpsychist interpretation. Pro-panpsychism readings are found in Harris 1973, in Bennett 1984, in Delahunty 1985, in Allison 1987, and in Curley 1988. Even Hampshire (2002) seems to have turned toward a more sympathetic interpretation.^27 Curley (1988: 64) seems to go so far as to argue for a kind of super-panpsychism in Spinoza, in which not only do extended, physical things have minds, but so too do modes of all the other unknowable attributes. Few Spinoza scholars seem to acknowledge this large-scale shift toward a panpsychist interpretation.

3.7 Locke and Newton

John Locke and Isaac Newton played central roles in advancing the materialist and mechanistic worldview, but both appear to have had lingering doubts about the relationship between matter and spirit. Apparently neither seemed completely confident that pure materialism could account for the phenomena of the natural world. Both seemed to be open to the possibility that matter might possess an intrinsic mental aspect.

Locke (1632–1704) is perhaps best known for his empiricism—especially as expounded in the Essay Concerning Human Understanding (1689), in which he lays out his views on morality, knowledge, and humans’ abilities to comprehend the world. The final book of the Essay contains a controversial passage on the relationship between mind and matter. Locke inquires into the question of how the human body, as a material object, is able to think. A point of interest to him is whether the material body has some kind of innate ability to think or whether divine intervention is necessary. Locke seems to have recognized the possibility that former position could lead to a version of panpsychism, and to have attempted to clarify the issue. In section 6 of chapter III of book IV (“The Extent of Human Knowledge”) he writes:

We have the ideas of matter and thinking, but possibly shall never be able to know whether any mere material being thinks or no; it being impossible for us … to discover whether Omnipotency has not given to some systems of matter, fitly disposed, a power to perceive and think, or else joined and fixed to matter … a thinking immaterial substance. … We know not wherein thinking consists, nor to what sort of substances the Almighty has been pleased to give that power. … For I see no contradiction in [that God] should, if he pleased, give to certain systems of created senseless matter … some degrees of sense, perception, and thought. … [No one can] have the confidence to conclude [that God] cannot give perception and thought to a substance which has the modification of solidity.

On the surface, this passage can be seen as an argument for the omnipotence of God: God can do anything at all and therefore can certainly grant the power of thought to mere matter, any matter. Locke doesn’t want to be seen limiting the power of God.

There is no obvious endorsement of panpsychism here. Locke makes no clear statement that “matter thinks,” or that “anything besides humans think.” On the other hand, he speaks of “matter,” and not, say, the “human body.” He sees “no contradiction” in the possibility that “certain systems of matter,” presumably including non-human ones, may have “some degrees of sense, perception, and thought.”

Locke is clear that matter has no inherent ability to think: Elsewhere in the same chapter, he claims that matter “is evidently in its own nature void of sense and thought,” and thus thinking, wherever it may occur, must come from God, who after all can place it anywhere he likes. So who is to say that God has not given other material objects, or even all objects, some degree of thought?

Locke seems to avoid committing himself to a position. Near the end of section 6 he claims agnosticism, stating that the issue of understanding how any material object can think is “a point which seems to be put out of reach of our knowledge” and that “we must content ourselves in the ignorance of what kind of being [the “thinking substance” in us] is … . [For after all], what substance exists, that has not something in it which manifestly baffles our understandings.” As a classical empiricist, Locke recognizes the impossibility of investigating the internal perceptions of the non-human mind. This is perhaps an indication that rationalist approaches are the more promising.

Newton (1642–1727) was not only a great scientist but also a philosopher of science. His Principia (1687) described the laws of gravity and the basic equations of force and motion. But he was concerned not only how to describe the actions of nature in terms of universal laws but also how to grasp the underlying meaning. He sought explanations as much as descriptions.

In the so-called Newtonian worldview, inert material objects move about under mechanistic forces in a clockwork fashion. Such a universe is commonly understood to be non-spiritual, if not outright atheistic in its physical dimension. However true this may be of modern depictions, it was certainly not the view of Newton, as he was a profoundly religious and spiritual man. His belief that God was immanent in the universe and actively involved in its state of affairs is one of the few consistent threads in his philosophy.

Furthermore, Newton had serious doubts about viewing matter as dead and inert. In fact, he seems to have had a strong inclination to view all matter as living, and even as possessing mind-like qualities. McRae (1981) conducted a brief but interesting study along this line, based largely on a detailed investigation by McGuire (1968) of Newton’s post-Principia writings. McRae states very directly that “Newton had no objection to hylozoism [and] indeed, appears to have been powerfully attracted to [it]” (191). The basis for this can be found in a draft variant of Query 22 in the 1706 work Optice:

For Bodies … are passive … . They cannot move themselves; and without some other principle than the vis inertiae [inertial force] there could be no motion in the world … . And if there be another Principle of motion there must be other laws of motion depending on that Principle … . We find in ourselves a power of moving our bodies by our thoughts … and see [the] same power in other living creatures but how this is done and by what laws we do not know … . It appears that there are other laws of motion … [and this is] enough to justify and encourage our search after them. We cannot say that all nature is not alive. (in McGuire 1968: 170–171)

The final sentence is fairly astonishing, especially in view of Newton’s traditional mechanistic image.

Other passages confirm this hylozoist inclination. As early as the Principia Newton acknowledges the existence of two states of force (later, two principles): passive (or “resistance”) and active (or “impulse”). This apparent connection with Stoic philosophy is no coincidence; he had studied ancient philosophy and was undoubtedly influenced by Stoicism.^28 Definition III of book I of the Principia discusses the vis inertiae, or inertial force of a static body. When experiencing an external force, he writes, the vis inertiae exerts itself in two ways:

as both resistance [passive] and impulse [active]; it is resistance so far as the body … opposes the force impressed; it is impulse so far as the body, by not easily giving way to the impressed force … , endeavors to change the state of that other.

The vis inertiae actively exerts an effort; it acts back on the force, and attempts to change it. There is an implied notion of will or agency here.

Stoicism associated life, mind, and soul with the active principle. Newton seems to have done likewise. In the Optice, in draft Query 23, he challenges the notion that nature has only a passive inert principle:

[T]o affirm that there are no other [laws beside “passive”] is to speak against experience. For we find in ourselves a power of moving our bodies by our thought. Life and Will (thinking) are active Principles by which we move our bodies, and thence arise other laws of motion unknown to us.

[I]f there be an universal life, and all space be the sensorium of a immaterial living, thinking, being, … [then] the laws of motion arising from life or will may be of universal extent. (in McGuire 1968: 171, 205)

For Newton it was not only the vis inertiae that animated matter. Some time after 1706, he hit upon the idea that electricity might be the main force acting at small distances. Further, he felt that in this might lie a new universal principle, which McGuire describes as “an electrical arche connecting mind with matter” (176). Newton made this clear in Quest 25:

Do not all bodies therefore abound with a very subtile, active, potent, electric spirit by which light is emitted, refracted, and reflected [by which] the small particles of bodies cohere when contiguous … and regulate almost all their motions amongst themselves. For electric [force] uniting the thinking soul and unthinking body.

As McGuire notes (177), “Newton was speculating on the possibility of uniting under one principle, life and nature, vitality and matter”—hardly what one would expect from the West’s greatest mechanistic scientist.^29

3.8 Leibniz

The panpsychism of Gottfried Leibniz (1646–1716) was rooted in his conception of the monad. Yet even before his development of that concept he found reason to see all things as animate. Some of Leibniz’s earliest philosophical writings date from the mid 1680s, when he was about 40 years old. In Primary Truths he asserted, with emphasis, that “every particle of the universe contains a world of an infinity of creatures” (1686a/1989: 34). The same year, in a letter to Arnauld, he defined soul as “substantial form” and attributed it to all things with a “thoroughly indivisible” unity: “I assign substantial forms to all corporeal substances that are more than mechanically united.” (1686b/1989: 80) The extent of such objects is presumed to be widespread but is left unspecified.

Leibniz seems to have had at least two reasons for thinking this way. The first was Leeuwenhoek’s recent (ca. 1660) invention of the microscope and his discovery of “animalcules” in apparently clear drops of water. This was dramatic empirical evidence that hitherto unseen forms of life resided in unsuspected places. A plethora of life implied a plethora of souls. Leibniz admitted as much in a 1687 letter to Arnauld: “[E]xperience favors this multitude of animated things. We find that there is a prodigious quantity of animals in a drop of water.” (1989: 88) Second, Leibniz found theological reasons for this belief. An ensouled universe was more nearly perfect than one in which only mankind possessed soul, and thus was more in line with the perfection of God. It is, he wrote, “in conformity with the greatness and beauty of the works of God for him to produce as many [true] substances as there can be in this universe” (1687/1989: 87). It is “a perfection of nature to have many [souls].”

Leibniz did not make detailed reference to the notion of the monad until 1698, and did not develop the monad theory fully before Principles of Nature and Grace (1714a) and Monadology (1714b). However, even his writings leading up to the concept of the monad indicate that he associated the soul or substantial form with an atomic or point-like entity. As early as 1671, at age 25, he wrote that “the soul, strictly speaking, is only at a point in space” (in Hoeffding 1908: 335). In 1695 he wrote of “true unities” underlying reality:

[I]n order to find these real unities, I was forced to have recourse to a real and animated point, so to speak, or to an atom of substance which must include something of form or activity to make a complete being. (1695: 139)

Here again we see the association of animation with a point-like entity. Leibniz continues:

I found that [the atoms’] nature consists in force, and that from this there follows something analogous to sensation [i.e. perception] and appetite, so that we must conceive of them on the model of the notion we have of souls.

Like Bruno’s, Leibniz’s monad was a point-like, atom-like entity that constituted all extant things. The monad was the true substance of the world, and all other things were simply collections or aggregates of these monadic substances: “These monads are the true atoms of nature, and, in brief, the elements of things.” (1714b, section 3) Monads, he writes, have the rather paradoxical quality of being at once absolutely simple and “without parts” and yet being absolutely unique. In fact every monad is a kind of focal point for its own perspective on the universe, and is internally as complex and ordered as the entire cosmos:

[T]here must be a plurality of properties and relations in the simple substance [i.e. monad], even though it has no parts. (1714b, section 13)

[E]ach monad is a living mirror … which represents the universe from its own point of view, and is as ordered as the universe itself. (1714a, section 3)

And these simple yet complex monads have other relevant characteristics. First, they are “windowless”—they have no direct interaction with the outside world or with each other, and they are exempt from physical causality. Second, and more to the point, monads have two primary capabilities: perception and appetite. Perceptions are the states that monads pass through as they continually reflect their ever-changing perspective on the universe. The appetite, or desire, “brings about the change or passage from one perception to another” (section 15). The importance of these two qualities cannot be overestimated. All mind, Leibniz says, even the simplest, possesses at least the subjective property of perception—feeling—and the intentional property of will or appetite. This aligns well with much of present-day philosophy of mind, which holds that the mind seems to have two irreducible components, namely the qualitative and the intentional.

Monads thus serve as the theoretical basis for Leibniz’s panpsychism. Consider this passage:

I believe that … it is consistent neither with the order nor with the beauty or the reason of things that there should be something vital or immanently active only in a small part of matter, when it would imply greater perfection if it were in all. And even if … intelligent souls … cannot be everywhere, this is no objection to the view that there should everywhere be souls, or at least things analogous to souls. (1698/1956: 820; section 12)

In Monadology (section 66) he reiterates this view: “we see that there is a world of creatures, of living beings, of animals, of entelechies, of souls in the least part of matter.” Clearly panpsychism was a consistent and essential aspect of Leibniz’s metaphysics.

Leibniz faced three perplexing and related questions: How can point-like entities combine to form apparently solid objects? How can a theory of monads account for the high-level soul or mind that is found in humans? Why do certain collections of monads (e.g., humans) possess high-level unified minds whereas others (e.g., rocks) do not?

The answers to these questions center on two concepts: that of the aggregate and that of the dominant monad. Throughout his philosophical career, Leibniz emphasized the distinction between mere collections or aggregates of monads and collections with a real and substantial sense of wholeness and unity. Aggregates include objects or systems that are loosely organized, such as a “heap of stones,” an “army,” a “herd,” or a “flock.” They furthermore include objects that are apparently solid and whole—rocks, tables, houses, shoes, and so on. In his theory of aggregates, Leibniz followed Democritus in asserting that aggregates only appear to be whole and unified.^30 Their unity is only in our minds, not in reality. This is clear in the cases of flocks and herds, less so in the case of a solid rock. Yet Leibniz saw them as on a continuum and as distinct from other objects—humans, other animals, plants, monads—that were truly integrated beings. Integrated objects possess a “substantial unity” that demands “a thoroughly indivisible and naturally indestructible being” (1686b/1989: 79). But this issue is metaphysically controversial.

The substantial unity of true individuals is realized physically by the dominant monad. Of the countless monads making up a person’s body, one monad somehow comes to dominate the others and to draw them together into cohesiveness.^31 This dominant monad, or “primary entelechy,” is the soul of the person. The human body, in itself, is considered a mere aggregate; but together with the dominant monad or soul it constitutes a “living being”:

[The dominant monad] makes up the center of a composite substance (an animal, for example) and is the principle of its unity, is surrounded by a mass composed of an infinity of other monads, which constitute the body belonging to this central monad. (1714a, section 3)

This again is the case for humans, animals, plants, and the microscopic animalcules in the droplets of water. Such things are in fact doubly ensouled: They consist of animate sub-monads and they possess a single unifying soul in the dominant monad. Aggregates, by contrast, are not animate in themselves, but of course are still composed of the soul-like monads. Therefore even aggregates are animate in a restricted sense. This is more or less identical to Bruno’s view, but Bruno offered no theory as to why it should be the case. Leibniz at least proposed the outline of a theory, even though he left many questions unanswered—including how and why one monad comes to dominate and why this happens only in certain collections of monads.

These open questions point to an incompleteness in Leibniz’s theory. He was never clear, for example, on whether large-scale objects or systems, such as the Earth, were to be considered “substantial unities.” Only once, in an early letter to Arnauld, did he address this directly:

[I]f I am asked in particular what I say about the sun, the earthly globe, the moon, trees, and other similar bodies. … I cannot be absolutely certain whether they are animated, or even whether they are substances. (1686b/1989: 80)

Leibniz later accepted plants as animated beings, but the general status of large-scale systems remained open for him throughout his life.

Two other points indicate Leibniz’s uncertainty about the status of aggregates. First, his final two major philosophical essays—Principles of Nature and Grace and Monadology—rarely mention the subject. Principles doesn’t discuss it, focusing instead on living beings and their dominant soul monad. Monadology actually reverses Leibniz’s usual terminology; he divides reality into “simple substances” (monads) and “composite substances,” wherein the composite “is nothing more than a collection, or aggregate, of simples” (section 2). Apparently, then, all living beings are to be considered aggregates. But the remainder of Monadology contains no further discussion of the soulless aggregates. That these two essays constitute a summary of Leibniz’s metaphysical system is all the more significant.

Second, there is Leibniz’s late (ca. 1712) introduction of the vinculum substantiale (substantial chain) as a kind of glue that bonds together the monads of a living being. He consistently affirmed that ordinary material objects, such as rocks, are mere phenomena and only appear to be unified beings. But this also holds for the body of an animal, which, apart from its dominant soul or mind monad, is also a mere aggregate. Concerned to differentiate the two, and knowing that “points can never form a continuum,” he introduced a substantial chain to link together all monads of true living beings. This chain is both “real” and “substantial,” and it is to be “added to the monads in order to make the phenomena real” (1716/1989: 203). In retrospect the whole concept of the vinculum substantiale seems an ad hoc construction to account for the differing properties of aggregates. It is in fact a whole new ontological category, distinct from the monads themselves. We are given no explanation of how this chain comes to exist, or of why it is present only in select aggregates and not in others.^32

A final point of note concerns the influence on Leibniz of the earlier panpsychists. Bruno clearly impressed him, and Leibniz’s use of the monad concept may well have been inspired, if only indirectly, by Bruno’s work. Consider the passage in section 66 of Monadology cited above: “we see that there is a world of creatures, of living beings, of animals, of entelechies, of souls in the least part of matter.” This seems to recall an earlier passage in which Bruno asserted that “there is not the least corpuscle that does not contain within itself some portion that may animate it.” And there were surely other Renaissance influences. We know for certain that Leibniz had read Campanella and thus was aware of Italian naturalism. He even seems to have picked up a central element of Campanella’s ontology: Monadology contains a virtual word-for-word reiteration of Campanella’s doctrine of the three primalities of power, wisdom, and love or will:

God has power, which is the source of everything, knowledge, which contains the diversity of ideas, and finally will, which brings about changes … in accordance with the principle of the best. (section 48)

Just before he introduced the term ‘monad’ in the late 1690s, Leibniz corresponded with the philosopher Francis van Helmont and was “considerably influenced” by him.^33 Helmont was a close associate of the British philosopher Anne Conway, who in turn was a colleague of Henry More. More cited the term ‘monad’ in his Cabbalistic axioms.^34 It is entirely plausible that either Conway or More (or both) picked up Bruno’s concept of the monad and incorporated it into their own writing. Thus, it may have been by way of More, Conway, and Helmont that Bruno’s influence was felt. In the end, Leibniz seems to have adopted many ideas of the Italian naturalists, elaborating and articulating them in his own terminology.

Notes

1. Dulles 1941: 89.

2. For details on the cosmic energy differential and the implications for universal evolution, see Skrbina 2015 or Chaisson 2001.

3. See, for example, Parmenides (129–132) and Phaedo (100–101).

4. For another, somewhat oblique view on Patrizi’s panpsychism, see Leinkauf 2010: 215: “Since the powers [of things] are conceived in accordance with the paradigm of the psychical, and the soul … functions as the forma universalis of the world, Patrizi’s cosmology … must be understood as affirming a universal … presence of the psychical, in the sense that all that exists is permeated by processual-dynamic structures.”

5. Bruno (1584b), cited on p. 58 of Singer 1950.

6. Bruno followed the ancient Greeks in equating “alive” and “ensouled.”

7. There are difficulties in defining a true individual. I examine this issue at length later in the book.

8. See also Aristotle, De anima 404b22: “Mind is the monad.”

9. The influence of Bruno on Leibniz is hotly debated. Leibniz makes only scattered references to the Italian; see the discussion on Leibniz below.

10. Cf. Singer 1950: 194; Kristeller 1964: 138; Calcagno 1998: 39.

11. Gilbert 1600/1958: xii.

12. For a further discussion of Gilbert’s theory of the magnet and his “animism,” see Henry 2001.

13. Campanella (1638), in Bonansea 1969 (p. 156).

14. See Bonansea 1969: 35–36.

15. For an elaboration on Campanella’s pansensism, see Ernst 2010: 262–263: “Thanks to sense, every being is endowed with the capacity to distinguish between that which benefits its existence and that which is harmful. … Every being shares in life and in sense, according to various degrees and in specific forms: some, such as the heavenly bodies and light, are endowed with a sense that is much more acute than that of animals, while others, such as minerals and metals, are endowed with a sense that is more obtuse and darker … .”

16. See part IV, chapter XXV.

17. The philosophical use of conatus was taken up by Leibniz and, especially, Spinoza, both to panpsychist ends. For more on Hobbes’ use of the term, see Herbert 1989: 25–62.

18. Gaskin 1994: 253.

19. Compare this with Cudworth’s notion of the “plastic nature.”

20. More (1668), in Bonifazi 1978 (pp. 59, 64).

21. See, for example, Merchant’s Death of Nature (1979: 270–272).

22. On other, relatively obscure panpsychists of the time, including John Comenius and Jan Marek Marci, see Giglioni 1995.

23. Unless otherwise noted, the following citations refer to that work as published in Spinoza 1677/1994.

24. The general structure of Ethics, though, was closely anticipated some 1,200 years earlier by Proclus; see his Elements of Theology.

25. For a good discussion of this system and its implications, see Bennett 1984: 125–143.

26. Schopenhauer found some significance in this letter for his own panpsychist thinking. See Schopenhauer 1819/1995: 58 or Schopenhauer 1819/1969: 126.

27. Donagan (1989) is perhaps the only dissenter from this trend, but his dissent is mild and ultimately he yields to a grudging acceptance: Panpsychism is a “doctrine to which [Spinoza] is committed.” (129) But “[the mind of] a grain of sand … will not be cognition, and will be barely distinguishable from inanimateness” (130).

28. See the note on p. 204 of McGuire 1968. Also see the passage, quoted on page 196 of the same work, in which Newton directly observes that “the Stoics taught that a certain infinite spirit pervades all space … and vivifies the entire world.”

29. For a further discussion of these ideas relative to Aristotle’s views, see McGuire 1994.

30. Democritus wrote “By convention (nomos) sweet and by convention bitter, by convention hot, by convention cold, by convention color: in reality, atoms and void.” (in Barnes 1987: 252–253)

31. This role of the dominant monad is strongly reminiscent of the Stoic hegemonikon, discussed earlier in the present volume.

32. For an extended discussion of the problem of aggregates, see Skrbina 2008.

33. See note on p. 227 of Leibniz 1989.

34. See Brown 1990.

4 Continental Panpsychism of the Eighteenth Century

Mechanistic philosophy made substantial progress in eighteenth-century Europe, gradually displacing theism as the dominant worldview. Scientific advances were seen as validating the presumption of a mechanistic cosmos. Judeo-Christian theology was superseded, first in intellectual circles and then later in society at large; its explanatory power faded, and its theistic imperatives grew impotent.

The ascendancy of mechanism was opposed both by theists (on the ground that the cosmos was not without Spirit) and by those who argued for a panpsychist, animated worldview (on the ground that matter was not lifeless and inert). Panpsychism in various forms emerged as a significant challenger to mechanism, at least within the bounds of rationalist philosophy. As it happens, most of the important developments of the century occurred on the Continent, primarily in France and Germany. Notable philosophers, including LaMettrie, Diderot, Herder, Goethe, Maupertuis, and Priestley, argued for a panpsychist view. Even Kant had some interesting observations on the matter.

4.1 French Vitalistic Materialism

From the late 1600s on, the leading metaphor for nature was that of the machine. Descartes inaugurated this tradition, and Leibniz extended the usage by speaking about living beings as machines. Leibniz couched it in pleasant enough terms, calling living creatures “divine machines” and emphasizing that natural machines were qualitatively different from man-made versions. Further, these divine machines were at root spiritual; mind and soul resided in the monad atoms that composed them. Living beings were more or less automatons whose actions flowed from the nature of monads and from the universal laws of nature. Shortly thereafter, other thinkers took the next logical step and began to ask whether the soul hypothesis was really necessary at all.

Among the most notorious of these philosophers was Julien LaMettrie (1709–1751). Author of the provocative and scandalous L’Homme Machine, LaMettrie was the first thinker to unabashedly—though anonymously—claim that man was purely a natural automaton and did not require an immaterial soul to account for his behavior. He had been trained as a physician, and his study of human anatomy, along with the scientific theories of the day, seemed to support such a view.

LaMettrie’s brand of materialism ran against the grain of the time. Pure materialism had been out of favor for nearly 1,500 years, particularly since the rise of the Christian worldview. Virtually all philosophers and natural scientists after the Stoics had claimed that there was some non-material, incorporeal aspect to reality. Hobbes broke with this tradition in the middle of the seventeenth century and met with severe condemnation. Descartes unintentionally set the stage for LaMettrie when he removed the spirit from nearly all aspects of the physical world, save the human. To Descartes, animals were unfeeling natural automata, in a different class of existence than humans. And as science came to explain more about physical reality, the need for an active incorporeal realm lessened. Also, there was increasingly less reason, from a physiological standpoint, to distinguish between humans and other animals. By the early 1700s, LaMettrie could speculate that either the soul did not exist or, if it did, it was essentially identical with the workings of the human body. In openly denying the immaterial soul, he carried scientific philosophy to its logical limit.^1

LaMettrie is also widely pronounced a mechanist; however, that characterization is not correct, and the distinction is quite important. The mechanistic view sees matter as fundamentally lifeless and inert. If one believes that motion and mind somehow arise purely through physical interaction of inert and lifeless atoms, then one is a mechanistic materialist. That approach follows directly from a Cartesian view of matter—pure extension, completely dead. To account for the human mind or soul, a mechanistic philosopher must resort to brute emergentism, supernatural dualism, epiphenomenalism, or eliminativism. Those were not viable options for LaMettrie. To him, mind was a very real entity, and clearly it was embedded in a material cosmos. An obvious solution, therefore, was to see matter itself as inherently dynamic, capable of feeling, even intelligent. Motion and mind derive from some inherent powers of life or sentience that dwell in matter itself or in the organizational properties of matter. That view, sometimes called vitalistic materialism, is the one that LaMettrie—and later Diderot—adopted.^2

Commentators often portray LaMettrie as a mechanist because it is assumed that anyone who denies the spiritual realm must see all things, and in particular all living things, as products of dead matter. It is quite common, even today, to equate materialism with mechanism. But, as has been noted, the two are logically independent. In fact, LaMettrie’s first philosophical work attacked the Cartesian notion of animals as unfeeling machines, calling such a position “a joke” (see below). Though he obviously adopted the term ‘machine’ in his L’Homme Machine, it was in a specifically vitalistic sense.

LaMettrie’s writing demonstrates that he had quasi-panpsychist and hylozoist inclinations, which necessarily have no role in a mechanistic materialism. Vitalistic materialism sees some degree of life and mind in all things; it seeks a natural rather than a supernatural explanation. LaMettrie’s man-machine was not a machine in the modern sense but rather a natural material object, one capable of self-motion and self-animation. As Vartanian (1960: 19) saw it, LaMettrie’s “primary task was to vitalize the Cartesian ‘dead mechanism.’” It was science that set the example: “Just as the inexplicable force of attraction [i.e. gravity] was proved empirically to inhere in matter, LaMettrie was encouraged to suppose by analogy that matter might also be capable of consciousness.” (67)

LaMettrie’s first philosophical work, L’Histoire Naturelle de L’Ame (Natural History of the Soul), was published in 1745.^3 It begins with a quasi-Stoic explanation of the soul viewed as the “active principal” of the body rather than as an immaterial substance that somehow interacts with it. Following Descartes, he then accepts that all matter possesses the attribute of spatial extension. Next he claims that matter has an inherent animating force that gives it the power of motion: “it is clear enough that matter contains the motive force which animates it and which is the immediate cause of all the laws of movement” (1745/1996: 49). Later in the work, LaMettrie carries out the full implications of this thought, arguing for a third general attribute of matter: feeling. But he is not entirely clear as to how we are to understand that faculty. At one point he informs us that it is a general property of matter, something that is clearly apparent in living organisms. Elsewhere we read that this faculty is not always manifest: “Here then is yet another faculty [i.e. feeling] which likewise seems to inhere in matter only potentially, like all the others.” Furthermore,

We must nevertheless admit frankly that we do not know whether matter has in itself the immediate faculty of feeling or only the power of acquiring it through the modification or forms of which it is susceptible. For it is true that this faculty only appears [to us] in organized bodies. (51)

Feeling becomes apparent to us when matter is sufficiently organized, but it exists latently in all matter. This seems to be the logical conclusion.

At the same time, LaMettrie chastises the Cartesians for positing non-human animals as unfeeling machines—another indication of his anti-mechanistic position:

I am aware of all the efforts vainly made by the Cartesians to take [feeling] away from matter. … They thought they could extricate themselves with the absurd system “that animals are mere machines.” Such a ridiculous opinion has never been accepted by philosophers except as a joke. … Experience proves that the faculty of feeling exists in animals just as much as it does in men. (50)

Science and physiology prove that there is a “perfect resemblance … between man and beast,” which philosophers ignore at their peril. Thus he places humanity firmly in the natural order and denies any categorical distinction.

LaMettrie doesn’t offer a good explanation of how matter can be sentient. In the passage cited above, he admits that it is not known whether feeling is inherent in all matter or is acquired through the forms it takes on. “How,” he asks candidly, “can we conceive that matter can feel and think? I admit that I cannot conceive it.” (65) Yet it self-evidently does, in ourselves and other animals.

LaMettrie’s strongest case for vitalistic materialism appears in L’Homme Machine (1747). He begins by criticizing Leibniz’s monadology as “unintelligible,” arguing that Leibniz went in the wrong direction: “he spiritualized matter rather than materialized the soul” (1747/1994: 27). Later LaMettrie reiterates his view that men are really no different from animals and in fact should be “honored to be ranked among them” (47). And he again defends his thesis that the organizational complexity of the human body accounts for the so-called faculties of the soul:

[T]hese faculties are obviously just this organized brain itself, there is a well-enlightened machine! [Even our conscience is] no more foreign to matter than thought is. … Is organization therefore sufficient for everything? Yes, once again. (59)

Utilizing a form of the Continuity argument, he argues that it is the matter of the body itself that exhibits feeling: “Since thought obviously develops with the organs, why would the matter of which they are made not be susceptible to [for example] remorse once it has acquired in time the faculty of feeling?”

Near the end of L’Homme Machine LaMettrie reiterates his claim that mere matter can think, but he acknowledges once again that there is an epistemological problem here. If matter can think, that implies a thinking subject, albeit one that is inherently unknowable:

On the basis of these [previous] observations and truths, we can attribute the admirable property of thinking to matter even without being able to see the connection between the two, because the subject of that thinking is unknown to us. (75)

This is a modern perspective. The subject—that which does the thinking—is known only to itself. The inner subjective feelings of any material being are forever hidden from public view. Vartanian notes that “the growth of subjective reality from matter in motion remains, in LaMettrie’s opinion, a metaphysical riddle lying beyond the competence of psychological [and philosophical] investigation” (1960: 23).

In his effort to unify nature, LaMettrie compared humans not only to animals but also to plants. In 1748, a year after L’Homme Machine, he published a short work, L’Homme Plante, in which he noted the many similarities in physiology between humans and plants (anticipating Fechner) and disputed the ancient notion (e.g., in Aristotle) of plant-souls; he also explicitly denied the concept of a world-soul. He did make one small adjustment to his organizational complexity thesis, arguing that mind is proportional not merely to complexity but more specifically to “needs,” the demands that the organism makes on the environment: “man is neither entirely a plant nor yet an animal like the others. … Because we have infinitely more needs, it follows necessarily that man must have infinitely more mind.” (1748/1994: 90) The implication is that all beings possess mind proportionate to their need to maintain their existence. The mind of a plant, though “infinitely smaller” than that of a human, is not nonexistent. Unfortunately, LaMettrie seems not to have pursued this line of thought.

LaMettrie’s works, in particular L’Homme Machine, caught the attention of the scientist-philosopher Pierre-Louis Maupertuis (1698–1759). In 1751, Maupertuis published a collection of meditations on the philosophy of biology under the title Systeme de la nature. In an earlier work, Venus physique (1745), he had argued for the view that natural organisms were formed in the womb by particles of matter that were pulled together by a force of attraction, supplemented by a kind of memory that reminded them where to go. His reference to “attraction” derived from Newton’s theory of gravitation and the universal attractive force that all matter exhibited.

Newton’s use of the word ‘attraction’ to describe his universal force was controversial. The word has clear animistic overtones, a fact not lost on the scientists and philosophers of the day. It recalls Empedocles’ notion of Love as the universal attractive force, not to mention Cardano’s “sympathy” of all things and the corresponding panpsychist theories of the world. In the 1680s Fontenelle had warned that granting the power of attraction to matter could lead to further animistic—and therefore digressive—attributions.

In Systeme de la nature, Maupertuis did precisely that. He determined that attraction alone, or even attraction with a degree of memory, was not sufficient to construct the complex unity of a living creature. Somehow there had to be a form of intelligence in the matter itself: “it is necessary to have recourse to some principle of intelligence, to some similar thing like that which we call desire, aversion, memory” (in Beeson 1992: 209). Thus Maupertuis took the standard conception of the material world as consisting of extended matter, motion, and attraction and supplemented those qualities with intelligence. Beeson writes:

Extension and movement are [for Maupertuis] not sufficient to explain the reproduction of living organisms, and it is therefore necessary to … abandon some simplicity in fundamental assumptions for the sake of closer agreement with observation. Maupertuis proposes the adoption of four concepts: extension, movement, attraction and intelligence, all viewed as essential properties of matter. (209–210)

Consequently, the smallest units of matter must be associated with some smallest units of intelligence or perception. Maupertuis referred to such units as “percipient particles,” a notion that recalls both the soul-atoms of Democritus and the monads of Leibniz. Thus were the physical properties (extension, movement) supplemented with mental properties (intelligence). Here again we see a form of panpsychic dualism—or perhaps dual-aspect panpsychism—argued for on the basis of first principles. And these intelligent qualities are seen to account for the unified form and properties of a living organism (argument by Design).

Denis Diderot (1713–1784) is best known as a co-editor, with Jean Le Rond d’Alembert, of the Encyclopedie—a monument to rationalist, secularist, and humanist thought of the French Enlightenment. The central project in all his writing was to dispel supernatural and theistic superstitions and to ground all phenomena in naturalistic explanations. That this could lead to panpsychism is perhaps surprising.

Like LaMettrie and Maupertuis before him, Diderot grappled with a fundamental problem: Given that there is neither a God nor an immaterial soul, one must still account for motion, life, and mind. Each of those three men had a strong intuition toward unity and holism, and all wanted to integrate the human into the natural world. They rejected the purely mechanistic interpretation of a universe of dead matter pushed around by myriad forces, and instead sought solutions in which life and sensitivity were inherent in all things. It is not surprising that, given these conditions and the state of scientific knowledge at the time, they came to similar conclusions.

Rather than formalize things, Diderot prefers to address general themes of a holistic and evolving natural world. Of those themes, the two most relevant here are panpsychism and the unity of the self.

Diderot’s panpsychist inclinations first appeared in his Pensees sur l’interpretation de la nature (Thoughts on the Interpretation of Nature), published in 1754. In section 50 he offers a sympathetic account of the “intelligent matter” hypothesis of Maupertuis.^4 Diderot elaborates on this new modification of matter, referring to the various noetic qualities as “desire, aversion, memory, and intelligence” (1754/1966: 79). He notes that Maupertuis accepts these qualities “as being present, in due proportion to their forms and masses, in the smallest particle of matter as well as in the very largest animal.” Diderot, clearly impressed by that thesis, devotes a rather large section of Pensees to it. He does not, however, offer it up as his own theory, as he would do 15 years later.

The concept of “sensitive matter” is one of the central themes in Le Reve de d’Alembert (D’Alembert’s Dream), perhaps Diderot’s most important philosophical work. Written as a dialogue between the author, D’Alembert, and a few minor characters, it explores a wide variety of themes, touching on psychology, morality, biology, and cosmology. In the opening passage of the first section, D’Alembert challenges Diderot with the classic rebuttal to panpsychism: “if this faculty of sensation … is a general and essential quality of matter, then stone must be sensitive” (1769/1937: 49). Diderot’s casual reply is “Why not?” The everyman D’Alembert answers “It’s hard to believe.” As the dialogue progresses, it becomes clear that there are two levels of sensitivity in matter: an active form, such as is found in organic beings, and a passive form, such as is found in rocks and inanimate objects. The passive becomes active when taken up in an organic body, as when it is consumed; plants consume minerals, for example, and thus make their sensitivity active.^5 And yet, even as Diderot distinguished degrees of sensitivity, it is clearly the sensitivity itself that is primary.

Throughout the dialogue there are repeated references to “the general sensitivity of matter.” Later we learn that “from the elephant to the flea, from the flea to the sensitive living atom, the origin of all, there is no point in nature but suffers and enjoys” (80). Diderot seems to simply accept this panpsychism—or rather pansensism—as a fundamental aspect of nature, and doesn’t work it into a comprehensive metaphysical theory.

This outlook recurs in his other writings. In Elements of Physiology, for example, we find the following passage:

Some day it will be demonstrated that sensitiveness or feeling is a sense common to all beings. There are already phenomena which suggest this. Then matter in general will have five or six essential properties: dead or living force, length, breadth, depth, impenetrability, and sensitiveness. (1774–1780/1937: 139)

Diderot thus effectively modified Maupertuis’ four essential properties of matter, arriving at force, extension, impenetrability, and sensitiveness. His notion of force incorporated the three general categories of kinetic (“living”) energy, potential (“dead”) energy, and gravity.

A second theme, unity of the self, addresses the well-known combination problem of panpsychism: If each particle of matter is individually intelligent, how do they combine to form the single sense of being that we all feel? Leibniz solved it by creating the dominant monad. In Le Reve, Diderot points toward an amorphous notion of unity of being that occurs when the intelligent particles are sufficiently interactive. He makes an analogy to a swarm of bees: “This cluster is a being, an individual, an animal of sorts.” (67) It is a unitary being because of the extremely tight interaction between parts, which pass from being merely “contiguous” to being truly “continuous.” Strength of interaction determines the intensity of being; one might also say that intensity of exchange determines intensity of mind. The human body is not categorically different from a swarm of bees. The body is a collection of organs, which “are just separate animals held together by the law of continuity in a general sympathy, unity, and identity” (68). It is the “continual action and reaction” between parts that creates the unity. “It seems to me,” Diderot writes, “that contact, in itself, is enough.” (76)

4.2 Kant and Priestley

The forefront of panpsychist philosophy moved from France to Germany over the course of the 1700s. But before discussing the role of German Romanticism it is necessary to address two intermediate figures: Immanuel Kant and Joseph Priestley.

Kant’s (1724–1804) thinking on the matter of hylozoism and panpsychism underwent an interesting progression over the course of his life, moving from early sympathies to a final analytic rejection. A little-known booklet published in 1766, Traume der Geisterseher (Dreams of a Spirit-Seer), focuses on Kant’s interest in the spiritual realm and the possibilities of trans-physical phenomena. “I confess,” he writes, “that I am very much inclined to assert the existence of immaterial natures in the world, and to put my soul itself into that class of beings.” (1766/1900: 52) He adds in a footnote that whatever “contains a principle of life, seems to be of immaterial nature,” and that “those immaterial beings which contain the cause of animal life … are called spirits.” He then addresses the idea of hylozoism or panpsychism:

For every substance, even a simple element of matter, must have an inner activity as the reason for its external efficiency, although I cannot specify in what it consists. (53–54)

Another footnote contains this fascinating and revealing comment:

Leibniz says that this inner reason … is the power of conception [i.e. intelligence], and later philosophers received this undeveloped thought with laughter. But they would have done better if they had first considered whether a substance of the nature of a simple particle of matter is possible without any inner state. [If so, they would have to] think out another possible inner state than that of conceptions. … Everybody recognizes [that] even if a power of obscure conceptions is conceded to … matter, it does not follow thence that matter itself possesses power of conception, because many substances of that kind, united into a whole, can yet never form a thinking unit.

Kant thus views the combination problem as insurmountable, stating directly that many individually intelligent particles can never form a single intelligent entity. Beyond this, he doesn’t absolutely rule out Leibniz’s panpsychist thesis; he recognizes that the issue is not as clear-cut as many would suppose. We see further evidence of his sympathies in the following chapter:

[T]o which members of nature life is extended, and … those [to which] degrees of it … are next to utter lifelessness, can, perhaps, never be made out with certainty. Hylozoism imputes life to everything; materialism, carefully considered, kills everything. (57)

That materialism “kills everything” is quite a statement. Kant seems to recognize a danger in this ontological view.^6 He then cites Maupertuis’ panpsychist theory, going on to observe that, as Newton argued, one cannot be sure that all things are not alive: “The undoubted characteristic of life [is] free movement … , but the conclusion is not certain that, wherever this characteristic is not found, there is no degree of life.” Though certainly not endorsing hylozoism, Kant is at least open to the possibility.

Fifteen years later, Kant’s focus had shifted from hylozoism to something more akin to true panpsychism. In Critique of Pure Reason (1781) he famously argued that das Ding an sich is inherently unknowable, and thus almost nothing can be said of it. However, in one passage in book II of the Transcendental Dialectic—chapter 1, “Paralogisms of Pure Reason (B)”—Kant accepts that the thing-in-itself may share some essential characteristic or quality of mind. In a short section titled “Conclusion, In Regard to the Solution of the Psychological Paralogism,” he claims that his arguments “supply a sufficient answer to this question [of] the communion of the soul [i.e. mind] with the body.” He elaborates:

The difficulty peculiar to the problem consists, as is generally recognized, in the assumed difference [in nature] between the object of the inner sense (the soul) and the [material] objects of the outer senses. But if we consider that the two kinds of objects thus differ from each other, not inwardly but only in so far as one appears outwardly to the other, and that what, as Ding-an-sich-selbst, underlies the appearance of matter, perhaps after all may not be so different in character, this difficulty vanishes … .

Thus he observes that if one assumes that the soul and the objects of the material world are fundamentally alike, i.e., of the same ontological class, then the mind-body problem is resolved. Kant’s wording suggests that he would look favorably on such an assumption, though he clearly stops short of endorsing it. Still, the implication is that matter, of which we do not know the true essence, is somehow like our mind, of which we do know, intimately, the essence. We may be mistaken about the true nature of mind, but we certainly know it more directly than we know anything else in the universe. One reasonable conclusion, therefore, would be that all matter has a mind-like quality in and of itself.^7 This leaves us, Kant continues, with only the problem of “how in general a communion of [such] substances is possible.” But he doesn’t address this, saying that it lies not only “outside the field of psychology” but also “outside the field of all human knowledge.”

Kant’s Critique of Judgment (1790) presents his final analytical stance. He writes that there are two types of philosophical systems that can explain the “productive power” and “purposiveness” of nature: realism and idealism. Both of these can exist in two forms: physical and trans-physical. Physical realism, he tells us, “bases the purposes in nature … on the life of matter (either its own or the life of an inner principle in it, a world-soul) and is called hylozoism” (1790/1951: 239). That option, unfortunately, is inconceivable:

[T]he possibility of living matter cannot even be thought; its concept involves a contradiction, because lifelessness, inertia, constitutes the essential character of matter. The possibility of matter endowed with life … can only be used in an inadequate way … , [and] in no way can its possibility be comprehended a priori. … Hylozoism, therefore, does not perform what it promises. (242)

This seems to be Kant’s final word on the matter. Unfortunately, he never pursued the suggestion mentioned in Critique of Pure Reason. For him, apparently, the conceptual weaknesses could not offset the potential explanatory power.

As it happens, Priestley (1733–1804) did not see things as Kant did. Priestley is best known for his discovery of oxygen (in 1774), but he was also an astute natural philosopher. He was concerned with the problem of mind and body, and in 1777 he wrote a rather lengthy treatise on the subject, titled “Disquisitions relating to matter and spirit,” arguing for the idea that mind and matter are not incompatible Cartesian substances but rather share common qualities, and in fact can be seen as different manifestations of the same underlying entity.

Priestley begins by challenging the traditional view that matter is something defined by extension, inertness, and impenetrability. He accepts the first of these, but replaces the latter two with a pair of forces: “I … define [matter] to be a substance possessed of the property of extension, and of powers of attraction or repulsion.” (1777: 219) He argues that these three properties—extension, attraction, repulsion—are sufficient to account for all material phenomena.^8

Priestley’s ideas were anticipated already in 1758 by the Italian scientist and philosopher Roger (Ruggiero) Boscovich. Boscovich’s Theoria philosophiae naturalis presented a thesis in which the forces present in matter were the ultimate ontological reality—a view that came to be known as dynamism. Priestley accepted and expanded on that view, adding the quality of extension under the presumption that form or shape was also an essential quality of matter.

For Priestley, the overriding opposition between classical matter and spirit was that matter was solid and spatial whereas spirit was non-spatial and immaterial. That incompatibility was the source of the problem of mind-body interaction. He argued that by dematerializing matter—by making it penetrable (i.e., pure force)—he could remove that barrier. For him, mind was then completely compatible with matter and could in fact be seen as a particular mode of it:

[S]ince it has never yet been asserted, that the power of sensation and thought are incompatible with these [powers of attraction and repulsion], I therefore maintain, that we have no reason to suppose that there are in man two substances so distinct from each other as have been represented.

Priestley sought a materialist monism that shared some qualities with the views of LaMettrie and Diderot; in particular, it saw matter as fundamentally dynamic and animated, and mind as a function of the organizational qualities of matter. In short, Priestley sought to “prove the uniform composition of man” (220). For him, “mind … is not a substance distinct from the body, but the result of corporeal organization; … whatever matter be, … mind is nothing more than a modification of it.” Mind reduces to matter, but matter which is, in some sense, fundamentally mind-like. Matter “ought to rise in our esteem, as making a nearer approach to the nature of spiritual and immaterial beings” (230).

Nowhere did Priestley explicitly state that all matter possesses mind, but this implication can be seen to follow from his premises. He was an implicit panpsychist, and one who, in his time, fundamentally challenged the inert-matter view of the world.

4.3 German Romanticism and Naturphilosophie

By the late 1700s, philosophical opposition to mechanistic thinking had moved to Germany. Panpsychism continued to play a prominent role, particularly in the emerging views of Johann Herder, Johann Wolfgang von Goethe, and Friedrich Schelling.

Herder (1745–1803) was a dynamist who rejected the idea that such a view implied materialism. He sought a naturalistic non-reductive ontology in which mind and matter were different degrees of organization of a single underlying force or energy called Kraft. In denying conventional materialism and placing force in a unique ontological category, Herder was one of the first explicitly neutral monists of the modern era, though the designation would not be used until the time of Bertrand Russell.

In the late eighteenth century, science recognized many different forces in nature—gravity, magnetism, electricity, light, and motive force, among others. Herder sought to unify these forces as the singular Kraft, of which the various Kräfte were different manifestations. Furthermore, Kraft was to be seen not merely as physical force but as an animating energy in which the individual sub-forces were in themselves soul-like entities. He wrote of the universal Kraft in On the Cognition and Sensation of the Human Soul:

Quite generally, nothing in nature is separated, everything flows onto and into everything else through imperceptible transitions; and certainly, what life is in the creation is in all its shapes, forms, and channels only a single spirit, a single flame. (1778/2002: 195)

Thus all material things, in addition to the standard forces of physics, are unified and vivified by the universal Kraft. It is at once a life-energy, spirit, and mind—recalling the pneuma of the Stoics.

The passage above could be interpreted as expressing a pure, almost idealist monism. However, Herder’s thinking was more of a panpsychist variety in which each thing has an interior life and experiential perspective. Nisbet (1970: 10) explains that, in an early 1769 manuscript, Herder discusses “how the human body, and by analogy, the planets, are formed by the action of an inner Monas [unity], Kraft [force], or Seele [soul or mind].” Herder’s 1778 work refers to the Continuity argument and the process of analogical inference: “the more we thoughtfully observe the great drama of effective forces in nature, the less we can avoid everywhere feeling similarity with ourselves, enlivening everything with our sensation” (1778/2002: 187).

Later he became even more explicitly panpsychist. Nisbet (1970: 11) notes that Herder “represents the Kräfte of plants and stones as analogous to the soul. … Each endowed with a different degree of consciousness.” In the attempt to classify Herder’s metaphysical view, Nisbet runs through a number of panpsychism synonyms, ultimately deciding that “pan-animism” is most appropriate.

The panpsychist theme continues in Herder’s later writings. Ideen zur Philosophie der Geschichte der Menschheit (Ideas for the Philosophy of the History of Humanity; 1784–1791) includes, for example, this passage:

All active forces of Nature are, each in its own way, alive; in their interior there must be Something that corresponds to their effects without—as Leibniz himself assumed … . (book I, section XIII, in Clark 1955: 311)

Herder clearly saw such a panpsychist dynamism as an alternative to the reigning Cartesian mechanistic materialism, which he strongly opposed. This opposition is consistent throughout his philosophical writings. Nisbet notes that for Herder “the psychology of feeling tends to replace mechanical analysis … , and Kräfte increasingly supplant ‘dead’ matter.” From 1769 on, Herder “consistently attacks mechanistic theories of nature” (133).

Herder shared many opinions with his contemporary and friend Goethe (1749–1832). Like William Blake, Goethe infused many of his literary works with philosophical insight. The exemplary German Romantic, he combined a poetic, mystical feeling for nature with a strong sense of unity and holism.

Elements of panpsychism are found only indirectly in Goethe. First there is his general identification of Nature with God: “I have at times to resort to pantheism to satisfy my being.”^9 Then there is his frequent attribution of personal and human traits to the phenomena of nature. Sherrington notes that “in reading Goethe’s science we are never left long without a reminder of his tendency to personify Nature.”^10 Goethe expresses this sentiment when he notes that Nature “reflects herself … everywhere in a manner analogous to our mind.”^11 And we find suggestive passages such as this: “it is the observer’s first duty … to aim at the completeness of the phenomena … so that they will present themselves to one’s observation as an organization manifesting an inner life of its own.”^12 The “inner life” of natural phenomena suggests the presence of mind in nature.

The panpsychist and hylozoist Ernst Haeckel cited Goethe on multiple occasions in support of his own ideas. Haeckel held that mind and matter were inseparably linked, and he attributed the same belief to Goethe:

As even Goethe has clearly expressed it, “matter can never exist and act without mind, and mind never without matter.” (1868/1876: 487)

Here we find a beautifully concise statement: no matter without mind, no mind without matter. There is no claim that mind is identical with matter, or that one can be reduced to the other; there is simply the statement that mind and matter are conjoined, that neither exists without the other. This is an essential feature of panpsychism.

Haeckel’s citation comes from a letter Goethe wrote in 1828, near the end of his life. The original passage is enlightening. Goethe notes that there are “two great driving forces in all nature: the concepts of polarity and intensification” (1828/1988: 6). The former is associated with the material dimension of reality, the latter with the spiritual. He defines polarity in a very Empedoclean manner as “a state of constant attraction and repulsion,” and characterizes intensification as an evolutionary imperative—a “state of ever-striving ascent.” He continues: “Since, however, matter can never exist and act without spirit [Seele], nor spirit without matter, matter is also capable of undergoing intensification, and spirit cannot be denied its attraction and repulsion.” Again, no matter without mind, no mind without matter.

Herder and Goethe articulated aspects of a holistic philosophy of nature, but its culmination in Germany was achieved in the Naturphilosophie of Friedrich Schelling. In Schelling’s view, humans were deeply integrated into nature, physical forces were seen as manifestations of a single underlying force, and mechanism was soundly rejected. He unified these elements and created a comprehensive philosophical system.

For the most part, Schelling’s case for panpsychism is implicit. His absolute idealism emphasizes Mind as the underlying unity of all things. Everything finds meaning and resolution in the Mind of the Absolute: “Nature is to be invisible mind, mind invisible nature.”^13 His early work Ideas for a Philosophy of Nature (1797/1988) includes this remark: “[T]here is a hierarchy of life in Nature. Even in mere organized matter there is life, but a life of a more restricted kind.” (35) He understands matter as intimately connected to mind: “Matter is indeed nothing else but mind viewed in an equilibrium of its activities.” (1800/1978: 92) In arguing that mind in nature reveals itself as a form of will, which is a “primal being,” Schelling was one of the first modern German philosophers to emphasize the ontological importance of the will, following Bruno and Campanella and anticipating Schopenhauer, Hartmann, and Nietzsche.

Commentaries on Schelling’s panpsychism are rare. Blamauer (2012) offers what may be the most detailed discussion. Rothschuh describes Schelling’s system as essentially that of an evolving spirit: “Nature is spirit in the course of becoming.”^14 Such a vision appears to describe a cosmos wherein all things possess an element of mind. Werner Marx (1984: 58) notes that for Schelling “nature is rather a spirit that, in a dynamic series of stages from inorganic matter up to consciousness, is similar to an ego.” This evolving mind is therefore in some sense a subject, a personality, that is manifest in all levels of matter.

Notes

1. LaMettrie was not an outright atheist. Rather, he held more to an agnostic view. On his view, one could certainly continue to believe in God, but it was strictly a matter of faith. God had no role to play in the material world, and certainly no explanatory power over natural phenomena. Nonetheless, atheism was his preferred position, and he asserted that “the world will never be happy until it is atheist.” (1747: 58)

2. Vitalistic materialism was anticipated by Cavendish in her theory of organicist materialism of the 1660s—recall the discussion in chapter 3. Both of these forms of panpsychic materialism ultimately draw from the Greek notion of a material cosmos pervaded by the pneuma.

3. This work was amended and republished in 1750 as Treatise on the Soul.

4. Referred to with the pseudonym “Dr. Baumann, of Erlangen.”

5. We see here a close connection to LaMettrie’s distinction between “direct” and “potential” ability to feel.

6. It is clear that he means mechanistic materialism.

7. Kant leaves open the possibility of a neutral-monist position, in which case something other than mind or matter would underlie both.

8. His use of the two opposing forces again recalls Empedocles’ Love and Strife.

9. Goethe (1824), in Sherrington 1949 (p. 33).

10. Sherrington 1949: 21.

11. In Vietor 1950 (p. 13).

12. In Naydler 1996 (p. 83).

13. In Bowie 1998 (p. 509).

14. In Schnaedelbach 1984 (p. 242).

5 Panpsychism, Mechanism, and Science in Nineteenth-Century Germany

Germany remained at the center of evolving views on panpsychism throughout the nineteenth century, even as mechanistic philosophy became increasingly dominant. Paradoxically, new developments in science, physics, and mathematics allowed both mechanists and panpsychists to strengthen their cases. Among the major philosophers advocating or sympathizing with panpsychist views were Schopenhauer, Fechner, Lotze, Hartmann, Mach, Haeckel, and (controversially) Nietzsche. By the end of the century, Friedrich Paulson could compile the first substantial overview of panpsychist philosophy, one that acknowledged the many important German contributions.

5.1 Schopenhauer

The philosophical system of Arthur Schopenhauer (1788–1860) is conveniently summarized in the title of his most famous work, Die Welt als Wille und Vorstellung (The World as Will and Idea).^1 Reality is comprehended in two distinct but connected ways. “World as idea” is essentially equivalent to classical idealism, in which things are collections of sensory images. “World as will,” however, is something entirely new; it completely and radically rewrites our metaphysical picture in panpsychist terms.

To elaborate: When we examine the world in a naïve or prima facie sense, what we perceive, fundamentally, is a patchwork of sensory impressions: colors, shapes, sounds, scents, and textures. The mind, attempting to make sense of the world, immediately bundles these sensory impressions together into what we identify as individual objects. An apple, for example, is roundish, of a certain size, has a reddish color, smells and tastes a certain way. It is precisely this unique bundle of impressions that allows us to call a certain thing an apple. And so it is with every object that we perceive.

From the time of Bishop Berkeley, sensory impressions had been thought of as ideas, and “things” as self-evidently collections of ideas. He contemplated a further question: What are things, apart from the ideas? His answer was Nothing; things are only ideas, and they exist only in a perceiving mind or soul. Matter, or material substance, literally doesn’t exist. This outlook, which came to be known as idealism, has traditionally been attributed to Berkeley and his work of the early 1700s.

Schopenhauer accepted the notion that things were bundles of ideas, but he emphatically rejected the thought that they were nothing more. If Berkeley were right, he said, the entire world would be intrinsically empty—a kind of phantom or dream. There would be no substance to reality. There had to be an inner nature to things, something substantial, in order to “objectify” or reify the world.

Various attempts had been made throughout history to determine this inner nature, the thing-in-itself of material objects. Descartes had famously determined that it was an “extended, flexible, changeable” substance of an otherwise indeterminate nature.^2 For Kant, it was some inherently unknowable entity. To Schopenhauer, both answers were inadequate. Descartes, Kant, and Berkeley had failed to discern the truth because they neglected to consider the one object in the universe that they knew better than anything else: one’s own body. Had they not neglected to consider it, they would have realized that the human body, most essentially, knows and feels its own wants, urges, needs, and desires—in sum, its will. For Schopenhauer, the will was the ontological essence of the human being, our true inner nature.

Schopenhauer completed his argument by noting that the human being is simply an object like every other in the world, composed of the same elemental substances and subject to the same laws and forces. If the human was essentially will, then so too was everything else. He thus reasoned that all things, in themselves, were will. His overall conclusion was that the things of the world were both, and at once, idea from the outside and will from the inside: “For as the world is in one aspect entirely idea, so in another it is entirely will.” (1819/1995: 5)

As has already been noted, the world as will directly challenges Kant’s conception of a fundamentally unknowable Ding an sich. The difference between the two views, however, may not be as great as Schopenhauer presumed, if we recall Kant’s speculation that the Ding an sich may be of a mind-like nature. Hartmann recognized this very point: “What Kant entertained as timid supposition, that the thing of itself and the active subject might be one and the same existence, Schopenhauer declared as categorical assertion, in that he recognized the will as the positive character of this essence.” (1869: 236) For Schopenhauer, the will was clearly and unambiguously mental. He thereby thrust the concept of the will into a central ontological role. Will, for him, was not merely the equivalent of human desire but was more generally a universal force, a drive, something that impelled and sustained all things. Hamlyn (1980: 95) argues that this will was “a kind of force which permeates nature and which thus governs all phenomena.” Magee (1983:145) describes it as literally force or energy—making Schopenhauer out to be a dynamist or energeticist—and argues that the developments of twentieth-century physics have “provided the most powerful confirmation that could be imagined” of his metaphysics.

Schopenhauer lends credence to the dynamist view in his own writing. On a number of occasions he equates will with the physical forces of nature. For example, he notes that “the force which attracts a stone to the ground is according to its nature, in itself, and apart from all idea, will” (1819: 38). In a later work, Über den Willen in der Natur (On the Will in Nature), he states that “generally every original force manifesting itself in physical and chemical appearances, in fact gravity itself—all these in themselves … are absolutely identical with what we find in ourselves as will” (1836: 20).

But Schopenhauer goes further in his thesis that the world is will. He speaks of material things as literally “objectifications of will”—as physical manifestations, or solidifications, or tangible embodiments of will. Of the human body, he says that “the whole body is nothing but objectified will” and “the action of the body is nothing but the act of the will objectified” (1819: 33). His graphic explanations leave no doubt: “Teeth, throat, and intestines are objectified hunger; the genitals are objectified sexual desire.” (41) Objectification occurs in varying levels or degrees throughout nature, generally corresponding to the complexity of the object. The human being is the highest grade of objectification; the physical forces are the basest. “The most universal forces of nature present themselves as the lowest grade of the will’s objectification.” (61)

Since the will is clearly and unambiguously mental, panpsychism is a central feature of his metaphysics. Thus we can understand Popper’s quip “One can say that Schopenhauer is a Kantian who has turned panpsychist.” (1977: 68) This aspect is particularly evident in Schopenhauer’s concept of will as manifest in inorganic objects. Book II of World as Will and Idea focuses extensively on the identification of will with the forces of nature:

[T]he force which stirs and vegetates in the plant, and indeed the force by which the crystal is formed, that by which the magnet turns to the North Pole, the force whose shock [results] from the contact between different metals, the force which appears in the elective affinities of matter as repulsion and attraction, separation and combination, and, lastly, even gravitation, … all these [are recognized] as in their inner nature as identical [to that] which is called will. (1819: 42)

This will in nature is, in principle, the same as the will in man:

[The will] is manifest in every force of nature that operates blindly, and it is manifest, too, in the deliberate action of man; and the great difference between these two is a matter only of degree of the manifestation, not in the nature of what is made manifest.

One can see in this quotation a reflection of Spinoza’s idea that “all things are animate in varying degrees,” and in fact Spinoza was highly influential in Schopenhauer’s thinking. World as Will and Idea refers explicitly to Spinoza’s notion that all things, even stones, possess an aspect of mentality:

Spinoza says that if a stone which has been catapulted through the air had consciousness, it would think that it was flying of its own will. I add only that the stone would be right. That catapulting is for the stone what the motive is for me … . (58)^3

The point here is that the inner nature of both men and stones is the same: will. Furthermore, it is a will that has the appearance of freedom to the subject. We feel free in our own actions, just as the stone (wrongly) would if it could contemplate such things. In any case, the essence of both is the same: “In people [will] is called character, while in a stone it is called quality, but it is the same in each.”

Even though Schopenhauer denied consciousness to all but the animals, it is clear that the will was to be described in terms of the human personality, and as a psychic or mental disposition:

When we scrutinize [the forces of nature] closely, we observe the tremendous, irresistible force with which rivers hurry down to the sea, the persistence with which the magnet turns again and again to the North Pole, the readiness with which iron flies to the magnet, the eagerness with which in electricity opposite poles strive to be reunited, and which, just like human desire, is the more intense for being thwarted: … it will cost us no great effort of the imagination, even at so great a distance, to recognize our own nature. (50)

Human nature is a reflection of universal nature. That which we see in ourselves must apply to reality writ large.

Schopenhauer’s panpsychism is reiterated in his other two major works, On the Will in Nature (1836) and Parerga und Paralipomena (1851). In the former he looks to developments in the natural sciences as confirmation of his ideas. He finds in inorganic nature “absolutely no trace of a consciousness of an external world,” yet even such things as “stones, boulders or ice floes” are “affected by an influence from without … which one can accordingly regard as the first step toward consciousness” (1836/1993: 82). And plants, though likewise lacking true consciousness, can be seen as experiencing “an obscure self-enjoyment” and “a feeble analogue of perception.” In examining the study of gravitation and astronomy, he notes with satisfaction that Herschel and Copernicus spoke of gravity in terms of “desire” and “will”: In 1883 Herschel wrote that objects drawn to the Earth are “impelled to this by a force or effort, the direct or indirect result of a consciousness and a will existing somewhere,” and in De revolutionibus Copernicus expresses a belief “that gravity is nothing but a natural craving” (85–86). And Schopenhauer claims, for the record, to have been “the first to say that a will is to be attributed to the inanimate, to the inorganic” (88).^4

This theme continues in Schopenhauer’s late work Parerga und Paralipomena. In a notable passage near the end of that book, he decries the “fundamentally false antithesis between mind and matter” (1851/1974: 212). To the extent that one can speak of “mind” or “matter” in the real world—that is, the inner and outer manifestations of things—mind must be equally attributable to both the organic and the inorganic. Any two material objects, such as (to use his examples) the human body and a stone, have internal qualities that are of necessity alike. Both are driven by the same forces of nature, both have mass and volume, and both are thus describable in the same metaphysical terms. If in one case we find mind, so must we find it in the other:

Now if you suppose the existence of a mind in the human head, … you are bound to concede a mind to every stone. … All ostensible mind can be attributed to matter, but all matter can likewise be attributed to mind; from which it follows that the antithesis [between mind and matter] is a false one. (213)

In the same passage, Schopenhauer makes an important observation on the limitations of the mechanistic philosophy in comprehending such truths: The mechanist knows only the mathematically derivable effects of nature, not nature as it is in itself. For a mechanist, “the exertion of weight in a stone is every bit as inexplicable as is thought in a human brain,” and, insofar as these natural phenomena are related, “this fact would suggest the presence of a mind in the stone.”^5 The mechanistic account of nature “is limited … to determining its spatial and temporal qualities.” Furthermore,

as soon as we go beyond what is purely mathematical, … we stand before modes of expression which are just as mysterious to us as the thought and will of man, … for [to the mechanist] unfathomable is what every natural force is.

All this is undoubtedly true, and is furthermore an important anticipation of the later and related thoughts by Bertrand Russell and Arthur Eddington. This insight, in fact, is the basis for the so-called Russellian monism, much discussed in recent years, which naturally lends itself to a form of panpsychism.

Schopenhauer explicitly acknowledges his debt to Empedocles, especially for the general concept of existence as a struggle between forces of will—specifically, Love and Strife: “Everywhere in nature we see strife, conflict, and the fickleness of victory. … This strife may be seen to pervade the whole of nature; indeed nature … exists only through it.” (73–74) He cites Aristotle’s commentary: “as Empedocles says, if there were no strife in things, everything would be one and the same” (cf. Metaphysics, 1000b1). Thus nature reflects a kind of law of the jungle, with each form of existence competing with all others to maintain and fulfill itself.^6

Schopenhauer saw struggle and strife all around him, and that led to his notoriously pessimistic assessment of life in general. He was exceptional in that instance; most all panpsychist philosophers seem to have adopted sympathetic, compassionate, and optimistic worldviews. Most philosophers seem to have found wonder and transcendence in the fact that mind pervades the universe. Schopenhauer saw a world of objectified wills locked in an eternal, almost Darwinian struggle for dominance. Such a view was, in its own way, influential, especially through Nietzsche.

5.2 Fechner

Gustav Fechner (1801–1887) was, in a sense, the antithesis of the pessimist Schopenhauer. Fechner’s vibrant, exuberant, life-enhancing perspective on the world was intimately and openly linked to his panpsychist philosophy, perhaps more so than the perspective of any other major philosopher. And he was a first-rate scientist and mathematician. He virtually invented the science of psychophysics, and he discovered the principle that the perceived strength of a sensation is proportional to the logarithm of the intensity of the stimulus (which came to be known as “Fechner’s Law”). His important philosophical works include Nanna, oder über das Seelen-Leben der Pflanzen (Nanna, or on the Soul-Life of Plants, 1848), Zend-Avesta (1851), Über die Seelenfrage (On the Soul-Question, 1861), and Die Tagesansicht gegenüber der Nachtansicht (The Daylight View as Opposed to the Night View, 1873). The fact that little of this material has been translated into English accounts in part for Fechner’s relative lack of exposure and analysis in the English-speaking countries. Only two books published in English explore his metaphysical views. The first is a series of partial translations of his major works compiled under the title Religion of a Scientist (1946). The second is a relatively lengthy and sympathetic discussion by William James in A Pluralistic Universe (1909). James was impressed by Fechner, calling him “a philosopher in the ‘great’ sense” (149) and noting that the current state of knowledge of psychology, psychophysics, and religion had led to “a decidedly formidable probability in favor of a general view of the world almost identical with Fechner’s” (309–310).

The most important aspect of Fechner’s panpsychism is his conception of the world as composed of a hierarchy of minds or souls (Seele). There are souls “below” us in the plants, and there are souls “above” us in the Earth, the stars, and the universe as a whole. Humans are surrounded, at all levels of being, by varying degrees of soul. This is Fechner’s “daylight view”—the human soul at home in an ensouled cosmos. He contrasted it with the materialist “night view” of humans as alone, isolated points of light in a universe of utter blackness.

Consider separately Fechner’s discussions of the lesser (sub-human) and greater (super-human or collective) minds. The former consist almost entirely of discussions of plants, which he is sure possess minds. His case relies on a form of the Continuity argument and on an analogy with human beings,^7 though he employs at least four other arguments for panpsychism. The Continuity argument appears repeatedly in Nanna, for example in this passage:

If we take a cursory glance at some of the outstanding points, is not the plant quite as well organized as the animal, though on a different plan, a plan entirely of its own, perfectly consonant with its idea? If one will not venture to deny that the plant has a life, why deny it a soul? For it is much simpler to think that a different plan of bodily organization built upon the common basis of life indicates only a different plan of psychic organization. … Whether it be a plant or an animal, the complexity of structure and process is so completely analogous, except that the cells are differently arranged … . (1848/1946: 168–169)

Because we cannot directly know the inner life of a plant, scientific or logical analysis is useless; “in this field, one must remember, there is nothing we have to rely upon except analogy” (175).

Fechner’s personal, intuitive feel for the plant-soul is abundantly evident throughout his writing. One finds passionate and poetic words, such as the following:

I stood once on a hot summer’s day beside a pool and contemplated a water-lily which had spread its leaves evenly over the water and with an open blossom was basking in the sunlight. … It seemed to me that nature surely would not have built a creature so beautiful, and so carefully designed for such conditions, merely to be an object of idle observation. … I was inclined rather to think that nature had built it thus in order that all the pleasure which can be derived from bathing at once in sunlight and in water might be enjoyed by one creature in the fullest measure. (177)

Or consider this passage, in which he describes the glory of the daylight view:

With the abolition of the plants from the realm of souls how sparsely scattered would sensibility be in the whole realm of nature … ! How different it all is, if the plants have souls and are capable of feeling! … Is it not more beautiful and glorious to think that the living trees of the forest burn like torches uplifted towards the heaven? To be sure, we can only think this; we do not directly see anything of these soul-flames of nature; but since we can think it, why are we not willing to? (180)

We see here a culmination and synthesis of Goethe’s poetic imagery and Schelling’s Naturphilosophie; it is a rebirth of the religious view of nature, and perhaps one of the earliest forerunners of the ecological worldview that, in Skolimowski’s words, sees “the world as a sanctuary.”^8 We find even stronger evidence of this in Fechner’s discussion of the earth-soul.

According to Fechner, plant-souls are the most direct indicators of the overall panpsychic nature of the world. He explains this in On the Soul-Question:

[B]elief in the plant soul is just a little instance of the general situation … , for in this whole question the least and the greatest things are closely connected. … I considered that in the little soul of the plant I had found a little handle by which faith in the greatest things could be more easily hoisted to the big pedestal. (1861/1946: 138–139)

And, as he states in Nanna, “the decision as to whether the plants are animated or not decides many other questions and determines the whole outlook upon nature” (1848/1946: 163).

Of course, for Fechner this “whole outlook” is a panpsychic one in which every thing and every part of every thing is ensouled. Regarding plants, he argues that “there are as many individuals as there are leaves on the tree, nay, there are in fact as many as there are cells” (204). These individuals, whether cells or whole plants, are not simply part of some larger mind; they possess souls in their own right: “It is only an independent animate life we have in mind when we enquire about the souls of plants.” (165) Each thing has its own unique view on the world and interacts with the world as a unitary mind.

Perhaps more important than Fechner’s elaborations on the plant-soul was his discussion of what James called the “superhuman consciousness”—the mind of society, of the Earth, of the stars, and of the cosmos. Fechner was the first scientist-philosopher to examine these possibilities seriously and to regard them as actual features of reality. James provides an excellent summary:

In ourselves, visual consciousness goes with our eyes, tactile consciousness with our skin. … They come together in some sort of relation and combination in the more inclusive consciousness which each of us names his self. Quite similarly, says Fechner, we must suppose that my consciousness [and yours, though] they keep separate and know nothing of each other, are yet known and used together in a higher consciousness, that of the human race. … Similarly, the whole human and animal kingdoms come together as conditions of a consciousness of still wider scope. This combines in the soul of the earth with the consciousness of the vegetable kingdom, which in turn contributes … to that of the whole solar system, and so on from synthesis to synthesis and height to height, till an absolutely universal consciousness is reached. (1909: 155–156)

So here is a view of mind as a nested hierarchy, reaching from the lowest forms to the highest. It is, as James said, “a vast analogical series, in which the basis of the analogy consists of facts directly observable in ourselves” (156).

Fechner’s view is often described as a form of psycho-physical parallelism of the sort that Spinoza proposed. But Fechner went further, laying out an explicitly pluralist panpsychism. James embraced it wholeheartedly, while emphasizing that all these levels of hierarchy in the world possess, individually, their own minds:

The vaster orders of mind go with the vaster orders of body. The entire earth on which we live must have, according to Fechner, its own collective consciousness. So must each sun, moon, and planet; so must the whole solar system have its own wider consciousness, in which the consciousness of our earth plays one part. So has the entire starry system as such its consciousness … . (152–153)

The limit in this sequence, the mind of the cosmos, Fechner took as God.

Of special interest is Fechner’s emphasis on the Earth as a consciousness and spirit, an “angel” that supports all life. His vision would seem to draw from the Platonic notion of the Earth as a god, and it anticipated the Gaia concept of the 1970s, in which the Earth is seen as a living, sentient being. The idea of an Earth-soul was critical to Fechner: “Just as man is the starting point … for belief in animate character of all other creatures, so is the animated earth the starting point … for belief in the animate character of all other stars.” (1861: 150) As with plants, he starts with a Continuity argument: “[I]s not the earth in its form and content, like our bodies, and like the bodies also of all animals and plants … ?” (155) He then lays out four points in support of this view. First he notes that the Earth is a unified system, relatively closed and well defined. Second, it develops, like living organisms, from within; it is relatively self-sufficient, and it contains its own means for self-realization. Third, it is a complex being, vastly more so than any mere plant or animal. Last, it is a unique member of the class of planetary bodies, which constitute a kind of “species” of things.

Beyond these arguments, Fechner clearly adopted a spiritual and reverential attitude toward the Earth. It was not just some animated rock; it was his sacred home:

One spring morning I went out early: the fields were greening, the birds were singing, the dew glistening; … it was only a tiny fraction of the earth, only a tiny moment of its existence, and yet, as I comprised more and more in the range of my vision, it seemed to me not only so beautiful but so true and evident that it is an angel, so rich and fresh and blooming, and at the same time so stable and unified, moving in the heavens, turning wholly towards heaven its animated face, and bearing me with it to that same heaven—so beautiful and true that I wondered how men’s notion could be so perverted as to see in the earth only a dry clod … . (1861: 153)

Such a divine being deserves our most profound reverence. As James said (1909: 153), Fechner “treats the earth as our special human guardian angel; we can pray to the earth as men pray to their saints.”

Though relying chiefly on analogy, Fechner used a variety of arguments to make his panpsychist claims. Above we have seen a number of arguments by Continuity, but he employed at least four other arguments:

In-Dwelling Powers—Plants have the power to take ordinary matter and make it living, and in this sense they have more “vital force” than do animals. “Out of raw earth, water, air, and decaying substances the plant makes glorious forms and colors.” (1848: 184)
Non-Emergence—The Earth must be sentient, because “animate beings cannot arise from inanimate” (1861: 156).
Design—The cosmos creates ensouled beings in order to attain full and complete enjoyment of existence. (Recall the passage on the water lily.)
Theological—Fechner admitted that there is an element of faith involved here, writing that “however we begin it or however we end, we shall not be able to discover and impart any exact proofs” (135). He noted that even in traditional theology the Spirit of God is everywhere: “If one concedes a God who is at once omnipresent, omniscient, and omnipotent, then in a certain sense the universal animation of the world by God is already admitted.” (1848: 163–164)

In the end, Fechner was, after all, a hard-headed rationalist. He spoke not as a poet, not as an artist or mystic, but as an empirical scientist drawing reasonable conclusions about the world. He made clear that his entire philosophical system was intended as a literal truth of reality: “All this is not metaphorical, is not an hypothesis: it is a simple and literal statement of how things are.” (1861: 153) Evidently it was a compelling vision, at least to certain prominent scientists. The Dutch physicist Hendrik Lorentz stated, in a letter of 1915, that he explicitly endorsed Fechner’s psycho-physical parallelism:

[T]he mental and the material are inviolably tied to one another, they are two sides of the same thing. The material world is a way in which the Weltgeist appears, since the smallest particle of matter has a soul, or whatever one chooses to call it. This is all closely tied to Fechner’s views … and I think that we have to assume something similar. (in Heidelberger 2004: 178)

Albert Einstein concurred, stating in a 1922 letter that relativity theory was fully compatible with Fechner’s views: “To guard against the collision of the various sorts of realities’ with which physics and psychology deal, Spinoza and Fechner invented the doctrine of psychophysical parallelism, which, to be frank, satisfies me entirely.” (in Heidelberger 2004: 177)

5.3 Other Scientist-Philosophers of the Age

Among the German scientist-philosophers, Fechner was the outstanding proponent of a panpsychic worldview. However, a few other thinkers—important philosophers in their own right—merit discussion. They will be addressed here in the order in which their panpsychist views emerged.

R. Hermann Lotze (1817–1881), trained as a physician and a philosopher, saw merit in both mechanism and idealism, and yet he sought to avoid the more extreme claims of each. He saw that mechanistic materialism was coming to dominate the philosophical and cultural landscape, and he was deeply concerned about the loss of reverence and wonder in the world.

Lotze’s major work, Microcosmos (1856–1864), describes his comprehensive views on mind and matter. He prefaces the entire discussion by describing the antipathy between “mechanical science” and “Philosophy of the Feelings.” Here we find one of the first explicit acknowledgments of two competing worldviews, two completely divergent platforms from which to understand the cosmos. As the mechanical view came to dominate, its weaknesses became apparent. The proponents of this view were becoming increasingly bold, even arrogant, and they showed utter disregard for the spiritual aspects of life. As Lotze explains, these people “estimate the truth of their new philosophic views in direct proportion to the degree of offensive hostility which [this view] exhibits toward everything that is held sacred by the living soul of man” (1856–1864/1971: iii). They have forgotten that the true nature of intellectual inquiry is to ultimately provide “one meaning”: “to trace an image of the world from which we may learn what we have to reverence as the true significance of existence” (ix). Mechanism disintegrates the harmony of the ancient cosmic order, and “the further advance of mechanical science begins to threaten with similar disintegration the smaller world, the Microcosm of man” (xv).

The mechanist philosophers seek to describe everything in terms of forces and laws, but they overlook that such things “are not the ultimate components of the threads that weave the texture of reality” (xii). The reality Lotze has in mind is a panpsychic reality, one rather similar to Leibniz’s monadology. Early in the book he briefly recounts the history of animism and its attribution of personal spirits to nature; he also examines its role in satisfying a deeper spiritual need of humanity—the need to feel at home in the cosmos. Mechanistic philosophy, according to Lotze, has taken people completely away from this primitive worldview, and he slowly leads the reader back toward acceptance of just such a world. In part II he introduces the notion that all matter has “a double life, appearing outwardly as matter, and as such manifesting … mechanical [properties, while] internally, on the other hand, moved mentally” (150). He speaks of this inner soul- or mental-life as an “absolute indivisibility” (157), and he proceeds to draw analogies between the soul and the indivisible atoms of matter.

In a very Leibnizian manner, Lotze proposes that in fact atoms are prime candidates for possessing an inner psyche: “We once again take for granted in the multitudinous connected atoms of the body that internal psychic life which … must be attributed to all matter.” (161) Lotze’s full panpsychist view is finally laid out in part III, where he makes his bid for “a thoroughgoing revolt of the heart against the coldness of a theory that transforms all the beauty and animation of forms into a rigid physico-psychical mechanism” (344). His panpsychism is founded on the principle of the indivisibility of the atom. Matter as “infinitely divisible extension” is “an illusion” (354); rather, matter consists of point-like atoms structured in a cohesive pattern by their respective forces. It is precisely this point-like nature of the atom that permits us to see it as a single unifying center of experience, with its own psychic life:

The indivisible unity of each of these simple beings [atoms] permits us to suppose that in it the impressions reaching it from without are condensed into modes of sensation and enjoyment. [As a result,] no part of being is any longer devoid of life and animation. (360)

Like the ancient Greeks, Lotze accepts that motion is ultimately attributable to such a psyche: “We must … in general allow and maintain that all motion of matter in space may be explained as the natural expression of the inner states of beings that seek or avoid one another with a feeling of their need.” (363)

The psychic lives of atoms join together to create the soul of the body. For Lotze this occurs in a very specific and fundamental process of two-way interaction. He explains that bi-directional interaction is in fact the very basis of ontology, both physical and mental. Kuelpe (1913: 168) comments on this aspect of Lotze’s philosophy: “We know real relations … only in the form of reciprocal action. Consequently the whole problem of ‘being’ narrows down to acquiring an understanding of reciprocal relations.” Lotze then claims that the soul, as a spiritual being, stands as an unchanging entity in relation to these changing reciprocal actions. Kuelpe adds this:

Consequently all things, whose unity we recognize and for which we presuppose real relations, must be considered after the analogy of our own inner being, as spirits or souls. According to this, our body is regarded by Lotze, as it was earlier by Leibniz, as a multiplicity of individual souls … . (171)

Kuelpe proposes that this “theory of reciprocal action is the most original and most important point” of Lotze’s metaphysics (173). It is undoubtedly a central aspect of his panpsychism, as it outlines an explanation for the combination problem that faces any monad-like ontology.

Lotze acknowledges the prima facie improbability of his view:

Who could endure the thought that in the dust trodden by our feet, in the … cloth that forms our clothing, in the materials shaped into all sorts of utensils … , there is everywhere present the fullness of animated life? (1856–1864: 361)

And yet this view fundamentally changes one’s outlook on the world: “dust is dust to him alone whom it inconveniences.” Ultimately it is the “beauty of the living form [that] is made to us more intelligible by this hypothesis” (366). And this, says Lotze, is precisely why we must accept his view. Science itself neither wants nor needs panpsychism; rather, it is needed by the human spirit, to make the nature of the soul comprehensible.

Eduard von Hartmann (1842–1906) further developed Schopenhauer’s system of the world as will and idea, drawing in elements of Leibniz, Schelling, and Hegel into a doctrine of spiritual monism. In his most famous work, Die Philosophie des Unbewussten (Philosophy of the Unconscious), published in 1869, he articulates a view of the unconscious will as the cause of all things. The fact that matter is resolvable into will and idea leads Hartmann to conclude “the essential likeness of Mind and Matter” (1869/1950, volume 2: 81). Like Schopenhauer, he holds to a dynamist conception of matter, of the will as manifest in elementary atomic forces:

Hencewith is the radical distinction between spirit and matter abolished; their difference consists only in higher or lower forms of manifestations of the same essence. … The identity of mind and matter [becomes] elevated to a scientific cognition, and that, too, not by killing the spirit but by vivifying matter. (180)

Hartmann continues by noting that previous attempts at monism were extreme: materialism denied spirit, and idealism denied matter. He sees his monism as a system that does justice to both.

Like Fechner, Hartmann sees each cell of the organic body as endowed with consciousness. The animal “has as many (more or less separate) consciousnesses as he has nerve-centers, nay, even as he has vital cells” (225). These individual consciousnesses are united through intimate communication:

Only because the one part of my brain has a direct communication with the other is the consciousness of the two parts unified; and could we unite the brains of two human beings by a path of communication equivalent to the cerebral fibers, both would no longer have two, but one consciousness. (224)

Communication and exchange thus resolve the combination problem, a view that recalls Diderot’s claim.

Hartmann’s work was prescient but unfortunately not very influential. His focus on the unconscious reappears, without credit, in the writings of Ernst Haeckel and Friedrich Paulsen. Generally speaking, his overall synthesis of ideas was underappreciated by later philosophers, in Germany and elsewhere.

The Austrian physicist Ernst Mach (1838–1916) was known primarily for his scientific advances, but he produced some important philosophical writings in the early 1880s. He made substantial contributions to the philosophy of science, and he was an early proponent of logical positivism. For Mach, the primary aim of science was to predict and describe, and only secondarily to explain. Epistemologically he was strongly empiricist.

Mach developed a neutral monist philosophy in which the primary substance of existence was neither mind nor matter but rather “sensations.” That led him rather suddenly to a panpsychist conception of reality. “In adolescence,” Hamilton recounts (1990: 127), “Mach was a Kantian, but then he reacted against the thing-in-itself, experiencing a panpsychic epiphany in which (to quote Mach) ‘the world with my ego suddenly appeared to me as one coherent mass of sensations.’” It was around this time, in 1863, that Mach wrote the following:

Let’s confess it straightaway! We cannot reasonably discover any external side to atoms, so if we are to think anything at all, we must attribute an internal side to them, an inwardness analogous to our own souls. In fact, how could a soul originate as a combination of atoms in an organism, if its germ were not already contained in the atom? (in Heidelberger 2004: 157)

This is a striking statement: Science reveals no “exterior” to atoms at all, only various fields of force. If they are to be real, then, they must have an interior, along the lines of our own mentality. And furthermore, since human minds cannot emerge from no-mind, it must reside in the atomic parts. Thus we find two compressed arguments for panpsychism in a single passage.

A decade later, Mach had apparently acquired something of an adverse reputation for such ideas. In his lecture notes of 1872, he cited a panpsychist statement by astrophysicist Karl Zöllner: “Sensitivity is a general attribute of matter, more general than mobility.” Mach then added this: “I myself have been reproached for saying that.” (in ibid.: 159)

Nonetheless, Mach persisted in his views, which were developed most fully in The Science of Mechanics (1883). “Properly speaking,” he wrote, “the world is not composed of ‘things’ … but of colors, tones, pressures, spaces, times, in short what we ordinarily call individual sensations.” (1883/1942: 579) On first glance the view that all things are sensations recalls a conventional Berkelian idealism, but then it becomes clear that there is no observing mind involved. One might call it a pansensist view, but one clearly different from the pansensism of Telesio or Campanella; they held that all things do sense (i.e., have the power of sensing), whereas Mach holds that all things in themselves are sensations. But who or what is doing the sensing? Or are things simply subjectless sensations? At one time he accepted the idea of a personal ego, but eventually he dropped it. He thus seems to ultimately have argued for a theory of “objective sensations,” independent of any so-called ego or subject.^9

If Mach is less than clear on the details of his pansensism, he is unambiguous about his monist ontology and its panpsychist implications. “The fundamental character of all these [human] instincts,” he writes, “is the feeling of our oneness and sameness with nature; a feeling … which certainly has a sound basis” (559). He goes on to characterize both mechanistic monism and animistic monism as inadequate worldviews:

[O]ur judgment has grown more sober. … Both [the mechanical and animistic mythologies] contain undue and fantastical exaggerations of an incomplete perception. Careful physical research will lead … to an analysis of our sensations. We shall then discover that our hunger is not so essentially different from the tendency of sulphuric acid for zinc, and our will not so greatly different from the pressure of a stone, as now appears. We shall again feel ourselves nearer nature, without its being necessary that we should resolve ourselves into a nebulous and mystical mass of molecules, or make nature a haunt of hobgoblins. (560)

Clearly Mach is sensitive to the close association between his view and primitive animism, and he wants to make nature sensate without introducing personal spirits. He seems to draw inspiration from Schopenhauer (note the comparison between “will” and “pressure of a stone”), if only implicitly, and we know from his other writings that he was highly influenced by Fechner. Mach equates the processes of nature with human inclinations and feelings, and his opposition to mechanistic ontology steers him toward a view of “nature as animate” rather than “human as mechanical.” His particular form of pansensism led the way for the soon-to-follow developments of James (radical empiricism) and Whitehead (process philosophy).

One of the first major philosophers to embrace Darwin’s theory of evolution was Ernst Haeckel (1834–1919). Haeckel, who developed the biogenetic law that ontogeny recapitulates phylogeny, quickly became known as the leading German Darwinist. He developed a monistic philosophy in which both evolution and the unity of all natural phenomena played major roles. His system was clearly panpsychist, even pantheist, and he strongly opposed the mysticism and irrationalism of Christianity.

Even in his first philosophical work, The History of Creation (1868), Haeckel vigorously promoted his monistic philosophy, using the theory of evolution as evidence. The unity and relatedness of all living things convinced him that all dualities were false, and especially that of body and mind. Furthermore, he argued, mind-body duality was a particular instance of the physical duality of matter and force (or energy), and hence that too was a false duality; body was equated with matter, mind was equated with energy, and all were intimately connected:

[B]ody and mind can, in fact, never be considered as distinct, but rather that both sides of nature are inseparably connected, and stand in the closest interaction. … The artificial discord between mind and body, between force and matter, … has been disposed of by the advances of natural science. (1868/1876: 487)

Science had now achieved what philosophy alone could not: compelling proof of the monist worldview. Truth was to be found in nature, and it was therefore “necessary to make a complete and honest return to Nature and to natural relations” (496). Natural science had proved the truth of evolution, and this theory promised great things for humanity: “[In the future] mankind … will follow the glorious career of progressive development, and attain a still higher degree of mental perfection.” (495)

Haeckel was explicitly panpsychist by 1892. In an article for The Monist he wrote: “One highly important principle of my monism seems to me to be, that I regard all matter as ensouled, that is to say as endowed with feeling (pleasure and pain) and motion.” (1892: 486) Here he offers one argument for panpsychism, namely that “all natural bodies possess determinate chemical properties,” the most important being that of “chemical affinity.” This affinity, Haeckel says, can be explained only “on the supposition that the molecules … mutually feel each other” (483). Elsewhere he employs evolution on behalf of the Continuity argument, claiming that evolution shows “the essential unity of inorganic and organic nature” (1895: 3). Evolutionary monism strikes at the heart of both the religious worldview and the mechanical philosophy: “Our conception of Monism … is clear and unambiguous; … an immaterial living spirit is just as unthinkable as a dead, spiritless material; the two are inseparably combined in every atom.” (58)

Haeckel’s most famous work, The Riddle of the Universe (1899), was meant to be a popular book that would explain the essentials of the monistic view to the general public. It succeeded in becoming a best-seller in Europe—rare for a work of natural philosophy. Drawing on the latest developments in physics, Haeckel presented the case for his monism, then claimed that science had proved the conservation of mass, the conservation of energy, and the equality between matter and energy. In the end he arrived at a neutral-monist position in which his ultimate reality was “substance,” which possessed two simultaneous attributes: matter and energy. He embraced the term “force-matter,” which was functionally identical to our present-day “mass-energy.” This was something of a milestone in the history of monistic philosophy. From the earliest days of philosophy, when Empedocles argued that all reality was composed of four elements (fire, air, water, earth) and two forces (Love and Strife), philosophers had sensed that things like mass and energy were of fundamental importance, but the monists perennially had difficulty explaining just how these two entities were to be unified. Haeckel saw in evolutionary monism the resolution to many age-old problems in philosophy.

The specific resolution that Haeckel envisioned was equating mass with body and energy with spirit, then uniting these two pairs in an explicitly Spinozan manner. He made this case throughout The Riddle of the Universe: All living creatures, microbes included, possess “conscious psychic action.” The inorganic world also possesses an inherent psychic quality, though he took care to emphasize that this is “unconscious” rather than “conscious” mentality. This applied even to the atoms: “I conceive the elementary psychic qualities of sensation and will, which may be attributed to atoms, to be unconscious.” (1899/1929: 179)

One of Haeckel’s last major works, The Wonders of Life (1904), is primarily an elaboration of his previous ideas. In it, though, he refers to himself for the first time as a hylozoist, apparently fearing—unnecessarily—the connotation of consciousness with the term ‘panpsychism’. “Monism,” he writes, “is best expressed as hylozoism, in so far as this removes the antithesis of materialism and spiritualism (or mechanism and dynamism).” (88) And it is in this work that he first proposes a third fundamental attribute to his one substance—to matter and force he adds psychoma, or “general sensation.” This is his response to the charge that mere matter and force/energy are not in themselves “psychic” enough to account for mind. Paraphrasing and expanding on Goethe, he summarizes his view as follows: “(1) No matter without force and without sensation. (2) No force without matter and without sensation. (3) No sensation without matter and without force.” (465)

During Haeckel’s lifetime, philosophy and science had diverged to the point that he could be criticized by professional philosophers as a “mere scientist.” The conflict was exacerbated by his bold claims that natural science had solved problems that traditional philosophy found intractable. He drew the ire of major philosophers of the day, most notable among them Friedrich Paulsen (1846–1908). Paulsen was a panpsychist who had advocated a view that was substantially in agreement with Haeckel’s.^10 The root of the conflict seems to have lain in the fact that Haeckel’s primary training had been in biology and science, and that he had come rather late, but with spectacularly success, to philosophy—especially with The Riddle of the Universe. Paulsen disliked both Haeckel’s claim that evolutionary theory was the key to philosophical progress and his belief that religion and classical metaphysics had been defeated by natural science. The criticisms have some merit, but Paulsen’s disagreements seem to center more on professional competition than on substantial philosophy.

5.4 A Survey of the Field

Paulsen is an important figure in his own right. His 1892 Introduction to Philosophy was the first work in history to present a detailed academic survey of panpsychism and the first to review and summarize a number of historically important positions. In that book Paulsen also articulated his own views on panpsychism—views that were substantially in line with those of Haeckel, Fechner, Schopenhauer, and Leibniz.

As a German philosopher, Paulsen’s emphasis was, naturally, on German thought of the 1800s. In addition to Fechner, Schopenhauer, and Leibniz, he covered Lotze, Schelling, Wundt,^11 von Nägeli, and Zöllner, but he also referred to the panpsychist arguments of Spinoza, Hoeffding, and du Bois-Reymond. Paulsen’s survey is far from exhaustive; he mentions early Greek thinkers only in passing, he makes no reference at all to Hellenistic philosophy, Renaissance naturalism, or French vitalist materialism, and he inexplicably ignores the work of Hartmann and Mach. Despite these weaknesses, Introduction to Philosophy is an important book, presenting virtually every extant argument for panpsychism. Panpsychism is not the entire focus of the book, but it is clearly a central theme, forming the core of chapter 1 and persisting as a primary theme throughout. Many of Paulsen’s formulations of existing arguments are still advocated and debated today, and thus it is worthwhile to examine his general case for panpsychism in some detail.

Paulsen begins by attacking the basis of materialism. He claims that the materialistic theory—characterized as the theory that “all reality is corporeal or the manifestation of corporeality”—is a fundamentally inadequate conception. He immediately adopts an idealist standpoint: “Bodies have [only] phenomenal existence. … Their entire essence is a content of perception.” (1892/1895: 75) He then attributes to materialist philosophers two possible views: that “states of consciousness are effects of physical states” (reductive materialism) and that “states of consciousness … are nothing but physical states of the brain” (identity theory). He dismisses the second view, that “thoughts are movements in the brain,” by claiming that such a statement has no meaning. One is then obliged, he argues, to consider that the physical and the psychical bear some sort of relationship to one another. This relationship must be either interactionist (and hence causal) or parallelist (and therefore acausal). Materialism, Paulsen claims, typically opts for the former. But this involves a “transformation of motion or force into thought,” resulting in a “destruction of energy” in the physical realm—a recognized impossibility. Similarly, a transference from the psychical to the physical would appear as “creation out of nothing” and hence also impossible. Thus, one is forced to conclude that a form of parallelism must be true.

Parallelism, or acausality, logically assumes that the mental doesn’t affect the physical, and conversely that the physical doesn’t affect the mental. The first condition leads one to the view that “the living body is an automaton” (87), albeit a complex and sophisticated one. Of the second condition, Paulsen states that psychical events, such as a particular sensation, must have a cause. Since the cause cannot be physical—under the conditions of parallelism—it must be psychical. In other words, mental events are caused only by preceding events of a like nature.

Paulsen concludes, along with Spinoza and Fechner, that physical events move along in corporeal causal chains, and mental events move along in psychical causal chains. The two chains simply proceed together; they are “concomitant.” Furthermore, Paulsen claims that, of the two chains, the psychical is the more fundamental, because it is “the representation of reality as it is by itself and for itself” (92). He attributes this advance to Leibniz. And it justifies his claim that such a view is a form of idealism.

Paulsen then addresses the question of panpsychism: In which physical structures does this parallel chain of events exist? Like Schopenhauer, he begins introspectively. Each person is directly aware of his own mental states. He then extends this by analogy to other human beings and deduces the existence of others’ mental states. The crucial question is “How far may this inference be extended?” The commonly accepted view of the time was to include all animals, but he notes that there is no sharp dividing line between animals and plants, and that therefore the rational conclusion is that plants possess an inner life as well. He notes additional similarities between animals and plants: in aspects of nutrition, cellular structure, genetic reproduction, development and death, even language. In considering whether such a position constitutes a proof of the plant-soul, Paulsen quickly turns the tables on the materialist: “To deny that there is [a plant-soul], would, to say the least, require some proof.” (96) “The burden of proof,” he argues, “rests on him who denies the validity of the analogical syllogism. He must show why it is not valid here, otherwise his negation is arbitrary.” (98)

Eventually Paulsen arrives at the main point of contention: the inorganic world. In brief, his arguments are the following:

(1) There is “no difference in substance” between organic and inorganic bodies; they are “composed of the same ingredients” (the Evolutionary Continuity argument). Developments in biology and chemistry had confirmed this by the late 1800s, and the theory of vitalism—that living beings are composed of some unique material or substance—was becoming discredited. “The same forces act in inorganic as well as in organic bodies.” (104)
(2) The question “Whence did psychical life arise?” (100) raises the classic emergence issue. The sudden appearance of a mental realm “would be an absolute ‘world-riddle’; it would mean a creation out of nothing.” This Non-Emergence argument is supported by natural science. Since scientists accept that organic beings are formed out of inorganic material, and hence no new “vital substance” appears, they should accept the same reasoning and allow that psychical life of the higher organisms is composed of lower elements of inorganic mentality. And within the realm of living beings, the theory of evolution supports this view: “The process of psychical evolution runs parallel with the evolution of organic life.” (143)
(3) Paulsen addresses the argument that living beings exhibit “spontaneous activity,” and that this is an indication of an inner sense. He points out that chemistry and physics demonstrate that even the smallest and simplest pieces of matter are active, self-organizing, and responsive (the Indwelling Powers argument): “Your inert, rigid matter … is a phantom that owes its existence, not to observation, but to conceptual speculation. … Modern science has utterly discarded that idea of such absolutely dead and rigid bodies. Its molecules and atoms are forms of the greatest inner complexity and mobility.” (101–102) This, of course, is true, and aligns with our current thinking.
(4) Schopenhauer’s Continuity argument, based on first principles, holds that all things appear to us as sensations or sensory phenomena—that is, as ideas. But, like humans, things must also have an inner nature. Thus, Paulsen informs us, “that which appears to us as a body must be something in and for itself” (105). We know firsthand that human bodies have an inner sense, and logically “analogous phenomena point to analogous inner being.” Therefore, “to every body which … appears as a relatively complete system of phenomena and activities, [the logical thinker] ascribes a relatively complete inner life like his own.”

Like Fechner, Paulsen applied similar reasoning to large-scale systems such as the Earth, concluding that it is clearly reasonable to ascribe them an inner life as well. Ultimately he acknowledged that such arguments stand on a different plane than conventional scientific or materialist ones: “these thoughts are not matters of scientific knowledge. … This is no place for real scientific work.” (109) “Still,” he continued, “they have their value.” The world-soul, which he saw as a logical necessity, can serve as a kind of non-religious deity, arrived at by reasoning rather than ancient theological texts. More important, “this view destroys the negative dogmatism of a purely physical view of the world” (110). Conversely, the hallmark of an “empty and low life” is the development of “a nihilistic conception of life, [and] a loss of reverence for moral and spiritual greatness” (69). Inevitably, “such a nihilistic view of life naturally tends to a materialistic philosophy” (70). For Paulsen, materialism was an indicator of weakness and deficiency; panpsychism was a sign of greatness and depth.

5.5 Nietzsche and the Will to Power

No philosopher placed more emphasis on the philosophy of greatness than Friedrich Nietzsche (1844–1900). If Paulsen saw panpsychism as the path to greatness, Nietzsche strode that path with the utmost flair and conviction. The foundational concept of this approach was his ultimate metaphysical principle, der Wille zur Macht—the will to power. In humans, according to Nietzsche, this power is manifest as the consummate life-affirming drive, an inclination to achieve dignity, mastery and greatness. But it is also the ground-source of the flourishing of life generally, and most broadly, the force by which all things in nature exert and expand their claim on existence. A strong argument can be made that the will to power was ultimately a form of panpsychism, but one that he developed only cautiously.

The evolution of Nietzsche’s thinking on panpsychism constitutes a fascinating study of the emergence of one of his central themes. It seems that he was strongly predisposed to something like panpsychism from his teenage years, though initially it was more a version of classical pansensism than a system based on the will. From late 1865, when Nietzsche was 21 years old, the influence of Schopenhauer’s panpsychist metaphysics became pronounced, ultimately looming over of all of his writings. Parallel to his thinking on panpsychism was his development of the will-to-power thesis. For several years these two concepts existed side by side; not until in 1884, when he was 40, did they become unified.

The strikingly hostile reception to Nietzsche’s panpsychism among recent commentators is directly relevant to the present study. His view is denied, defamed, denigrated, and ignored—despite considerable evidence to the contrary. Indeed, this is a case study in present-day attitudes toward panpsychism generally.

Let me begin by presenting the evidence for Nietzsche’s panpsychism in his own words. It is extensive, but most of his statements on the topic occur not in his published works but in the Nachlass, his unpublished notebooks. Consistent with their unpublished status, they are also unpolished—often mere sentence fragments, and cryptic ones at that. This is perhaps the critics’ strongest point; had he truly been committed to panpsychism, they say, he surely would have emphasized it in his published books. But I do not find that argument very compelling. Nietzsche’s primary concern seems to have been humanity—specifically our values, our religious beliefs, our societal norms, and our human condition. His metaphysics is developed primarily as it applies to human beings and their place in the world. At least toward the end of his short productive life, he seems not to have developed a systematic metaphysics of reality in general—at least, not to the point where he was ready to compose a book on the subject.^12 With more time, he might have tackled the subject directly. As it is, we must reconstruct his thinking largely on the basis of the notebook entries.

His earliest known reference to panpsychism comes from 1861, when Nietzsche was only 17 years old. In an autobiographical essay, he notes in passing that “the ‘spiritless’ [Geistlose] cannot exist—all that is, lives.”^13 One may be inclined to dismiss such a passage as mere youthful hylozoistic musing, but it does indicate a general sympathy to the idea, and from an early age.

More than a decade passed before Nietzsche’s next series of comments on the subject. In his notebooks of 1872 we read the following:

Is there such a thing as an unconscious inference? Does matter infer? It has feelings and it strives for its individual being.

What if thoughts were the essence of things? What if memory and sensation were the matter of things?

The impact, the influence of one atom upon another is likewise something which presupposes sensation [Empfindung].^14 Something which is intrinsically alien can have no effect upon anything else. What is difficult is not awakening sensation, but awakening consciousness. Yet this is nevertheless explicable if everything is sensate. [In this case,] whether larger or smaller, these sensation complexes would be called ‘will’.^15

Notable here is his recognition that a pansensist universe would solve the emergence problem. Also significant is his connection, already at this early date, between the sensation-complexes and the will.

In the same year, 1872, Nietzsche published his first major work, The Birth of Tragedy—a book that contains some suggestive though ambiguous passages relating to panpsychism. He writes of the “omnipotent art impulses” in nature, and notes that the more closely he perceives them the more he is “impelled to the metaphysical assumption [of] the truly existent primal unity” which is “eternally suffering and contradictory” (section 4). A few lines later he speaks of “suffering, primal and eternal, the sole ground of the world.” These thoughts recur in section 5, where the “primal unity” is said to experience “pain,” and the “heart of the world” is portrayed as “primordial contradiction and primordial pain, together with primordial pleasure.” All this points to a kind of sensitivity at the core of being. Also suggestive is Nietzsche’s extended quotation of Schopenhauer’s panpsychist masterpiece The World as Will and Idea in the same section.^16

In the following year, 1873, we find this notebook entry: “I have nothing but sensation [Empfindung] and idea [Vorstellung]. … That which is, is sensation and idea.” (KGW 26[11])^17 Three years later, in 1876, we find the first mention of the phrase Wille zur Macht (will to power) in the notebooks (KGW 23[63]); it would not appear in published form until Thus Spoke Zarathustra in 1883. As was noted above, there was no initial linkage between will to power and anything like panpsychism.

The will-to-power thesis was slow to develop. A second appearance in the notebooks would not occur until 1880 (KGW 4[239]), some four years after its debut. But related terms did gradually emerge. Daybreak (1881), for example, includes several mentions of a “feeling of power” (Gefühl der Macht).^18 The Gay Science (1882) includes a reference to “the doctrine of the feeling of power” in section 13, and in section 310 Nietzsche examines “will and wave,” in which the crashing ocean waves exhibit many signs of purposive activity.^19

In Zarathustra (1883) we find the first publication of the phrase “will to power”: “A tablet hangs over every people. … Behold, it is the voice of their will to power.” (1883/1954: 170) Later in the work there is an implied connection to Schopenhauer:

Where I found the living, there I found will to power. … Only where there is life is there also will: not will to life but—thus I teach you—will to power. (226–227)

Schopenhauer’s notion of the world as will is elaborated in his primary work as a specific form of will, namely will to life: “And since what the will wills is always life … it is all one and a mere pleonasm if, instead of simply saying ‘the will,’ we say, ‘the will to life’” (1819/1995: 177).^20 Nietzsche rejected this qualification, even as he initially found will to power only in living things. Life wills power, not merely more life.

Had this been his final word on the matter, we would have had will to power as a strictly organic phenomenon; in Zarathustra, only living things will power. In recent literature, this interpretation is called the “biological will-to-power.” Some current commentators believe that this was always Nietzsche’s view, or even that he only ever meant it to apply to human beings (“anthropocentric will-to-power”). My claim here, by contrast, is for ontological will-to-power^21: will to power as an essential feature of reality. Only this suffices to demonstrate a panpsychist outlook.

Up to Zarathustra, we have no evidence of ontological will-to-power in the writings of Nietzsche. But a contemporaneous notebook entry suggests that something comparable is forthcoming. In an important 1883 entry, Nietzsche comments on the lack of grounding for the assumption that matter is non-experiential: “Substance devoid of feeling is only a hypothesis! No experience [of this]! Sensation [Empfindung] is thus a property of substance: there are sensitive substances.” (KGW 24[10]) Then in the next year, 1884, we find a decisive and unambiguous notebook entry: “reduction of generation to the will to power (it must also be present in the appropriated inorganic matter!)” (KGW 26[274]). This is our first indication that a shift has occurred; will to power is now seen as residing in matter itself. If the will is now an ontological feature of reality, as it was for Schopenhauer, then a form of panpsychism obtains.

In 1885, several of Nietzsche’s notebook entries confirm the ontological view. Consider this clear and explicit statement from Writings from the Late Notebooks: “that it is the will to power which guides the inorganic world as well, or rather, that there is no inorganic world” (Nietzsche 2003: 15). Most of the relevant entries from that year, though, appear in the posthumous book The Will to Power (1906/1967):

The only force that exists is of the same kind as that of the will. (section 490)

The victorious concept of “force” … still needs to be completed: an inner will must be ascribed to it, which I designate as “will to power.” (section 619)

We cannot think of an attraction divorced from an intention. (section 627)

The drive to approach—and the drive to thrust something back are the bond, in both the inorganic and the organic world. The entire distinction is prejudice. (section 655)

There is absolutely no other kind of causality than that of will upon will. (section 658)

Perhaps the most dramatic such statement appears in the final entry in the book (still from 1885):

This world is the will to power—and nothing more! And you yourselves are also this will to power—and nothing more! (section 1067).

But there is nothing on the ontological will-to-power thesis in Nietzsche’s published works until Beyond Good and Evil (1886), wherein we find the extended and hotly debated section 36, in which he seems to endorse the ontological view. But his tone raises questions, providing an opening for his critics. He writes in provisional language (“Suppose … ”) and speaks of an “experiment”: What, he asks, if “the so-called mechanistic (or ‘material’) world” held the same rank as “a more primitive form of the world of affects in which everything still lies contained in a powerful unity” before it became “organic”—“as a kind of instinctive life,” as a “pre-form of life.”^22 If the will has causal power, he writes, “then we have to make the experiment of positing the causality of the will hypothetically as the only one. … In short, one has to risk the hypothesis whether … all mechanical occurrences are not, insofar as a force is active in them, will force, effects of will.” The section concludes as follows:

Granted finally that one succeeded in explaining our entire instinctual life as the development and ramification of one basic form of will—as will to power, as is my theory—[then] one would have acquired the right to define all efficient force unequivocally as: will to power. The world seen from within, the world described and defined according to its “intelligible character”—it would be “will to power” and nothing else.

I won’t relate here the many alternate interpretations of this section.^23 On my view, the suppositional form and the “experimental” language do not alter the basic commitment to the message. It is rather like an atheist saying “Suppose there were no God” and then laying out his case. It is a rhetorical tactic, nothing more.

We find two other clues later in Beyond Good and Evil. Section 186 speaks assertively of “a world whose essence is will to power”—a relatively clear and explicit phrase. But then we have section 259, which has been used by some proponents of biological will-to-power, and against the ontological view. Nietzsche writes that “life simply is will to power,” and of “the will to power, which is after all the will of life.” But this is no contradiction: On the ontological view, everything, life included, is will to power. If on certain occasions he emphasizes this fact, it doesn’t exclude the notion that nonlife is also will to power. He doesn’t say that only life is will to power. He simply observes that life, like everything, is such a will at its core.

A second published reference to the ontological view appears in On the Genealogy of Morals (1887). The primary passage comes in the second essay, but early in the work we read that “a quantum of force is equivalent to a quantum of drive, will, effect—more, it is nothing other than precisely this very driving, willing, effecting” (34). Nietzsche then cites an inorganic example—lightning—to press his point, followed by references to the scientific concept of force, the atom, and the thing-in-itself. The main passage, though, comes in section 12 of the second essay:

… all aims, all uses are merely signs indicating that a will to power has mastered something less powerful than itself and impressed the meaning of a function upon it in accordance with its own interests. So the entire history of a “thing,” an organ, a custom may take the form of an extended chain of signs … . (58)

The meaning of this becomes clearer as we progress:

I emphasize this central perspective of historical method all the more since it is fundamentally opposed to the prevailing instincts and tastes of the time, which would rather accommodate the absolute arbitrariness, even mechanistic senselessness of all that happens, than the theory of a will to power manifesting itself in all things and events. (59)

The “senselessness” of mechanistic philosophy derives from the fact that it posits nothing, no motive force, at the center of material reality. There is no interior at all. This notion is reflected in the contemporaneous book 5 of The Gay Science, in which Nietzsche says “an essentially mechanical world would be an essentially meaningless world” (section 373).

The year 1887 also continued the string of relevant notebook entries. In The Will to Power we read:

“Being” as the universalization of the concept “life”. … Being—we have no idea of it apart from the idea of “living.”—How can anything dead “be”? (sections 581–582)

In Writings from the Late Notebooks (Nietzsche 2003) we find this: “what appears to be ‘purposiveness’ … is merely the consequence of the will to power played out in everything that happens” (156). And this: “the ‘will to power’ expresses itself in the interpretation, in the way that force is consumed” (199). Will to power seems to be a primordial aspect of the world: “the ‘will to power’ cannot have become” (207). And further: “all ‘purposes,’ ‘goals,’ ‘meanings,’ are only modes of expression and metamorphoses of the single will that inheres in all that happens, the will to power” (217).

Into his last productive year, 1888, Nietzsche continued such observations with unwavering consistency. In one of his final published works, Antichrist, he virtually defines will to power as the ultimate good: “What is good? All that enhances the feeling of power, the Will to Power” (section 2). The Will to Power contains several reiterations of the ontological view:

Every atom affects the whole of being. … That is why I call it a quantum of “will to power.” (section 634)

The will to power not a being, not a becoming, but a pathos—the most elemental fact from which a becoming and effecting first emerge. (section 635)

[E]very center of force—and not only man—construes all the rest of the world from its own viewpoint, i.e. measures, feels, forms, according to its own force. … My idea is that every specific body strives to become master over all space and to extend its force (—its will to power) … . (section 636)

[A]ll driving force is will to power, that there is no other physical, dynamic or psychic force except this. (section 688)

The will to accumulate force. … Should we not be permitted to assume this will as a motive cause in chemistry, too?—and in the cosmic order? (section 689)

[L]ife is merely a special case of the will to power. (section 692)

[T]he innermost essence of being is will to power … . (section 693)

And then the last such entry (2003: 259):

That will to power in which I recognize the ultimate grounds and character of all change … .

Such is the evidence. Objectively considered, the case for ontological will-to-power—that is, for panpsychism—seems clear enough. Nietzsche’s lifelong sympathy, the extensive notebook entries (documented over the final five years of his productive life), and the occasional published references all point to this conclusion. His general acceptance of Schopenhauer as his “great teacher”^24 is another clue, as is his high regard for the panpsychist pre-Socratic philosophers. Galen Strawson (2015b) is certainly sympathetic to this conclusion; that Nietzsche held that “reality is suffused with—if it doesn’t consist of—mentality in some form or sense” he calls “very probably true” (11). On the strength of the primary evidence, it would be difficult to come to any other determination.

Or so one would think. Somehow, though, mainstream thinking on Nietzsche disagrees—and strongly. A review of the recent literature exposes the striking fact that nearly every recent commentator opposes the ontological view, and dismisses any talk of panpsychism in the strongest possible terms. This phenomenon is highly revealing as a statement on panpsychism generally.

The tone was set in 1950, when Walter Kaufmann, in an influential book titled Nietzsche: Philosopher, Psychologist, Antichrist, concluded that “the projection of the will to power from the human sphere to the cosmos is an afterthought—an extreme conjecture which is not substantiated by the evidence and at variance with Nietzsche’s own critical principles” (367). Later, in his entry on Nietzsche in The Encyclopedia of Philosophy, Kaufmann put it even more bluntly: “As a metaphysical theory about the universe or ultimate reality, the doctrine need not be taken seriously, not even in an effort to understand Nietzsche.” (1967/1972: 510) Nehamas (1985: 75) clearly agrees, calling the ontological view “horrible,” a “wildly implausible picture,” and “unflinchingly obscure.” By 1990, Maudemarie Clark was ready to launch an all-out attack, arguing that the ontological view is not “worthy of serious consideration” (209), that there is “overwhelming reason to deny that Nietzsche accepts” the view (213), and that Nietzsche himself “pretty much admits [that it is] only interpretation” (221). Poellner (1995: 286) simply states that “this [ontological] model is itself not a coherent one.”

Things did not improve in the new millennium; in fact they got worse. Richardson (2000: 114) finds the “vitalist” ontological view “unbelievable,” something that “involve[s] a confused projection of human cognitive powers into places they simply can’t be.” Williams (2001: 77) states, flatly, “I interpret will to power nonmetaphysically, noncosmologically, and nonontologically.” For Moore (2002: 43), ontological will-to-power is “anthropomorphic” and “reminiscent of Leibniz’s pan-animism.” Bittner (2003: xxi) castigates Nietzsche for being “somewhat cavalier” and writes that the ontological view represents a kind of “mummification” of thought; it is “really sunk” and has “no chance of being true.” For Richardson (2004: 51), it is merely a “useful fiction,” a “metaphor or image.” The literal view is “incredible” and an “apparent absurdity” (64). Stack (2005: 198) finds the crucial section 36 of Beyond Good and Evil to be “a completely suppositional Gedanken-experiment” that lays out a “deliberately constructed exoteric myth.” It is “an elaborate, cleverly devised deception” and “cunningly misleading.” Porter (2006: 551) finds the ontological view “deeply anthropomorphic” and “too fantastical even to imagine.” Mincing no words, Janaway (2007: 153) calls it an “appalling embarrassment,” asserting that defenders of the panpsychist interpretation have “a virtually impossible task” and that section 36 is “not really a literally meant argument at all.”

The past few years have brought more of the same. Young (2010: 545) says there is “nothing more anthropomorphic” than the ontological view, calling it “obviously false.” Clark and Dudrick (2012: 237) declare the view “a nonstarter,” “laughable,” and “obviously implausible.” For Endries and Pichler (2013: 105) the “supposedly central ‘doctrine’” is “purely virtual.” Leiter (2013: 594) calls the ontological view “silly,” “unimportant,” and (four times on the same page) “crackpot.” Loeb (2015) at least tries to be objective, writing that the widespread “interpretive hostility” to the ontological view “derives from a misunderstanding of this concept as panpsychist” (!). Surprisingly, Loeb asserts that section 36 of Beyond Good and Evil is “actually … a refutation of panpsychism” (85), merely a “counterfactual thought experiment” that involves a “confused projection of human psychology” (72). In the end, he writes, “Nietzsche’s naturalistic methodology commits him to rejecting panpsychism as an anthropomorphic falsification of nature and reality.” (76)^25

What can we say about such statements? What thinking is operating behind such evidently deficient assessments?^26 I think we can reconstruct an implicit argument here: (1) Panpsychism is a ludicrous and discredited thesis. (2) No philosopher of any merit would hold such a view. (3) Nietzsche is among the greatest philosophers in history. Therefore, (4) Nietzsche was not a panpsychist. And then the analysis proceeds from there. The evident bias is clear. Undoubtedly all the above commentators know little or nothing about the history or arguments for panpsychism; if such were not the case, they would not dismiss it out of hand as “crackpot,” “laughable,” or a “nonstarter.”

The situation with Nietzsche today is comparable to that with Spinoza in the middle years of the twentieth century, when nearly all commentators were hostile to panpsychism. It took 30 or 40 years for the consensus opinion to shift to a panpsychist reading. By all accounts, a comparable shift on Nietzsche’s views will take as long.

Notes

1. Vorstellung is sometimes translated as “Representation” (e.g., in the 1958 translation by Payne), and occasionally as “Presentation” (e.g., by McCabe in Haeckel 1904: 466). The translation as “Idea” is found in the 1883 translation by Haldane and Kemp and in the 1995 Berman translation, which I will follow here.

2. Second Meditation (1641).

3. Letter 58, Spinoza to Schuller, dated 1674, cited on p. 267 of Spinoza 1677/1994.

4. This is not true, as we have seen. Leibniz attributed appetite or desire to all monads, which is a form of will. Campanella granted will or love to all things, as one of his three primalities. And even Empedocles’ concepts of Love and Strife can be seen as manifestations of will. But it is true that Schopenhauer was the first to explicitly declare the will as the essential reality of physical things.

5. I note in passing that Ludwig Wittgenstein was significantly influenced by Schopenhauer’s metaphysics, and two passages in Philosophical Investigations (1953) seem to refer to his notion that a stone has a mind. Both occur in book I. The first passage reads “Could one imagine a stone’s having consciousness? And if anyone can do so—why should that not merely prove that such image-mongery is of no interest to us?” (section 390) Wittgenstein is clearly disparaging the entire notion. The second passage seems to at least suspend judgment on the matter: “Is my having consciousness a fact of experience?—But doesn’t one say that a man has consciousness, and that a tree or a stone does not?—What would it be like if it were otherwise?—Would human beings all be unconscious?—No; not in the ordinary sense of the word. But I, for instance, should not have consciousness—as I now in fact have it.” (section 418) He suggests that the consciousness of man and of tree or stone are necessarily of different types—that seeing stones as conscious would entail viewing humans as something else, as “unconscious.” He seems unwilling to consider them as both possessing a common type of mentality, in any sense of the word. Thus he rejects one of Schopenhauer’s main theses.

6. This has clear ethical implications in the social realm. Schopenhauer (1819/1995: 74) notes that it speaks to a view in which homo homini lupus—man is a wolf to man.

7. For an analysis of Fechner’s analogical arguments, see Woodward 1972.

8. See, for example, Skolimowski 1990, 1992, and 1993.

9. This was the view of Hamilton (1990: 117–118): “the ‘given’ … was not to be construed as given to someone. ‘Experience’ was essentially subjectless.”

10. For a good summary of Paulsen’s criticisms, see DeGrood 1965: 57–64.

11. Wilhelm Wundt is occasionally cited as a panpsychist, but he seems to have been half-hearted at best. His primary treatise on psychology (1892) offers scant mention of the subject. He does oppose emergentism (“It is surely inadmissible to suppose that mental existence suddenly appeared at some definite point in the developmental chronology of life”—1892/1894: 443), which implicitly leaves him with some form of panpsychism. But the discussion that follows includes only a single passage that cautiously endorses it: “[W]e have every right to assume that primitive mentality was a state of simple feeling and sensing; while the possibility that this state accompanies every material movement-process … is still certainly not to be denied. At least, it looks very much more probable than the materialistic function hypothesis, if we accept the dictum ‘Ex nihilo nihil fit’ [out of nothing comes nothing].”

12. Early in 1889, when he was only 44 years old, Nietzsche suffered a severe mental breakdown that ended his productive life. The cause is unknown; it has been variously attributed to syphilis, manic-depression, meningioma, stroke, and early-onset dementia.

13. Denn alles, was ist, lebt (Nietzsche 1954, volume 3: 89).

14. Empfindung is usually translated as “sensation,” but it can also mean “feeling” or “perception.”

15. Nietzsche 1979: 35–36.

16. And again, at even greater length, in section 16. The English translations of passages in The Birth of Tragedy given here are Kaufmann’s.

17. KGW refers to Kritische Gesamtausgabe Werke (Colli and Montinari 1967). The German text is available at http://www.nietzschesource.org/ under “Posthumous fragments.”

18. See sections 23, 113, 189, 204, 348, and 356.

19. “How greedily the wave approaches, as if it were after something! … It seems that it is trying to anticipate someone. … And now it comes back … with excitement; is it disappointed?—But already another wave is approaching … and its soul, too, seems to be full of secrets and the lust to dig up treasures. Thus live waves … .”

20. Of course, this will to life is embodied in all things, non-living included. Evidently, for Schopenhauer even inorganic substances have a will to life.

21. Also called cosmological or metaphysical will-to-power in the literature.

22. This recalls Aristotle’s “sort of life” in all things, discussed in chapter 2 of the present volume.

23. For a flavor of the debate, see Clark 1990: 212–218; Clark and Dudrick 2012: 229–243; Endres and Pichler 2013; Hill 2007: 77–87; Janaway 2007: 154–157; Loeb 2015; Stack 2005: 197–201.

24. Preface to On the Genealogy of Morals.

25. Strawson (2015b) gives one of the few sympathetic treatments. Parkes (1994) and Hill (2007) are relatively neutral on the matter. Reginster (2012) declares himself “agnostic.”

26. As evidence of this deficiency, the reader is invited to review any of the critical sources mentioned above and then determine how many of the relevant Nietzsche passages are cited there.

6 The Anglo-American Perspective

Near the end of the 1800s, the focus of panpsychism shifted again, this time to the Anglo-American philosophers. In the early years of the twentieth century, panpsychist views appeared in the writings of Charles Sanders Peirce, William James, Francis Bradley, and Josiah Royce. Since that time the majority of works addressing panpsychism have come from British and American thinkers. The century was also marked by the emergence of several prominent scientist-philosophers who either sympathized with or directly advocated panpsychist views; they will be discussed in chapter 8.

6.1 Anglo-American Panpsychism of the Late Nineteenth Century

English panpsychism, largely absent since the time of Henry More and Margaret Cavendish, was reestablished in 1874 by the physicist and philosopher William Kingdon Clifford (1845–1879). That year, he published an article, titled “Body and Mind,” in which he claimed that science had bridged the gap between the organic and the inorganic. By then it was known that the same chemical elements and same laws of physics applied to both realms, and hence the laws of the organic were “only a complication” of the inorganic. Clifford then proceeded to explore whether there was a basis for believing that a similar bridge had been built between the Science of Physics and the Science of Consciousness.

Beginning introspectively, Clifford notes that, for him, “there is only one kind of consciousness, and that is to have fifty thousand feelings at once, and to know them all in different degrees” (1874/1903: 46). This state of consciousness is “an extremely complex one,” a complicated unity arising from a multiplicity of sensations. As a singular state of consciousness, it is something completely non-physical and non-material: “We have no possible ground … for speaking of another man’s consciousness as in any sense a part of the physical world of objects or phenomena. It is a thing entirely separate from it.” (53) Clearly he is referring to a naturalistic yet non-material mind, and not arguing for an immaterial soul in the traditional sense. If the mind is immaterial, it cannot be reduced to force, as others have argued, because force is clearly physical and observable. The conclusion then must be a form of parallelism—“the physical facts go along by themselves, and the mental facts go along by themselves.”

The view Clifford arrived at was a form of Spinozan parallelism that incorporated elements of LaMettrie’s and Diderot’s vitalist materialism. Clifford regarded the human body as “a physical machine,” but “not merely a machine, because consciousness goes with it” (57). In making his case for panpsychism, he applied the Continuity argument: As we move down the chain of living organisms,

it is impossible for anybody to point out the particular place in the line of descent where [absence of consciousness] can be supposed to have taken place. … Even in the very lowest organisms, even in the Amoeba … there is something or other, inconceivably simple to us, which is of the same nature with our own consciousness, although not of the same complexity. [Furthermore] we cannot stop at organic matter, [but] we are obliged to assume, in order to save continuity in our belief, that along with every motion of matter, whether organic or inorganic, there is some fact which corresponds to the mental fact in ourselves. (60–61)

Echoing Fechner, Clifford then notes that his doctrine “is no mere speculation, but is a result to which all the greatest minds that have studied this question in the right way have gradually been approximating for a long time.”

Four years later, Clifford expanded on his views in the journal Mind, advocating a monist philosophy in which the basic constituent of reality is “mind-stuff.”^1 Mind-stuff is neither mind nor consciousness, but rather the elements that combine together to form “the faint beginnings of Sentience.”^2 Mind is viewed as composed of “mental atoms” that exist in parallel with physical atoms and which combine in an analogous manner. “A moving molecule of inorganic matter does not possess mind, or consciousness; but it possesses a small piece of mind-stuff.” (1878: 65) Intelligence and volition emerge only in higher-level complexes of mind-stuff, but a kind of proto-consciousness seems to be present in all things.

Clifford’s mind-stuff theory was vulnerable to the combination problem. He offered no answer, and his untimely death a year later precluded any chance for resolution. This unresolved issue led certain philosophers to “reject decisively every form of mind-stuff.”^3 Others, including William James, were fascinated by it. James dedicated an entire chapter of his 1890 book Principles of Psychology (“The Mind-Stuff Theory”) to it. After acknowledging the power and attraction of such a theory, he rejected it for essentially the same reason: Mental atoms cannot combine, because to do so they would have to be combined “upon some entity other than themselves” (158)—i.e., something non-mental.^4

The next important development occurred in a work by the noted British author Samuel Butler (1838–1902). More a novelist than a formal philosopher, Butler nonetheless offered speculations on philosophical and metaphysical matters, and was an ardent supporter of evolution. He discussed his panpsychist views in his 1880 book Unconscious Memory

Like many other thinkers of the time, Butler noted that scientists had determined that the nature of the organic was the same as that of the inorganic, that vitalism had been largely disproved, that organic matter had been shown to be identical with inorganic, and that the same forces were everywhere present—views that hold to this day. The logical conclusion, then, was that certain essential characteristics of the living must inhere, in some form, in the non-living. “If we once break down the wall of partition between the organic and inorganic,” Butler writes,

the inorganic must be living and conscious also, up to a point. … It is more coherent with our other ideas, and therefore more acceptable, to start with every molecule as a living thing … than to start with inanimate molecules and smuggle life into them; … what we call the inorganic world must be regarded as up to a certain point living, and instinct, within certain limits, with consciousness, volition, and power of concerted action. (23)

At the conclusion of Unconscious Memory Butler reiterates his perspective, suggesting that it is the morally enlightened view: “I would recommend the reader to see every atom in the universe as living and able to feel and to remember, but in a humble way. … Thus he will see God everywhere.” (273) That a moral perspective is engendered by panpsychism is perhaps not obvious: “True, it would be hard to place one’s self on the same moral platform as a stone, but this is not necessary; it is enough that we should feel the stone to have a moral platform of its own.” (275) This is one of the earliest commentaries, along with those of Fechner and Paulsen, to cite the moral relevance of panpsychism. It indicates an emerging ecological value system in which objects of nature have intrinsic moral worth.

Gregory Bateson, apparently inspired by Butler, cited him on a number of occasions. But Bateson disagreed with the principle of attributing life and mind to atoms; rather, he adopted more of a qualified panpsychism in which all things except atoms possess minds—because they have no parts.^5

In an 1884 article titled “Religion: A Retrospect and Prospect,” the noted evolutionist Herbert Spencer (1820–1903) retraced the evolution of religion, discussed the origins of primitive animism, and observed that the spirits of nature gradually became more powerful, more unified, and more abstract. The concept of God, he asserted, lost more and more of its anthropocentrism, eventually becoming a kind of pure consciousness or spirit.

Spencer argued that the concept of God-as-First-Cause was a necessary and real aspect of the world, and that this God, stripped of all superfluous characteristics, was nothing more than pure mind. He saw force and consciousness as two distinct entities, but since “either is capable of generating the other, they must be different modes of the same [thing]” (1884: 9). He concluded from this that “the Power manifested throughout the Universe distinguished as material, is the same power which in ourselves wells up under the form of consciousness.” Science, he noted, had confirmed that view. He then went on to claim that physics had revealed the “incredible power” of brute matter, as with the ability of simple materials to transmit sounds over wireless airwaves. And so too “the spectroscope proves … that molecules on Earth pulsate in harmony with molecules in the stars.” The man of science, Spencer wrote, was forced to conclude that

every point in space thrills with an infinity of vibrations passing through it in all directions; the conception to which [the enlightened scientist] tends is much less that of a Universe of dead matter than that of a Universe everywhere alive: alive if not in the restricted sense, still in a general sense. (10)

In 1885, Morton Prince published The Nature of Mind and Human Automatism, in which he presented a naturalist, Schopenhauerian metaphysic that he characterized as a form of materialism in which the inner essence or thing-in-itself of matter was, following Clifford, mind-stuff. Prince’s was not a dual-aspect theory; it was more of an idealist monism that opposed the inert view of mechanism: “matter is no longer the dead and senseless thing it is popularly supposed to be” (1885/1975: 163). Evolution suggested the unity of all phenomena. As a consequence, he wrote, “the whole universe … instead of being inert is made up of living forces; not conscious [but] pseudo-conscious. It is made up of the elements of consciousness.” (164)

Charles Strong wrote approvingly of Prince’s book, calling it “an extremely clear and forceful statement of the panpsychist hypothesis” (1904a: 67). He noted that Prince was “entitled to an honorable place among [panpsychism’s] earliest discoverers and defenders.” In fact Prince and Clifford were the first two philosophers to articulate systemic and explicit panpsychist theories strictly as theories of mind, rather than as adjuncts to larger metaphysical systems. Prince drew on both Schopenhauer and Clifford, and reinterpreted their theories in an evolutionary vein.^6

6.2 William James

In 1890, William James (1842–1910) published his first major work, the aforementioned Principles of Psychology. In it he examined the mind-stuff theory in detail, noting that the essence of the mind-stuff approach is that, as with the monads, higher-order consciousness is compounded of simpler, atomic mental entities. The theory of evolution, along with other scientific advances, offered a strong line of reasoning in favor of a panpsychist mind-stuff theory; if complex material bodies could evolve from simpler ones, why couldn’t the same happen for psychical entities? From an evolutionary-psychological viewpoint, James wrote, “if evolution is to work smoothly, consciousness in some shape must have been present at the very origin of things. … Some such doctrine of atomistic hylozoism … is an indispensable part of a thorough-going philosophy of evolution.” (1890/1950: 149)

James appears to have implicitly agreed with this statement but doesn’t seem to have been convinced that mind-stuff was the proper interpretation. As has already been noted, the combination problem was for him an insurmountable barrier to the mind-stuff theory. On the ground that mental entities can only compound upon something non-mental, he called the compounding of consciousness “logically unintelligible.” Further, he argued, such a sum exists only to an outside observer and not in itself. In support, he quoted Royce: “Aggregations are organized wholes only … in the presence of other [external] things. … Unity exist[s] for some other subject, not for the mass itself.” (159) However, James commented in a footnote (162) that he was not opposed to combination per se, only to the intelligibility of combination within the assumptions of the mind-stuff theory. On his view, a combination resulted in something “totally new” and unlike that which composed it. Mind-atoms could combine not to form mind, but rather something completely different—though perhaps still mind-like. Thus the problem remained unresolved.

Upon rejecting the mind-stuff theory, James offered up the alternative theory of “polyzoism” or “multiple monadism.” He claimed no originality for that view—which “has been frequently made in the history of philosophy”—but simply asserted that it was the most logically consistent and problem-free alternative. Consider the human brain. Under polyzoism, every cell in the brain has its own unique consciousness, which is distinct from and unrelated to the consciousnesses of the other cells. But the cells clearly interact physically, and their interaction is brought together in a unifying hypothetical entity that James calls the “central cell” or “arch-cell.” Unfortunately science finds no evidence of any such central cell in the brain or any other organ. Furthermore, one cannot stop logically at the cell; one must extend the reasoning down to some ultimately small and simple units, arriving at a system much like Leibniz’s monadology: “The theory [of polyzoism] must set up for its elementary and irreducible psycho-physic couple, not the cell and its consciousness, but the primordial and eternal atom and its consciousness.” (180) Such a view is “remote and unreal” but nonetheless “must be admitted as a possibility”—and in fact “must have some sort of a destiny.”

In 1890, James was only implicitly panpsychist. His soul-theory took on all the central features of Leibniz’s monadology, including the universal presence of a central unifying point of mind—though he did not yet claim that all things have souls. Not until later would he argue more explicitly for what he called “pluralistic panpsychism.” His panpsychist metaphysics is one of the few such systems to have been seriously discussed and debated in recent philosophical discourse; for a detailed treatment, see Ford 1982. I will summarize some of the most important points here.

James’ metaphysical turn roughly coincided with the turn of the century. In 1901 and 1902 he presented his Gifford Lectures, which were then published as Varieties of Religious Experience (1902). In the book he clarified his conception of panpsychism without yet truly endorsing it. First he indicated his sympathy with a panpsychist or animist worldview:

How could the richer animistic aspects of Nature … fail to have been first singled out and followed by philosophy as the more promising avenue to the knowledge of Nature’s life? … A conscious field PLUS its object as felt or thought of PLUS an attitude toward the object PLUS the sense of a self to whom the attitude belongs [constitutes a] full fact … ; it is of the kind to which all realities whatsoever must belong.” (392–393)

James’ first explicit endorsement of panpsychism came in a series of lecture notes to a philosophy course taught at Harvard University in 1902–03. According to Perry (1935: 373), James announced that “pragmatism would be his method and ‘pluralistic panpsychism’ his doctrine.”

The series of 1904–05 lectures that would become Essays in Radical Empiricism (1912) marks a further change in James’ thinking, as he seems to move more toward a position of neutral monism. Here he suggests, after the manner of Mach, that “pure experience” is the ultimate reality. James seems to recognize that his view of radical empiricism is close to panpsychism, yet he defers an elaboration:

The “beyond” must of course always in our philosophy be itself of an experiential nature. If not a future experience of our own … , it must be a thing in itself in [panpsychists] Dr. Prince’s and Professor Strong’s sense of the term—that is, it must be an experience for itself. … This opens the chapter of the relations of radical empiricism to panpsychism, into which I cannot enter now. (1912/1996: 88–89)

Later in the book, James again suggests that the problems of causality between mind and matter lead “into that region of pan-psychic and ontologic speculation of which [panpsychists] Professors Bergson and Strong have lately [addressed] in so able and interesting a way. … I cannot help suspecting that the direction of their work is very promising, and that they have the hunter’s instinct for the fruitful trails.” (189)

In his 1905–06 lecture notes, he once more steers toward panpsychism: “Our only intelligible notion of an object in itself is that it should be an object for itself, and this lands us in panpsychism and a belief that our physical perceptions are effects on us of ‘psychical’ realities.” (in Perry 1935: 446)

James’ 1907–08 Hibbert Lectures, published as A Pluralistic Universe (1909), not only furthered his commitment to panpsychism but also made clear his fundamental opposition to the attitude and logic of conventional materialism. There are, he said, two kinds of philosophers: the cynical and the sympathetic. The former inevitably develop materialistic philosophies; the latter develop spiritualistic ones. Here we see his recognition of the ethical imperatives that are built into one’s worldview. Spiritualism may be either of the traditional dualist type or of the monist variety. The spiritual monists, furthermore, may be radically monist (e.g., absolute idealism) or may be more a “pluralist monism.” James then places himself and his radical empiricism in the latter group. The monism resides in the fact that all things are pure experience, the pluralism in the fact that all things are “for themselves” (that is, are objects with their own independent psychical perspectives). Radical empiricism is thus not only sympathetic; it is a morally vital philosophy. Materialism, because it removes the intimacy between mankind and nature, is cynical and axiologically defective: “Not to demand intimate relations with the universe, and not to wish them satisfactory, should be accounted signs of something wrong.” (1909/1996: 33)

As I have already noted, James devoted an entire lecture (chapter) to Fechner’s panpsychism and gave a very sympathetic reading. The next lecture, “Compounding of Consciousness,” offers his final solution to the combination problem. Formerly he had argued that any collective experience had to be unlike the constituent experiences; they had to be “logically distinct.” The result, logically speaking, was that combination was impossible. Now he realizes that this situation is “almost intolerable” because “it makes the universe discontinuous” (206). Such logic forces one to conclude that the universe is a “contradiction incarnate.” If analytic logic compels one to this view, “so much the worse for logic” (207). For James, logic is an intellectual tool of the cynical, materialistic philosophers, and he thus transcends it. He adds this: “Reality, life, experience, concreteness, immediacy, use what word you will, exceeds our logic, overflows and surrounds it.” (212) Combination, therefore, is possible after all, and in fact it maintains the continuity of mind throughout the universe.

Here, too, James abandons his earlier soul-theory: “Souls have worn out both themselves and their welcome, that is the plain truth.” (210) Individual minds and the hierarchy of lower- and higher-order mind constitute the reality of the cosmos: “the self-compounding of mind in its smaller and more accessible portions seems a certain fact” (292).

In the final lecture, James states his belief in a superhuman consciousness and speculates that “we finite minds may simultaneously be co-conscious with one another in a super-human intelligence.”^7 Overall, he advocates “a general view of the world almost identical with Fechner’s” (309–310). He foresees a new worldview, a fundamental change in philosophy, “a great empirical movement towards a pluralistic panpsychic view of the universe” (313).^8 This new system “threatens to short-circuit” the cynical worldview of the mechanistic materialists.

Not that we must abandon all present modes of thinking, or fall into mysticism or irrationalism. James holds out the hope that, in his new worldview, “empiricism and rationalism might [yet] strike hands in a lasting treaty of peace”; he implores thinking people to “seek together … using all the analogies and data within reach” to understand this new conception of mind and consciousness. “Why,” he asks, “cannot ‘experience’ and ‘reason’ meet on this common ground?” (312) The new worldview is thus spiritual, sympathetic, even reverent. Following Paulsen, James notes that the greatest order of mind in the cosmos is that which we may call God. God is the mind of the cosmos, a kind of nouveau world-soul in which we all co-consciously participate. “Thus does foreignness get banished from our world. … We are indeed internal parts of God and not external creations, on any possible reading of the panpsychic system.” (318)

Others of James’ later writings reinforce his final commitment to panpsychism. In the Miller-Bode notebooks of 1908 he writes that “the constitution of reality which I am making for is of [the] psychic type” (in Perry 1935: 764). His last writings include a series of essays meant to be a kind of philosophical text; they were eventually collected and published as Some Problems of Philosophy (1911a). In the last two of these essays he again addresses the problem of causation, considering both the conceptual and the perceptual views. The conceptualist or “intellectualist” approach consists of essentially a Humean negation of causality, something he derides as “confused and unsatisfactory.” Preferable is a perceptualist view based on our own personal experience of the continuity of causality. This leads James into the mind-body relationship and its larger implications. He takes the experience of causal continuity as literally the stuff of causation—recalling his radical empiricism. Upon taking this view, “we should have to ascribe to cases of causation outside of our own life, to physical cases also, an inwardly experiential nature. In other words we should have to espouse a so-called ‘pan-psychic’ philosophy.” (218) In the posthumously published Memories and Studies, James remarks:

[T]here is a continuum of cosmic consciousness, … into which our several minds plunge as into a mother-sea or reservoir. … Not only psychic research, but metaphysical philosophy, and speculative biology are led in their own ways to look with favor on some such “panpsychic” view of the universe as this. (1911b: 204)

Ultimately, he writes, what is important in philosophy is vision. “Philosophy is more a matter of passionate vision than of logic.” (1909/1996: 176) Unfortunately, “few professorial philosophers have any vision,” and “where there is no vision the people perish” (165). Pluralistic panpsychism seems to provide James with the vision he seeks.

Reaction to James’ panpsychism is revealing. Despite the considerable evidence, most philosophers still argue that James only “toyed” with panpsychism. A few—among them Ford (1981, 1982), Kuklick (1977), Cooper (1990), and Sprigge (1993)—explicitly acknowledge his endorsement, Ford (1982) citing several examples to the contrary.

6.3 Royce, Peirce, and Other Sympathetic Thinkers

Four important panpsychist works were released in 1892. One was Friedrich Paulsen’s Introduction to Philosophy, discussed in chapter 5. Another was “Panpsychism and Panbiotism,” a notable article by Paul Carus, editor of The Monist. In the article, Carus offers some pro and con thoughts on panpsychism, proposing that the term ‘panbiotism’ be used in its place. “Everything,” he argues, “is fraught with life; it contains life; it has the ability to live.” (234) Surprisingly, he dismisses Ernst Haeckel’s view that matter possesses mind or soul as “fantastic,” and proceeds to develop his own definition of soul. One of the more interesting sections of Carus’ piece is titled “Mr. Thomas A. Edison’s Panpsychism.” In a brief essay titled “Intelligent Atoms,” Edison had stated that “every atom of matter is intelligent.” Carus quotes him as follows:

All matter lives, and everything that lives possesses intelligence. … The atom is conscious if man is conscious, … exercises will-power if man does, is, in its own little way, all that man is. … I cannot avoid the conclusion that all matter is composed of intelligent atoms and that life and mind are merely synonyms for the aggregation of atomic intelligence. (243)

Quite unexpected words from one of the world’s greatest inventors and practical thinkers!

In Spirit of Modern Philosophy, Josiah Royce—an American philosopher well known for his pragmatism and absolute idealism—proposed a theory of the Universal Self (or Logos, or World-Spirit, or God) as the cosmic mind which is the reality behind all physical phenomena. Of this Infinite Self, according to Royce, we know little directly—only that it exists, is conscious, and is fundamentally One. The Self doesn’t act on reality, precisely because it is reality: “He isn’t anywhere in space or in time. He makes from without no worlds. … The absolute Self simply doesn’t cause the world.” (1892/1955: 348)

Royce examines several dual-aspect theories of mind, including Clifford’s mind-stuff concept; he finds them unsatisfactory in their original form, but “luminous and inevitable” when understood in light of the Self. Consider two people. Their bodies follow physical laws and may interact in causal ways. But their physicality is merely a manifestation of their underlying inner reality as conscious beings. In the non-physical realm, their two minds interact, communicate, and participate—and this results in true knowledge. “He and I,” Royce claims, “have spiritual relations, think of each other, and do somehow indirectly commune together.” (417)

Like many other thinkers of the time, Royce saw in evolution grounds for viewing all physical objects as subject to the same metaphysical principles. Since humans possess an inner mind and a distinct identity, then so too does everything. This is the “relation of the inorganic world to our human consciousness”:

The theory of the “double aspect,” applied to the facts of the inorganic world, suggests at once that they, too, in so far as they are real, must possess their own inner and appreciable aspect. … In general it is an obvious corollary of all that we have been saying. (419)

[W]e … know that there is no real process of nature that must not have, known or unknown to us, its inner, its appreciable aspect. Otherwise it could not be real. (427)

Royce counsels the reader not to view this as mere animism or anthropomorphism. It would be simplistic and misleading to presuppose that “stones or planets” have anything like a human inner life: “it is not ours to speculate what appreciative inner life is hidden behind the describable but seemingly lifeless things of the world.” Yet we are certain that it exists, because “the Logos finds a place for it … in the world of appreciation.” The Logos is by definition timeless, and hence the cosmos has always had this inner life—before humans, before life, before the Earth.

Royce advances this line of thinking in Studies of Good and Evil (1898), displaying a deepening conviction that all things have inner lives with as much reality and intrinsic worth as those of humans:

[W]e have no sort of right to speak in any way as if the inner experience behind any fact of nature were of a grade lower than ours, or less conscious, or less rational, or more atomic. … This reality is, like that of our own experience, conscious, organic, full of clear contrasts, rational, definite. We ought not to speak of dead nature. (1898/1915: 230)

The contrast is clear: The “dead nature” of mechanism is fundamentally challenged by the panpsychic worldview.

The final and perhaps most important articulation of Royce’s panpsychism can be found in The World and the Individual (1899–1901). He asks the reader to “suppose that even material nature were internally full of the live and fleeting processes that we know as those of conscious mental life” (213). Drawing on recent science, he then introduces some new variations on the arguments for panpsychism, all based on “four great and characteristic types of processes” (219) that ordinary matter shares with “conscious Nature” (i.e., mankind). First Royce notes that both matter and mind exhibit irreversibility in their processes—a reference to the recently formulated second law of thermodynamics. Second, he notes that both realms display a tendency to communicate: Minds and ideas interact with each other, and likewise matter and energy exhibit field properties (“wave-movements”) that indicate an interpenetration and communicative interaction. Third, both show tendencies toward a quasi-stable behavior, in spite of their irreversibility, that Royce—following Peirce—calls a “habit.” Nature exhibits countless “approximate rhythms” that are repeatable and definite yet never absolutely fixed. Fourth, the process of evolution demonstrates the continuity of nature, from inorganic to organic to consciousness. These are all variations on the Evolution/Continuity arguments, employing the latest developments in science and physics.

From these arguments Royce concludes that a mental aspect of nature must exist, but that it operates so much more slowly than our human consciousness that we cannot perceive it:

[W]e have no right whatever to speak of really unconscious Nature, but only of uncommunicative Nature, or of Nature whose mental processes go on at such different time-rates from ours that we cannot adjust ourselves to a live appreciation of their inward fluency, although our consciousness does make us aware of their presence. (225–226)

The “very vast [mental] slowness in inorganic Nature,” such as in a rock or a solar system, is no less extant that our own mentality. Time scale is entirely arbitrary, and therefore slower is not lesser. The Mind in nature is fully conscious. Hence, a mental life is to be found everywhere:

Where we see inorganic Nature seemingly dead, there is, in fact, conscious life, just as surely as there is any Being present in Nature at all. And I insist, meanwhile, that no empirical warrant can be found for affirming the existence of dead material substance anywhere. (240)

The fourth significant publication of 1892 was “Man’s Glassy Essence,” in which Charles Sanders Peirce (1839–1914) discussed the relation between the psychical and physical aspects of material things. This was the fourth of Peirce’s five famous Monist articles on metaphysics, published in 1891–1893. The first three—“The Architecture of Theories,” “The Doctrine of Necessity Examined,” and “The Law of Mind”—laid the groundwork for the panpsychist vision he set forth in “Man’s Glassy Essence.”

“The Architecture of Theories” begins with a discussion of the “brick and mortar” of any viable philosophical system. That article, like all of the five, is very diverse in concepts; Peirce seems to dash from one topic to the next, only roughly forming a consistent overall theme. After discussing the relevance of evolution to philosophy of mind, he asserts that “the old dualistic notion of mind and matter … will hardly find defenders today” (1891/1992: 292). We are thus compelled to a new form of monism—one that he designates, surprisingly, ‘hylopathy’, meaning the view that all matter “feels.”

This monism must have one of three forms: neutralism (in which mind and matter are independent), materialism (in which the physical is primary), and idealism (in which the mental is primary). Peirce rejects neutralism because two independent entities are proposed where only one is required. He dismisses materialism as “repugnant to scientific logic” because “it requires us to suppose that a certain kind of mechanism will feel.” Thus, we are left with idealism. Peirce has in mind a particular variation, “objective idealism”:

The one intelligible theory of the universe is that of objective idealism, that matter is effete mind, inveterate habits becoming physical laws. (293)

Here Peirce refers to his so-called cosmogonic thesis in which the universe originates in a condition of pure, chaotic feeling, then becomes progressively crystallized into matter as this mind undergoes a kind of solidification through patterns of recurrence that he calls “habits.” Mind is thus at the core of reality. It exists in varying stages of solidification (or “objectification,” as Schopenhauer would have it), and can be seen in one sense as matter and in another as mind.

In “The Doctrine of Necessity Examined” Peirce rejects determinism, arguing instead for his own version of anti-necessitarianism (“tychism”). One of the reasons for his rejection is that necessitarianism requires an entirely unsatisfactory epiphenomenal view of mind: “Necessitarianism cannot logically stop short of making the whole action of the mind [simply] a part of the physical universe. … Indeed, consciousness in general thus becomes a mere illusory aspect.” (1892a/1992: 309) Some small degree of tychistic freedom is required to “insert mind into our scheme.”

Peirce returns to panpsychism briefly in “The Law of Mind.” He observes that “tychism must give birth to an evolutionary cosmology … and to a Schelling-fashioned idealism which holds matter to be mere specialized and partially deadened mind” (1892b/1992: 312). But he then diverts again to a different discussion. At the end of the article he reiterates that “what we call matter is not completely dead, but is merely mind hide-bound with habits” (331).

Coming now to the main piece, Peirce begins “Man’s Glassy Essence” with a look at physics and chemistry, then goes on to discuss primitive life forms and the protoplasm inside all living cells. Of all the properties of protoplasm, the most important is that it “feels”—and what is more, it exhibits all essential qualities of mind. Sensitivity and sentience are inferred, Peirce tells us, by analogy: “[T]here is fair analogical inference that all protoplasm feels. It not only feels but exercises all the functions of mind.” (1892c/1992: 343) Among the properties on which the analogy is based are reaction to the environment, ability to move, ability to grow, and ability to reproduce.

And yet, Peirce writes, protoplasm is simply complex chemistry, a particular arrangement of molecules. Feeling cannot be accounted for by mechanistic laws; therefore, we are forced to admit “that physical events are but degraded or undeveloped forms of psychical events” (348). He then presents his own dual-aspect theory of mind:

[A]ll mind is directly or indirectly connected with all matter, and acts in a more or less regular way; so that all mind more or less partakes of the nature of matter. … Viewing a thing from the outside, … it appears as matter. Viewing it from the inside, … it appears as consciousness. (349)

The dynamic sensitivity of protoplasm necessarily results in an enhanced capability for feeling: “nerve-protoplasm is, without doubt, in the most unstable condition of any kind of matter; and consequently, there the resulting feeling is the most manifest” (348). Again, this sort of sensitivity is a general property of matter: “Wherever chance-spontaneity [i.e. unstable sensitivity] is found, there, in the same proportion, feeling exists.” Peirce thus effectively introduces a new argument for panpsychism, drawing on the correlation between a specific physical characteristic—dynamic sensitivity—and the mental property of feeling. All matter is dynamic to some degree, and thus must be associated with an “interior” that feels. I will designate this as the argument from Dynamic Sensitivity. Like the evolutionary argument, it incorporates forms of continuity and non-emergence, to which it adds a reference to the indwelling power of dynamical systems. Clearly Peirce was only sketching out his views in this essay, but certainly the lack of a developed theory of dynamical systems restricted his ability to articulate himself. With the advent of chaos theory and non-linear dynamics in the late twentieth century, we now have new ways of expanding on Peirce’s insight—see, for example, Skrbina 2009b and chapter 9 below.

Later in “Man’s Glassy Essence,” Peirce elaborates on his notion of a “general idea.” Individual ideas, he claims, spread out over time, influence one another, and become fused together into a general idea. As he wrote in his earlier article “The Law of Mind,” such general ideas are “living feelings spread out” (1892b/1992: 327). Any general idea that comes to exhibit a pattern of regularity or recurrence is said to acquire a habit: “Habit is that specialization of the law of mind whereby a general idea gains the power of exciting [regular] reactions.” In fact the general idea is rather the mind of the habit. This mind associated with the general idea is a unity—one that is, in some fundamental ontological sense, like a human personality:

The consciousness of a general idea has a certain “unity of the ego” in it. … It is, therefore, quite analogous to a person; and, indeed, a person is only a particular kind of general idea. … Every general idea has the unified living feeling of a person. (1892c/1992: 350)

Peirce recognized that his generalized theory of mind applied to larger-scale super-human structures as well as the smaller sub-human systems. People who interact strongly with one another produce a true group mind that is essentially like the mind of the individual. Personhood or personality results when the feelings (sub-minds) are “in close enough connection to influence one another.” “There should be,” Peirce continues, “something like personal consciousness in [collective] bodies of men who are in intimate and intensely sympathetic communion.” In other words, degree of participation determines degree of mind. He adds that these ideas “are no mere metaphors” and that “the law of mind clearly points to the existence of such personalities.”

After the Monist series, Peirce continued to articulate his cosmogony, albeit in a vague and indeterminate way. This outlook relates to his broader semiotic conception of the world, in which the basic architecture of reality consists of signs. “All this universe is perfused with signs, if it is not composed exclusively of signs.” (1934: 302) Signs in general have a symbolic nature^9; they represent an object to an interpretant. Signs or symbols are furthermore alive; they grow, expand, and reproduce. “[E]very symbol is a living thing, in a very strict sense that is no mere figment of speech.” (1992b: 264) The symbol or sign is the most general conception of life, a “living general”; “it is of the nature of a sign to be an individual replica and to be in that replica a living general. … There can be no reality which has not the life of a symbol.” (1992b: 324) Biological life is but a special case of “living general.”

Peirce’s cosmogony, in brief, is this: In the beginning there was a vast formless state, which he calls “the ovum of the universe.” This ovum was not empty, but consisted of “a primeval chaos of unpersonalized feeling”^10—that is, of subjectless, disembodied, undifferentiated feeling-qualities. This cosmic Feeling is alive, is sentient, and may even be consciousness per se: “every true universal, every continuum, is a living and conscious being” (1993: 162), and “whatever is First is ipso facto sentient” (260). Random reactions within this vast sea of feeling-qualities at some point gave rise to a first symbol—an original, living entity that marked the beginning of natural law or “habit.” With the advent of symbols or signs came space, time, matter, and energy, all of which were emergent qualities. From these things the visible universe evolved. But the cosmos never lost its fundamental character as a composition of living, feeling signs. Halton (2005) refers to this metaphysical system as “Peircean animism.”

Burks (1996: 343), however, had it more correct: “Peirce is a panpsychist, making feelings (psychological Firsts) the elementary building blocks of the universe.” The primordial feelings are prior not only to mind and matter, but even to space-time: “As the ultimate atoms of the universe, panpsychic feelings (Firsts) are too simple to be related by space and time.” (345) Indeed, it was from precisely such feelings that space and time emerged: “Objects and events are relational complexes of Firsts. … This is the sense in which space and time have evolved … .” Burks dedicates an entire section of his paper to “Peirce’s panpsychic firsts.” In that section he explains that “objective idealism is a form of panpsychism, the view that all objects of the universe are constituted of basic feelings and their interactions” (349–350). There are even theological implications: “panpsychic feelings provide a mental basis for Peirce’s panpsychic God” (352). In a related essay, Burks (1997: 531) offers a concise summary: “Peirce’s cosmic theory of evolution was a panpsychism: the universe began as a chaos of primitive feelings and gradually evolved the material and mental laws and systems of today.” Houser (2014: 29) evidently concurs: “This is a panpsychism.” Without citing any history, Houser acknowledges its unconventional nature: “Clearly, though, Peirce’s panpsychism is not at all ordinary, but it is a panpsychism all the same … .” And it follows directly from the ideas sketched out in the Monist essays.

Such views are in striking contrast to Peirce’s more famous analytic work in logic and positivism. Yet it is clear that he read other panpsychist philosophers—he cites Fechner, Schelling, Clifford, Carus, Empedocles, Epicurus, Gilbert, James, Leibniz, von Nägeli, Royce, and the Stoics, all in contexts that would indicate familiarity with their theories of mind. Peirce’s pragmatism, like James’, thus seems to have been fully compatible with a panpsychist outlook. This fact may have influenced the later pragmatists John Dewey and Ferdinand Schiller, both of whom also articulated panpsychist views.

Anglo-American panpsychism of the late nineteenth century came to a close with the British idealism of Francis Bradley (1846–1924). In 1893 Bradley published the first edition of his major work, Appearance and Reality. His system of idealism was based on an absolute monism in which, as with Mach and James, the ultimate reality is pure experience. “Feeling, thought, and volition,” writes Bradley, “are all the material of existence, and there is no other material, actual or even possible.” (1893/1930: 127) Thus, this ultimate reality is not merely experience, but “sentient experience.” His monism doesn’t allow for separating subject from object, and as a result the subject himself is nothing more than experience—as was the case with Schopenhauer’s “will.” For both subject and object, “to be real is to be indissolubly one thing with sentience” (128).

Later in Appearance and Reality Bradley addresses the nature of the inorganic. In his absolute monism, all things are fundamentally one, and hence the inorganic shares essential qualities with the organic. This justifies an argument by analogy: “A sameness greater or less with our own bodies is the basis from which we conclude to other bodies and souls.” (239) Where the sameness is clear, so is the imputation of psychical life. But even in the cases where it is not obvious, we have “no sufficient warrant for positive denial [of mind].” In our profound ignorance of the absolute, we must allow for the possibility that “every fragment of visible Nature might, so far as is known, serve as part in some organism not [obviously] like our bodies.” He reaches a somewhat tentative panpsychist conclusion:

[Physical] arrangements, apparently quite different from our own, and expressing themselves in what seems a wholly unlike way, might be directly connected with finite centers of feeling. And our result here must be this, that … we cannot call the least portion of Nature inorganic. (240)

If this is less than a ringing endorsement, Bradley at least concludes—in the absence of evidence to the contrary—that the intellectually prudent view is to assume that inorganic matter has its own center of feeling.^11

Notes

1. The concept of a mind-stuff theory did not originate with Clifford. It was anticipated as far back as Democritus and his idea of the soul-atom. Leibniz’s monads are another, more developed precursor. And in Herbert Spencer’s Principles of Psychology (1855) we find this: “There may be a single primordial element of consciousness, and the countless kinds of consciousness may be produced by the compounding of this element with itself … in higher and higher degrees.” (1855/1897: 150) Clifford was, however, the first to explicitly promote a panpsychist mind-stuff theory.

2. This is very similar to the modern notion of “proto-mind” or “proto-consciousness,” in which certain basic elements of reality are not themselves mental, but in combination give rise to mind.

3. Stout 1919b/1952: 212–213.

4. For the early James, “mental combination” is impossible, whether for mental atoms or for individual people; the so-called group mind doesn’t exist. James responds to the challenge of mind-stuff by proposing his own alternative: “polyzoism” or “multiple monadism,” which is just as strongly panpsychist as the theory of mind-stuff. By 1907 James had revised his view to allow for the possibility of mental combination and group mind.

5. Bateson’s ideas are discussed in more detail in chapter 8 of this volume.

6. Prince summarized his theory and responded to some criticisms in his 1904 essay “The Identification of Mind and Matter,” and he also explicitly stated that “consciousness and the brain process are identical” (447), which made him one of the first identity theorists of his era in England. Prince’s view also emphasizes the close connection between identity theories and panpsychism. (See the discussion of Herbert Feigl in chapter 9 of the present volume.)

7. He comments that paranormal phenomena provide strong evidence for this view: “I find in some of these abnormal or supernormal facts the strongest suggestions in favor of a superior co-consciousness being possible.” (299)

8. “Empirical,” again, refers to his radical empiricism, in which everything is pure experience.

9. Formally, symbols are merely complex signs.

10. Cited on p. 27 of Houser 2014.

11. Sprigge (1993: 546) argues that only a panpsychist interpretation of Bradley is intelligible.

9 Panpsychism from 1950 to the Present

The previous chapter detailed some recent ideas and approaches to panpsychism from within the scientific tradition, broadly conceived. From a philosophical perspective, panpsychism diversified greatly in the middle and late years of the twentieth century, following a number of different routes.

First there was the ongoing development of the Whiteheadian process view, which had been defended and articulated for decades by Hartshorne. His writing was complemented by that of several other process philosophers, most notably Griffin but also including Ford, Birch, De Quincey, and others. The process philosophers have been among the more consistent and vocal advocates of panpsychism over the past several decades, and they deserve credit for keeping the topic alive within philosophical discourse.

Additionally we find a range of other approaches. The panpsychist implications of a part-whole hierarchy, first articulated by Cardano, were adopted and modernized by Koestler. Dual-aspect views, which are at least implicitly panpsychist, were defended by thinkers as diverse as Feigl, Nagel, Globus, Plumwood, and Chalmers. In the work of Abram, Berman, Zohar, Wilber, Harvey, and Orr, populist treatments also emerged. The endorsement of panpsychism by the prominent analytic philosopher Galen Strawson was a major development in the field. So-called Russellian monism has been taken up in earnest by professional philosophers, many of whom spell out the panpsychist implications. And various efforts have been made to build upon the insights of Peirce and to connect recent work in chaos theory and dynamical systems to forms of panpsychism.

9.1 Developments in the 1960s and the 1970s

In the second half of the twentieth century, apart from Hartshorne, a number of philosophical voices argued for variations on the panpsychist theme. Unsurprisingly, many were from outside the mainstream of traditional academia. Academic philosophy, having become thoroughly immersed in the analytic and linguistic disciplines, seems to have largely abandoned the deeper, more penetrating, more metaphysical questions of mind. Modern philosophy, at least as practiced in the major universities, primarily serves to perpetuate a positivistic, mechanistic worldview. As William James said, philosophy is ultimately about vision. The vision of modern philosophy is predominantly an analytical one, and thus largely sterile and inert: a world of passive matter acted on by blind forces. That such a world can give rise to life and mind becomes an inexplicable fact and an eternal mystery.

Scattered references to panpsychism, many of them confused and ambivalent, continued to appear in the 1950s and the 1960s. Consider the philosopher Herbert Feigl. In 1958 he published a lengthy and influential article, “The ‘Mental’ and the ‘Physical,’” in which he argued for a form of the identity theory that has been interpreted by certain writers as a kind of panpsychism. Identity theories generally equate the physical states of the brain with mental states, typically stating directly that mental states are brain states. On that view, a physical alteration in brain state necessarily implies a changed mental state, in a kind of one-to-one relationship. Such a mind-brain identity presents a number of difficulties, as Feigl points out; one of these is the precise meaning of ‘identical’.^1 Under most interpretations, it means that the mental is somehow dependent on or supervenient upon the physical.

If mental states are identical to physical brain or neural states, and if neural states are seen as not fundamentally unlike physical processes in general, then one is strongly inclined toward a panpsychist view. If one accepts an identity theory and yet denies panpsychism, then one necessarily accepts that there is something ontologically unique about the physical processes occurring in the brain, such that they alone give rise to consciousness or mind—a position that smacks of a kind of neo-vitalism and is extraordinarily difficult to defend.

Feigl seems to have recognized this dilemma, and yet he wavers between the two horns. After ruling out many common descriptors of “mental,” he determines that the two most appropriate terms are “direct experience” (qualia) and “intelligence.” Both are required, because if intelligence alone were chosen “as the sole criterion of mentality, then it would be hard to draw a sharp line anywhere within the realm of organic life. Even in the kingdom of plants … we find processes [characteristic] of purposive behavior.” (1958: 411–412) Furthermore, the notion of intelligence “may be attributed not only to the higher animals but also to the ‘thinking machines’ [computers]” (419).^2 Other putative characteristics of mind are inappropriate: “mnemic, teleological, holistic, and emergent features are not adequate as criteria of mentality, because these features characterize even inorganic processes and structures” (415)—apparently implying that panpsychism cannot be true, by definition.^3

All this leaves the “raw feels” of direct experience—that is, qualia or sentience—as the critical factor. Sentience can be attributed to things, Feigl argues, only by analogy: “I have no doubt that analogy is the essential criterion for the ascription of sentience.” (427) And analogy, of course, is at the heart of many panpsychist arguments. Feigl notes this but then claims that “the panpsychists’ hypothesis is inconsistent with the very principles of analogy which they claim to use” (451). This statement is based on “the enormous differences in behavior” between, for example, humans and insects. But this is no real counter-argument. Panpsychism in general accepts large differences in both qualitative states and functional behavior; it merely claims that all structures experience some qualia, even if they are unimaginably slight or foreign to us. It is thus not clear exactly how or why the panpsychist hypothesis is inconsistent.

Feigl’s wavering on this issue is especially evident later in the essay. On the one hand, “the identity theory regards sentience … and other [unexperienced] qualities … as the basic reality” (474). Yet at the same time he seeks to avoid “the unwarranted panpsychistic generalization.” However, “one is tempted, with the panpsychists, to assume some unknown-by-acquaintance qualities quite cognate with those actually experienced” (475). A strange sort of ambivalence is obviously present here.

Feigl’s position has been interpreted in varying ways, and even at the time it was apparent to many that he was implicitly arguing for panpsychism. He reacted to the criticism shortly thereafter: “Well-intentioned critics have tried to tell me that [my position] is essentially the metaphysics of panpsychism. … It is not panpsychism at all—either the ‘pan’ or the ‘psyche’ has to be deleted in the formulation.” (1960: 31) After adding that, in his view, “nothing in the least like a psyche is ascribed to lifeless matter,” he concludes that the term ‘pan-quality-ism’ “come[s] much closer to a correct characterization than ‘panpsychism’.”

And yet Feigl was never able to shake the panpsychist implications of his view. Popper (1977: 200) made him out to be a virtual panpsychist. Sprigge characterized his position as “to all intents and purposes, panpsychist” (1984: 7). Chalmers (1996: 166) classed him with Russell as a sympathizer of panpsychism. Privately, Feigl seems to have accepted this close association. Grover Maxwell recalled him as having said “If you give me a couple of martinis, a good dinner, and a couple of after-dinner drinks, I would admit that I am strongly tempted toward (a rather watered-down, innocuous) panpsychism.”^4 If true, this is indicative of his deep-seated conflictions about the subject.

Another implicit reference to panpsychism came in 1967 with Arthur Koestler’s book The Ghost in the Machine. Koestler’s theory is centered on a triple-aspect hierarchical structuring of reality. On his view, each well-defined structure or object possesses three essential characteristics: Each is composed of parts at lower levels of existence, is a whole in itself, and is a part of larger wholes. In this system—which closely reflects but doesn’t acknowledge Cardano’s outlook—each thing so conceived is referred to as a holon. Atoms are holons, as are cells, animals, social groups, and the Earth.

Koestler was clear that such an ordering encompasses living and nonliving systems, and that it implies a certain common basis for dynamic interaction with the world. The interactive mode of humans relates to our minds, and thus there is the implication that all holons relate to the world in a somewhat mind-like manner:

As we move downward in the hierarchy … we nowhere strike rock bottom, find nowhere those ultimate constituents which the old mechanistic approach to life led us to expect. The hierarchy is open-ended in the downward, as it is in the upward direction. (1967: 61–62)

Each holon struggles to maintain its own order of existence (“self-assertive tendency”) and yet also seeks to participate in larger-order structures (“participatory or self-integrative tendency”). This much is perhaps clear as it applies to living organisms, but Koestler was compelled by his own theory to acknowledge these tendencies at all levels of being. He saw this immediately and yet recoiled from the panpsychist implications:

It would, of course, be grossly anthropomorphic to speak of ‘self-assertive’ and ‘integrative’ tendencies in inanimate nature, or of ‘flexible strategies.’ It is nevertheless true that in all stable dynamic systems, stability is maintained by the equilibrium of opposite forces, one of which may be centrifugal or separative … representing the holistic properties of the part, and the other a centripetal or attractive or cohesive force which keeps the part in its place in the larger whole … . (62–63)

In the appendix Koestler adds that each level of being attains progressively greater consciousness: “Each upward shift is reflected by a more vivid and precise consciousness of the ongoing activity; and … is accompanied by the subjective experience of freedom of decision.” (347) Thus, in spite of his denial of panpsychism, he clearly ascribed mental-like qualities to all levels of existence. Like Feigl, he seems to have been torn by the implications of his own theory.

Koestler appears never to have resolved this conflict. Eleven years later he returned to the issue of mind in nature, explicitly addressing the topic of panpsychism. In Janus he observes (incorrectly) that “panpsychism and Cartesian dualism mark opposite ends of the philosophical spectrum” (1978: 229). His “holarchic” system, he claims, “replaces the panpsychist’s continuously ascending curve from cabbage to man by a whole series of discrete steps—a staircase instead of a slope.” Yet each step represents some level or degree of mentality:

In the downward direction we are faced with a multiplicity of levels of consciousness or sentience which extend far below the human level. … The hierarchy appears to be open-ended both in the upward and downward direction. (230)

Koestler thus once again accepted the existence of sentience throughout the ontological hierarchy, yet denied that his system was a form of panpsychism. The two views are difficult to reconcile.

The psychiatrist and philosopher Gordon Globus developed a panpsychist reading of the identity theory in the early 1970s. Starting from Feigl’s basic conception, Globus emphasized that there is no ontological divide between neural events and general physical events. “The present biological perspective,” he wrote, “suggests that physical nonneural events and those physical neural events identical with consciousness per se have similarity qua events” (1972: 299). Thus he was led to ask “Could consciousness per se … be in some way equivalent to the ultimate physical events which comprise reality?” His initial conclusion was that they are, if not identical, at least “congruent.”

In 1973 Globus wrote that mind is the process of embodying a physical event. The brain performs this function very well, and in fact “its capability for thus embodying events is identical with its capability of mind” (1134). But the brain is only a special, highly evolved instance of a physical structure. Other systems also embody events; “less evolved organs, organisms, and machines have only a ‘protomind’ to the extent that they are capable of embodying events.” This theory became explicit panpsychism in Globus’ 1976 article “Mind, Structure, and Contradiction.” Seeking to avoid a naive animism, he articulates a “psychoneural structural identity thesis” that associates mind with all physical structures. Adapting and modifying the Cartesian position into a dual-aspect theory, he argues that mind is “unbounded” whereas brain is “bounded,” but that each refers to the same structure of the underlying reality. The structure of the mind and the structure of the brain are “one and the same, even though the ‘stuff’ structured is unbounded in the first case and bounded in the second” (282). As an example Globus mentions the sense of sight, in which a pattern of light reflects off some object and reaches the eye:

[T]he electromagnetic waves impinging on the retina … conserves the structure of the “object” from which it has been reflected. … Further, the “stuff” structured varies: from whatever the object “stuff” is, to a light “stuff,” and finally to a neural “stuff”—but the structure per se is (more or less) maintained. (287)

Structure is thus embodied in many different forms. In humans we recognize mind as one aspect of this. More generally it is an “intrinsic perspective” that varies only according to the particular embodiment. Another of Globus’ examples is the following:

[A] brain and a rock are systems differing enormously in “richness” of structure, and the respective “minds” accordingly differ enormously. … Although I appreciate that most will consider it ridiculous to attribute awareness to a rock, for my purposes, I choose to emphasize the awareness intrinsic to rock. (290)

He employs the ancient Continuity argument: “At heart, the issue is just that there is no place to unarbitrarily draw a line (or even a range) in a hierarchy of systems increasing in complexity, above which we can say that mind occurs and below which it does not.” The whole notion of mind as emerging only in high-complexity structures is “human chauvinism at its worst.” Acknowledging that such a panpsychic worldview is “almost impossible to fathom” from within the scientific mindset, Globus concludes his “defense of panpsychism” with an appeal to intuitive and even mystical insight as necessary for full comprehension. Clearly panpsychism lies fundamentally outside the framework of contemporary mechanistic materialism, and therefore a radical break of some kind is required to deeply grasp and adequately assess such a view.

After these insightful early pieces, Globus moved away from the topic for more than three decades. He returned to it 2009 with an intricate new argument, not for true panpsychism, but for a very widespread presence of qualia in the natural world. Drawing from quantum theory, specifically from quantum thermofield dynamics (QTD), Globus argues that qualia, and hence mind, emerge only where there exists cooperative or correlated dynamics. QTD, he says, “does in fact prescribe a lower boundary below which there can be no cooperative dynamics, and without cooperative dynamics there is nothing mind-like, just the tedious random noise of fully thermalized systems” (2009: 67). This allows us, in some cases, to make precise determinations. Water, for example, can sustain quantum coherence only above a span of about 50 microns—roughly the width of a human hair. “Below the 50 micron threshold, cooperative dynamics cannot be sustained in water” (73), and thus a water-based organism’s nervous system must be structured above that threshold to allow for the emergence of consciousness. Globus concludes that, generally speaking, “any structured matter with cooperative dynamics has characteristics of psi [qualia] that arise above the coherence length” (82). Exactly what these systems are remains unclear; presumably they are widespread in the natural world but are certainly not universal. QTD thus “halts the descent into panpsychism,” but nonetheless “offers far more than panpsychist scoffers imagine.”

9.2 Mind in Nature: Panpsychism and Environmental Philosophy

Any metaphysical system that views all natural objects as endowed with mind-like qualities will have clear implications for one’s attitude toward nature and the environment. The growing awareness of environmental problems in the latter part of the twentieth century coincided with the emergence of ecological philosophy and the field of environmental ethics. Thinkers in these areas developed a variety of philosophical systems that attempted to create a deeper and more intimate connection between humanity and nature; these included deep ecology, eco-philosophy, indigenous-culture worldviews, Gaia theory, spiritualism, eco-theology, and various forms of pantheism.

Of particular interest are those philosophical systems that are grounded in animist or panpsychist ontologies. Such systems have their historical roots in a variety of individuals, some of whom I have discussed in previous chapters. One of the earliest was Francis of Assisi, who saw the Spirit of God in all natural things and thus treated everything with the greatest reverence. In the sixteenth century, Bruno’s pantheistic and panpsychist metaphysics implied a deeper integration of humanity into the natural order. His system put forth a “call for a healing of the division between nature and divinity decreed by Christianity” (Ingegno 1998: xxi). Calcagno (1998: 208) reflected on Bruno’s “effort to reattach the self to its broader natural context—something perhaps which eco-philosophy is attempting to achieve.” Leibniz demonstrated evident compassion toward even the smallest of creatures. In a passage titled “Duties to Animals and Spirits” (1784–85), Kant mentions that “Leibniz put the grub he had been observing back on the tree with its leaf, lest he should be guilty of doing any harm to it.” The vitalistic materialism of LaMettrie supported his sensitivity and passion for nature; the person who sees all things as animate “will cherish life … ; he will be full of respect, gratitude, affection, and tenderness for nature … ; and, finally, happy to know nature and to witness the charming spectacle of the universe” (1747/1994: 75). Schopenhauer was pessimistic about humanity but displayed both admiration and concern for nature; he wrote against cruelty to domestic animals and lamented the damage caused by the advance of industrial society. Goethe’s panpsychic worldview was deeply intermingled with his romantic sensitivity to the natural world. And Fechner, of course, grounded his ecstatic love of nature in a thoroughly panpsychic vision of the universe, and he deserves to be held as a founding father of the modern environmental movement; certainly he anticipated much of Gaia theory, more than a hundred years before Lovelock.

In the middle of the nineteenth century, Thoreau’s intimate awareness of nature led him to a kind of pantheism in which the Earth was alive and animate, as a single living organism—see “A Winter Walk” or “Succession of Forest Trees” in Walden. Perhaps his most explicit writing on the subject is to be found in a journal entry dated December 31, 1851:

[T[here is motion in the earth as well as on the surface; it lives and grows. It is warmed and influenced by the sun—just as my blood by my thoughts. … The earth I tread on [in winter] is not a dead inert mass. It is a body—has a spirit—is organic—and fluid to the influence of its spirit—and to whatever particle of that spirit is in me. … Even the solid globe is permeated by the living law. It is the most living of creatures.

Thoreau’s sympathies point to a cosmos of universal animation. And if the Earth is seen as animate in itself, what consistent ontology could refrain from accepting something approaching true panpsychism?

A more explicitly panpsychist outlook came from Thoreau’s younger contemporary John Muir. Muir developed a profoundly non-anthropocentric philosophy in which all living things possessed the right to self-realization and happiness: “Nature’s object in making animals and plants might possibly be first of all the happiness of each one of them, not the creation of all for the happiness of one [i.e. man].” More than this, he considered the possibility that all objects of nature were in some way sensitive and aware:

Plants are credited with but dim and uncertain sensation, and minerals with positively none at all. But why may not even a mineral arrangement of matter be endowed with sensation of a kind that we in our blind exclusive perfection can have no manner of communication with? (in Teale 1976: 317)

Such musings led Muir to a Franciscan outlook on nature in which “every rock-brow and mountain, stream, and lake, and every plant soon come to be regarded as brothers” (321).

Not long afterward, Aldo Leopold, “the father of environmental ethics,” also developed strong sympathies toward panpsychism. Leopold was deeply influenced by the panpsychist Russian philosopher Peter Ouspensky, citing him in an early essay titled “Some Fundamentals of Conservation in the Southwest” (ca. 1920/1979). Considering “conservation as a moral issue,” Leopold finds the organismic view of the Earth compelling. In the natural processes of the Earth we see “all the visible attributes of a living thing” (139). Furthermore, from this standpoint follows “that invisible attribute—a soul, or consciousness—which not only Ouspensky, but many philosophers of all ages, ascribe to all living things and aggregations thereof, including the ‘dead’ earth.” Leopold is clear that such a view can serve as the foundation for an environmental ethic: “Philosophy, then, suggests one reason why we cannot destroy the earth with moral impunity; namely, that the ‘dead’ earth is an organism possessing a certain kind and degree of life, which we intuitively respect as such.” (140) This declaration constitutes the first invocation of pan-spirituality as a potential remedy for healing the ecological damage brought on by modern industrial society.

Like Thoreau and Muir before him, Leopold was not an academic philosopher. All three men must be excused for relying more on intuitive insight than formal academic argumentation. But there is no doubt that panpsychist beliefs underlay much of their attitudes toward nature.

A deeper union of philosophy, environmentalism, and panpsychism occurred in the work of Albert Schweitzer, who outlined his views on history, culture, nature, and the problem of religious pessimism in The Philosophy of Civilization (1949). Schweitzer was heavily influenced by Schopenhauer in two respects. First, he adopted Schopenhauer’s ontology of all things as manifestations of pure will—specifically, the “will to live.” Second, he inverted Schopenhauer’s notorious pessimism, seeing in the will-to-live a profoundly optimistic and altruistic worldview.

Following (like Thoreau and Ouspensky) the ancient Greek conception of life, Schweitzer viewed all things in nature as alive in an extended sense of the word, as manifestations of a dynamic and spiritual cosmos:

The essential nature of the will-to-live is determination to live itself to the full. It carries within it the impulse to realize itself in the highest possible perfection. In the flowering tree, in the strange forms of the medusa, in the blade of grass, in the crystal; everywhere it strives to reach the perfection with which it is endowed. In everything that exists there is at work an imaginative force. (1949: 282)

From such a worldview derives the ethical imperative of reverence for life: “Reverence for life means to be in the grasp of the infinite, inexplicable, forward-urging Will in which all Being is grounded.” (283) The universal will to live, which is manifest in humans as reverence for life, is realized in the rest of nature as a kind of elemental, life-affirming force: “Nature knows only a blind affirmation of life. The will-to-live which animates natural forces and living beings is concerned to work itself out unhindered.” (290)

Nearly two decades passed before there was a reawakening of the connection between panpsychism and environmental attitudes. In 1967, the historian Lynn White Jr. published an influential and controversial article titled “The Historical Roots of our Ecologic Crisis.” In assessing the cultural and religious basis for Western attitudes toward nature, White focuses on the inherently alienating aspects of Christianity. In the first place, he argues, it virtually banished spirit from the natural world—excepting, of course, the human soul, and then only as a temporary condition. Second, it put humanity at the head of the corporeal hierarchy. Humans were thus established as radically distinct from, and radically superior to, all other earthly things. With nature despiritualized, humanity was free—even encouraged—to manipulate and exploit nature: “By destroying pagan animism, Christianity made it possible to exploit nature in a mood of indifference to the feelings of natural objects. … The spirits in natural objects, which formerly had protected nature from man, evaporated.” (1967: 1205) It was in this sense that White called Christianity “the most anthropocentric religion the world has seen.”

Yet White found a potential solution to the environmental crisis even within the Christian tradition—not surprisingly, in the radical views of Saint Francis. Francis’ “unique sort of panpsychism” (1207) could serve as a spiritual basis for natural reverence: “The profoundly religious, but heretical, sense of the primitive Franciscans for the spiritual autonomy of all parts of nature may point a direction.” This extends Leopold’s suggestion that something like a panpsychist outlook could heal our relationship to the natural world.

White’s article had an immediate and considerable influence in environmental and theological circles. A minor uproar ensued, and in a little-known 1973 essay he offered a few further reflections on the original 1967 piece. He observed that the ultimate drivers of social behavior are the base value structures of a given society, especially as reflected in that culture’s religion. Religion—whether in the overt, classical meaning of the word or in a more subtle, quasi-secular sense—embodies society’s fundamental values. White reiterated his view that techno-Christian values have led to environmental destruction as a result of a denial of spirituality to the objects of nature. He reaffirmed his idea that a respiritualization of nature is central to resolving the situation: “The religious problem [now] is to find a viable equivalent to animism.” (1973: 62) He noted that recent advances in science, specifically with respect to an understanding of viruses, have “smashed the artificial conceptual frontier between organic and inorganic matter.” As before, he observed that such an understanding leads to greater natural reverence. Anticipating debates to follow, he asked “Do people have ethical obligations toward rocks?” (63) But he recognized the inherent difficulties in even posing such a question:

[T]oday to almost all Americans … the question makes no sense at all. If the time comes when to any considerable group of us such a question is no longer ridiculous, we may be on the verge of a change of value structures that will make possible measures to cope with the growing ecologic crisis. One hopes that there is enough time left.

It seems that, even now, more than four decades later, we have made little progress on this question.

In early 1970, shortly after the publication of White’s original article, Gregory Bateson gave a lecture, later published under the title “Form, Substance, and Difference,” in which he explicitly located mind in all natural feedback (“cybernetic”) systems. He furthermore identified mind as the fundamental unit of evolutionary biology: “This identity between the unit of mind and the unit of evolutionary survival is of very great importance, not only theoretical, but also ethical. It means, you see, that I now localize something which I am calling ‘Mind’ immanent in the larger biological system—the ecosystem.” (1970/1972: 460) The ethical implications of such a panpsychism are, for Bateson, clear. If, he says, you adopt the conventional objectivist materialist view of mind, then “you will logically and naturally see yourself as outside and against the things around you. And as you arrogate all mind to yourself, you will see the world around you as mindless and therefore not entitled to moral or ethical consideration. The environment will seem to be yours to exploit.” (462) Continue in this objectivist mode too long and “your likelihood of survival will be that of a snowball in hell.” Later in the lecture Bateson reiterates this theme:

[W]hen you separate mind from the structure in which it is immanent, such as human relationship, the human society, or the ecosystem, you thereby embark, I believe, on fundamental error, which in the end will surely hurt you. … You decide that you want to get rid of the by-products of human life and that Lake Erie will be a good place to put them. You forget that the eco-mental system called Lake Erie is a part of your wider eco-mental system—and that if Lake Erie is driven insane, its insanity is incorporated in the larger system of your thought and experience. (484–485)

The beginning of a cure for such insanity, then, is a recognition and deep appreciation for the mind immanent in the natural world.

A related idea was independently advocated by the lawyer Christopher Stone in an influential 1972 article “Should Trees Have Standing?” This essay was the first to seriously propose rights for natural objects, and thus to make tangible the concept of intrinsic value. After noting that for more than a hundred years non-human entities such as corporations and nation-states have been granted legal personhood—including the ascription of minds and wills—Stone proceeds to analyze the status of natural beings. Arguing for a change in consciousness or worldview, he says that we must “be able to get away from the view that Nature is a collection useful [but] senseless objects.” Even more, “we have to give up some psychic investment in our sense of separateness and specialness in the universe”—such as the notion that we alone are intelligent and enminded. By thinking expansively, we will indeed “recognize more and more the ways in which nature … is like us” (498). He then quotes a passage in which Dane Rudhyar argues that “consciousness … exists at animal and vegetable levels, and most likely must be latent, or operating in some form, in the molecule and the atom.” Noting that “all the dominant changes we see about us point in [this] direction,” Stone makes his basic position clear: Something like panpsychism is true, and it serves as the ultimate basis for seeing intrinsic value in all natural objects. Panpsychism justifies legal rights for nature.

In 1975 Roderick Nash took up Stone’s suggestion that human society must find a way to envision the granting of rights to inanimate nature, even to rocks. In the process, he recounts Leopold’s hierarchy of expanding rights that culminated in recognizing the rights of “the land” itself. Acknowledging that “the transition from life to the non-living environment is the most difficult part of ethical evolution,” Nash is nonetheless confident that “it is possible to conceive of the rights of rocks” (1975/1980: 160). Noting that “there are several intellectual and emotional roads” by which to reach this point, he discusses just two. The first is the Eastern view of a “divine spirit which permeates all things, living and non-living.” The second, implicitly preferable, is the view that “rocks, rightly seen, are alive, hence deserving of the full measure of ethical respect accorded to all life.” Nash suggests that the current conception of life is too restricted—“perhaps there are ranges of life that also transcend our present state of intelligence.”

Nash then touches on the practical matter of how we are to act toward inanimate things that have been granted rights, especially given that we are generally in a poor position to assess their wants or needs:

What, after all, do rocks want? Are their rights violated by quarrying them for a building or crushing them into pavement or shaping one into a statue? … For the time being, the only way out may be to assume rocks and everything else want to stay as they are. Living things want to live; rocks want to be rocks. (160–161)

He thus argues for a kind of self-realization of all things in nature, of letting them play their natural role in the ecosystem. But to take this approach seems to require, for him, a panpsychist stance; it is something he calls an “essential underpinning” of an environmental ethic.

In 1977 Nash explicitly returned to the subject in an article titled “Do Rocks Have Rights?” Briefly reviewing the history of an expanded moral domain, including the ideas of Leopold, he argues that rocks can fall within the realm of moral regard even without themselves existing as moral beings: “Rocks may not be moral beings, but moral beings can attribute rights to them, claim rights for them, and represent them in the quest for such rights.” (1977: 8) He then once again discusses several ways in which we can understand the notion of such rights. One is to assume that rocks have intrinsic interests for themselves. There are a number of ways to envision such interests, ranging from Eastern mystical philosophy to indigenous or native worldviews to a straightforward pragmatic approach in which such interests are taken as a “convenient fiction.” Of the latter point, Nash asks “Pragmatically speaking, if it works to produce good results, why not believe it?” (10) This is an interesting approach because it suggests, indirectly, a potential new argument for panpsychism: If a belief in the rights, the interests, and even the psyche of rocks will lead to a better world, then it would be in our interest to adopt it. This anticipates what I will later call the Greater Virtue argument; see chapter 10 for an elaboration.

Beginning in 1979, the journal Environmental Ethics published a number of articles addressing such notions as intrinsic value, nonhuman rights, and moral considerability of natural objects. Some of these articles drew from panpsychist theories for their justification. In the first, titled “The Rights of the Subhuman World” (1979), Hartshorne briefly reiterates his view that “every singular active agent [that is, every true individual] … resembles an animal in having some initiative or freedom in its activity,” and hence each such agent possesses “inner aspects of feeling, memory, and expectation” (53). Furthermore, “where there is feeling there is value in a more than instrumental sense.” Thus, all individuals possess intrinsic value, and so are worthy of moral consideration. Yet there is the lingering problem of the Whiteheadian view that certain broad classes of natural entities—rocks, plants, mountains, ecosystems—are not seen as true individuals, and hence presumably have less moral standing than fully integrated beings such as atoms, cells, and animals—and perhaps none at all. The implications of this dichotomy for environmental ethics are still open.

In 1982 the environmental philosopher J. Baird Callicott published an article comparing European and Native American attitudes toward nature. The animist worldview of indigenous Americans is well known, and they have traditionally, though not uncritically, been attributed a deep-seated respect for the natural world; it is obvious to connect the two. Most commentators have described this connection in a dispassionate, third-person manner. But not Callicott. After elaborating something of the Indian view—“earth, rocks, water, and wind … ‘are very much alive’ … . Natural entities … have a share in the same consciousness that we human beings enjoy” (1982: 300–301)—he immediately declares his personal endorsement of it:

The Indian attitude … was based upon the consideration that since human beings have a physical body and an associated consciousness … , all other bodily things, animals, plants, and, yes, even stones, were also similar in this respect. Indeed, this strikes me as an eminently reasonable assumption. … The variety of organic forms … is continuous with the whole of nature. Virtually all things might be supposed, without the least strain upon credence, like ourselves, to be “alive,” i.e. conscious, aware, or possessed of spirit. (301–302)

He adds the observation, similar to that of Leopold and Hartshorne, that such a view is conducive to sympathetic approach to nature:

Further, and most importantly for my subsequent remarks, the pervasiveness of spirit in nature, a spirit in everything which is a splinter of the Great Spirit, facilitates a perception of the human and natural realms as unified and akin.

Callicott concludes by endorsing a very strong form of panpsychism, approaching that of traditional animism, in which “all features of the environment … possessed a consciousness, reason, and volition, no less intense and complete than a human being’s” (305). Apart from a few comparable remarks by Royce (1898/1915: 230), such a standpoint is unique in Western philosophy.

In 1983 Environmental Ethics published an article by Jay McDaniel titled “Physical Matter as Creative and Sentient.” Drawing, like Hartshorne, on both Whitehead’s process philosophy and ideas in quantum physics, McDaniel argues for a “theology of ecology” based on a view of ordinary matter as “life-like, albeit in an unconscious and primitive way” (1983: 292). Much of the article is a reiteration of standard ideas in process theory and quantum physics, but near the end he begins to draw out some ethical implications: “[The fact that] a rock exhibits unconscious reality-for-itself means that the rock has intrinsic value, for intrinsic value is nothing else than the reality a given entity has for itself, independent of its reality for the observer.” (315) The ethical implications arising from such a view are reflected in the values of “reverence” and “empathy”—reverence because all things have intrinsic value and thus are worthy of moral consideration, and empathy because all things are, like ourselves, enminded.

Continuing in the same line of argumentation, the philosophers Susan Armstrong-Buck (1986) and James O’Brien (1988) sought to ground the concept of intrinsic value in a panpsychist ontology. Armstrong-Buck pursued McDaniel’s theme, further exploring Whitehead’s ideas in an environmental context. Although she frequently cited his notions of true individuals as “experiencers” who are creative, self-enjoying, and self-actualizing, she characterized the assertion that Whitehead was a panpsychist as “inaccurate.” Her hesitation followed from an assumed definition of panpsychism as meaning that all things are conscious. As she read Whitehead, “intrinsic value resides only in the experiencing of value.” Since all things—that is, all true individuals—are said to be experiencers, then all possess intrinsic value. Once again, the moral status of compound or aggregate entities is left undecided.

O’Brien—adopting the perspective of that other great twentieth-century panpsychist metaphysician, Teilhard—spelled out similar conclusions. Embracing Teilhard’s panpsychist worldview, O’Brien recounts the thesis that “consciousness exists at all levels in hierarchical degrees” (1988: 332). This is presented as a central reason why all natural objects are “good in themselves” and thus worthy of moral consideration. As in the case of the followers of Whitehead, this is more of an interpretation rather than a direct reading of original works.

In a 1986 lecture that was published in 1991 as “Are There Intrinsic Values in Nature?” Tim Sprigge repeated the view that panpsychism is a basis—in fact, the “only basis”—for intrinsic value in nature. He claims that “there cannot be intrinsic value where there is nothing at all akin to pleasure and pain, joy and suffering” (1991a: 41). Nature, he says, is intimately bound up with mind. This can only be realized either by means of a Berkelian idealism (which he dismisses as too implausible) or more reasonably through a Whiteheadian panpsychic view of nature in which “the inner ‘noumenal’ essence of all physical processes consists in streams of interacting feeling.” Panpsychic-based intrinsic value, combined with a human-centered aesthetic value, constitutes Sprigge’s dual-aspect system of ecological ethics.^5

Also in 1986, something of an ironic twist occurred in a work of analytical philosophy by Martin and Pfeifer, “Intentionality and the Non-Psychological.” As will be discussed below, the article was to prove relevant to Val Plumwood’s biocentric “intentional panpsychism” of the 1990s. Intentionality, defined as a sense of aboutness or directedness, has been seen by many philosophers, since the work of Brentano in the late nineteenth century, as constituting one of the essential markers of mentality. Will, desire, belief, and knowledge all generally count as intentional qualities. In their essay, Martin and Pfeifer offer up some rather shocking news: Virtually all extant theories of intentionality fail to fundamentally discriminate between humans and natural objects in general, and thus intentionality—and hence mind—would seem to be omnipresent:

We will show that the most typical characterizations of intentionality, including … Lycan’s own suggested characterization and John R. Searle’s more extended treatments of the concept all fail to distinguish intentional mental states from non-intentional dispositional physical states. Accepting any of these current accounts will be to take a quick road to panpsychism! (1986: 531).^6

Martin and Pfeifer see panpsychism as a reductio ad absurdum and thus conclude that the standard view of intentionality is defective. Their analysis of current theories, though largely technical, centers on the fact that “recognition” and “awareness of satisfaction” are required as basic aspects of intentionality. They argue that if a thing meets certain “satisfaction conditions” resulting from environmental stimuli, “then clearly that aspect of awareness of satisfaction conditions is something mindless physical objects are equally capable of” (544). Citing the notorious thermostat example, they add that such devices have a “causal disposition” to act in certain ways once various conditions have been satisfied. Plants also exhibit a similar “satisfaction capacity.” Consequently, plants and thermostats would, on the conventional reading, have to be conceded intentionality and thus mind.

Recognizing the dreaded conclusion that “someone might interpret it as an argument for panpsychism,” and noting sarcastically that “for some, this may be a happy result,” Martin and Pfeifer quickly set out to fix intentionality by redefining the essential role that it plays in truly sentient beings. The degree to which they succeed is debatable, and so the theory of intentionality retains some of the larger panpsychic implications.

One environmental philosopher who did take intentionality as a basis for panpsychism was Val Plumwood. In Feminism and the Mastery of Nature (1993) she devotes a full chapter to critiquing the conventional mind-nature dualism of mechanistic, Cartesian philosophy. Taking issue with the concept of strong panpsychism—“the thesis that consciousness is fully present everywhere” (1993: 133)—Plumwood opts for a weaker form, later called “intentional panpsychism,” in which “mindlike qualities” are found throughout nature. She adopts a broad conception of intentionality, treating it as an umbrella term that includes such qualities as “sentience, choice, consciousness, and goal-directedness” (134). So conceived, it applies equally well to objects ranging from humans and other living creatures to natural processes and systems. Employing the Continuity argument, she observes that “intentionality is common to all these things, and does not mark off the human, the mental, or even the animate.”

Plumwood’s intentional panpsychism is centered on the self-realization of all natural things. She cites notions of growth, function, directionality, goal-directedness of a self-maintaining kind, and flourishing as indicative of the teleology of nature:

Mountains, for example, present themselves as the products of a lengthy unfolding natural process, having a certain sort of history and direction. … Trees appear as self-directing beings with an overall “good” or interest and a capacity for individual choice in response to their conditions of life. Forest ecosystems can be seen as wholes whose interrelationship of parts can only be understood in terms of stabilizing and organizing principles, which must again be understood teleologically. (135–136)

Such a worldview has a clear bearing on the realm of human ethics:

Human/nature dualism has distorted our view of both human similarity to and human difference from the sphere of nature. … When this framework of discontinuity is discarded, we can see [support for a worldview] in which nature can be recognized as akin to the human. … We can recognize in the myriad forms of nature other beings—earth others—whose needs, goals and purposes must, like our own, be acknowledged and respected. (137)

Plumwood’s thesis came under criticism from John Andrews in a 1998 article published in the journal Environmental Values. Andrews primarily addresses issues tangential to Plumwood’s main contention, such as her critique of moral hierarchy, her relatively broad interpretation of intentionality, her discussion of machine intentionality, and her use of the concept of agency. In the end he makes no substantial criticism against either the concept of panpsychism or its use as a basis for environmental ethics. In a footnote, though, he touches on the heart of the matter, the conflict of worldviews:

Where parties to a philosophical dispute disagree over the fundamental intuitive touchstones to which appeal should be made to test the adequacy of a claim, or theory, it becomes difficult to know how to proceed further. … I can imagine a stone as mindlike … or I can locate myself within a metanarrative that sees all nature as suffused with mindlike qualities—but [are these] appropriate to the way the world is or [are they] mere anthropocentric projection? What other way of answering this do we have other than to appeal to the very fundamental intuitive touchstones that are at stake? (1998: 395)

The answer, it would appear, is “none.” In fact, Andrews’ use of the phrase “the way the world is” betrays his own objectivist outlook. To suggest that reality exists in only one way, that there is only one absolute truth to the world, is to adopt a very restricted and almost naive form of realism. The nature of reality has changed countless times in the past, and it will change countless more. Reality is as varied as the sensitivity and subtlety of the mind and the culture that perceives it.

Plumwood (1998) responds ably to Andrews in the same issue of Environmental Values, but she does appear to soften her stance on panpsychism. She re-articulates her “thesis that elements of mind (or mindlike qualities) are widespread in nature” (400), but she disavows the view that Andrews attributes to her, namely that “each natural entity has its own distinctive mindlike properties”—her concern being with the terms ‘each’ and ‘own’. In a footnote she adds the following:

I would not be happy to say of such items as mountains that they “have minds” or “have mental states,” … although I am willing to say that mountains express or exhibit elements of mind, or have mind-like qualities. (417)

Most definitively, Plumwood labels as “absurd” the view “that each individual natural entity has its own distinctive kind of mind” (400). But it is not at all clear why such a view is absurd. Plumwood gives no arguments, but merely provides an unjustified assertion. Of course, if one were to define mind as something like a fully developed, fully aware, human-like consciousness, few would accept it. But given that there is no consensus on such a definition of mind, there is no a priori reason why it would be absurd. Furthermore, Plumwood is suggesting that perhaps not every individual thing has elements of mind, but then which things have them and which do not? And why? Drawing such distinctions presents major ontological problems. Her theory of intentional panpsychism would seem to require further elaboration before it can be fully evaluated as a theory of mind. Yet her view, even loosely articulated, has value as an ethical theory. As she says, the stance of intentional panpsychism is one of “openness to or recognizing the intentionality [or mind-likeness] of the world” (403). Accordingly, we must be “prepared to recognize the other’s intentionality as a necessary condition for developing richer experiential, communicative and ethical frameworks and relationships.” Such an attitude can clearly be adopted even in the absence of a fully articulated theory of mind.

Plumwood’s subsequent book Environmental Culture (2002) includes two chapters on the aforementioned subject. One of them—“Towards a Dialogical Interspecies Ethics”—is largely a reprise of her 1998 article. The other—“Towards a Materialist Spirituality of Place”—includes no specific mention of panpsychism but hints at it with talk of nature “participating in mindfulness” (223), of “a fusion of mind and matter” (226), and of “the world as another agent or player” (227).

A more recent articulation of ecological panpsychism occurs in the work of Freya Mathews. In her article “The Real, the One and the Many in Ecological Thought” (1998) and in her book For Love of Matter (2003), Mathews develops a sympathetic metaphysical system in which all things participate in the Mind of the cosmos. She justly criticizes conventional materialism as being unable to account for the evident reality of the world: “the deanimated conception renders realism with respect to the world untenable” (2003: 29). She proceeds to adopt a form of panpsychism and then to articulate a metaphysical worldview that follows from it, emphasizing “encounter” and “eros” as ways of sympathetically interacting with nature. Mathews’ work is notable in that it moves beyond mere analysis; she sees both an ecological and axiological imperative in viewing the world from the panpsychist perspective.

The past decade has seen a decline in panpsychist arguments on behalf of nature—a somewhat surprising situation in view of the generally increasing visibility of panpsychism. One of the few such pieces is my article “Ethics, Eco-Philosophy, and Universal Sympathy” (2013), in which I argue that mind in nature is a natural basis for sympathizing with all things. Sentience is typically a justification for ordinary interpersonal (human) sympathy, and the same logic suggests that sentience, awareness, and experientiality in nature should ground an analogous feeling. This in turn lends support to the notion of universal intrinsic value in nature.

9.3 Interdisciplinary and Populist Treatments

Given the inherently unusual nature of the subject, it is not surprising that panpsychism would begin to appear in less formally philosophical and more populist or interdisciplinary settings. I have generally avoided discussion of such works, but a few are worthy of brief mention, if only because the authors have some academic credentials, because the books serve to promote an awareness of panpsychism within society at large, and because such works tend to reach far more people than works of traditional academic philosophy and thus have a greater influence.

Panpsychism, in the guise of animism, first entered a somewhat popular sphere with the release of Morris Berman’s book The Reenchantment of the World (1981). In a rather simplistic depiction of Western civilization, Berman (a historian) argues that a fundamental shift in consciousness occurred around the time of Descartes. Our original mode of interaction—“participating consciousness,” defined roughly as an animistic, holistic, magical way of thinking—gave way to a mechanistic, non-participatory mindset. This modern form of consciousness, according to Berman, “recognizes no element of mind in the so-called inert objects that surround us.” “One of the goals of this chapter,” he announces, “is to demonstrate that it is this attitude, rather than animism, which is misguided” (69–70). He then recounts how Newton and Descartes succeeded in overthrowing the final remnants of animistic and occultist thinking. Berman claims that participating consciousness reemerged only relatively recently, in the ideas of quantum mechanics: the uncertainty principle, loss of classical determinism, Wheeleresque interactions between observer and observed, and even panpsychist attribution of mind to quantum particles.

The animistic dimension of participation finds support, Berman argues, in the work of the psychologists Carl Jung and Wilhelm Reich, who held that the mind is in the body, not just the brain, and that material objects possess a kind of indwelling unconsciousness. People comprehend with their entire physical being; the brain is merely a “thought amplifier” that accentuates what the body knows. Reich’s work, Berman says, is particularly relevant:

Reich supplies that missing link [between animism and participation]. For if the body and the unconscious are the same thing, the permeation of nature by the latter explains why participation still exists, why sensual knowledge is a part of all cognition, and why the admission of this situation is not a return to primitive animism. (180)

Berman concludes with a fairly detailed look at the ideas of Bateson as a viable path to recovery of the “alchemical world view.” There are in fact some strong elements of panpsychism in Bateson, as was discussed previously in this volume, but Berman alludes to them only indirectly. And he generally neglects the entire philosophical history of panpsychism.

Two populist books touching on panpsychism appeared in 1990. In The Quantum Self, Danah Zohar’s overall approach is to use concepts from quantum mechanics to illuminate issues of selfhood, society, consciousness, and religion. In a chapter titled “Are Electrons Conscious?” she proposes a “cautious or limited” form of panpsychism based, apparently, on a dual-aspect neutral monism. Recalling ideas from earlier in the twentieth century, she emphasizes that the wave-like nature of quantum particles may be interpreted as mind, and hence “the wave/particle duality of quantum ‘stuff’ becomes the most primary mind/body relationship in the world” (80). Yet this fact evidently has no bearing on macro-scale inanimate objects, “as there is nothing whatever about modern physics to suggest that mountains have souls or that dust particles possess an inner life” (39). This somewhat gratuitous comment seems intended to deflect the standard criticisms of strong panpsychism, and yet it requires Zohar to answer the question of precisely which objects have dual-aspect minds and why. Not surprisingly, she offers no resolution.

The second work of that year was The Rebirth of Nature, by Rupert Sheldrake. A biologist by training, Sheldrake challenges the mechanistic worldview that is at the core of biology by attacking the concept of matter as dead, insentient, and inert. He argues explicitly for a “new animism” that incorporates a strong version of the Gaia hypothesis: “If Gaia is in some sense animate, then she must have something like a soul … .” (130) He conceives of this soul as the unified field of the planet, aspects of which include the magnetic and gravitational fields that science recognizes. More generally, the planetary soul is a “morphic field”—an entity that organizes, integrates, and coordinates the activities of things in accordance with a preordained teleology.

Morphic fields, Sheldrake writes, are not limited to the Earth; “such fields animate organisms at all levels of complexity, from galaxies to giraffes, and from ants to atoms” (135). They also allow a kind of communication or resonance with other, similar forms of being—whether on the Earth or across the universe. Thus, he sees the cosmos as embracing a teleological synchronicity that unifies and vivifies all things. This is the foundation for his new animism.

As a scientist, Sheldrake seems to recognize that such a view has no direct bearing on scientific inquiry. The effects of this new worldview are to be found exclusively in our relations with the world. He cites three implications:

First of all, it undermines the [anthropocentric] humanist assumptions on which modern civilization is based. Second, it gives us a new sense of our relationship to the natural world, and a new view of human nature. Third, it makes possible a resacralization of nature. (173)

Thus his unique form of panpsychism focuses on the ethical and axiological benefits in a manner reminiscent of Fechner, though without Fechner’s extensive analogical argumentation. Not being a philosopher, Sheldrake doesn’t develop much of a systematic philosophy; instead he relies on basic assumptions and interpretations, from a biological standpoint, about the nature of reality.

A few years after the publication of the aforementioned books, Koestler’s holon theory was taken up and championed by the transpersonal philosopher Ken Wilber. Wilber adopts the basic hierarchical system of Cardano and Koestler and combines it with elements of Teilhard, Plotinus, Spinoza, process philosophy, and various Eastern philosophers, producing a hybrid ontology that is explicitly panpsychist in the sense that all individuals have an “interior” (or “depth” or “Emptiness,” as Wilber prefers). His system, laid out in detail in his 1995 book Sex, Ecology, Spirituality, envisions reality as a four-part structure in which each holon is at once an individual and a part of a social system and has both an exterior (physical) aspect and an interior (“mental,” loosely) aspect.^7

As explicit as his system is, Wilber has two concerns about the term ‘panpsychism’. First, he is worried that most panpsychists ascribe consciousness or some related variant of human experience to all things. His “depth” is “literally unqualifiable” (1995: 538), and hence cannot be described in terms relating to our human phenomenology. Sensation, feeling, and even psyche emerge at certain points in the hierarchy of being, and are merely different forms of the more general “depth”: “I am a pan-depthist, not a pan-psychist, since the psyche itself emerges only at a particular level of depth.” Wilber reiterates this idea in Integral Psychology (2000: 276–277).

Second, as is the case with the process philosophers, even Wilber’s ‘pan’ is not so extensive as to include literally all physical things. Aggregates, he explains, have no depth:

I agree entirely with Leibniz/Whitehead/Hartshorne/Griffin that only the entities known as compound individuals (i.e. holons) possess a characteristic interior. Holons are different from mere heaps or aggregates, in that the former possess actual wholeness. … Heaps [consist of] holons that are accidentally thrown together (e.g. a pile of sand). Holons have agency and interiors, whereas heaps do not. (2000: 279–280)

He goes on to observe that “the common panpsychist view … is that, for example, rocks have feelings or even souls, which is untenable.” Thus—apart from misreading the “common view” of panpsychism—Wilber, like Hartshorne, Griffin, and Leibniz, draws the burden of explaining just how and when an interior appears—or, for that matter, how a new interior of a brain is created from the union of independent and preexisting interiors of the neurons. Leibniz’s dominant monad, or Whitehead’s dominant occasion, was never a satisfactory solution, and unfortunately Wilber offers no better explanation.

The Spell of the Sensuous (1996) is more a poetic essay than a detailed philosophical inquiry but it presents a widely-cited account of something approaching a panpsychist worldview. David Abram argues from a phenomenological basis for a return to an animistic worldview as a remedy for the radical separation of humanity from nature, a separation resulting from Cartesian and mechanistic philosophies. Abram’s objectives are to provoke “new thinking” among intellectuals and to suggest a new conceptual approach “to alleviate our current estrangement from the animate earth” (1996: x). He recognizes that panpsychist outlooks in fact have significant potential to alter our philosophical worldview, as they get to the root of the inert-matter view held by mechanists. But he fails to examine its substantial philosophical underpinning. Of all the Western philosophical schools addressing panpsychism, phenomenology—at least, as it is found in the writings of its leading advocates—is among the least relevant.

Related works have continued to appear in recent years. Graham Harvey’s Animism (2005) and Handbook of Contemporary Animism (2015) and Emma Restall Orr’s Wakeful World (2012), for example, address panpsychist themes from the perspectives of religion, paganism, and Wiccan philosophy. Peter Ells’ Panpsychism: The Philosophy of the Sensuous Cosmos (2011) is an engaging and popular philosophical examination. Alex Wendt’s Quantum Mind and Social Science (2015) provides a fascinating application of panpsychism and quantum mechanics to social theory, arguing that something like a group or collective mind is at work in society. For a political scientist, Wendt has an excellent grasp of the relevant philosophical issues, and his impressive bibliography demonstrates his breadth of knowledge on the subject. He deserves credit for examining the larger implications of panpsychism, which are almost completely neglected by academic philosophers.

Most recently we have the work of the medical doctor, theoretical biologist, and complexity theorist Stuart Kauffman, who argues for “a vast participatory panpsychism” based on entangled quantum systems. His book Humanity in a Creative Universe (2016a) and his essay “Cosmic Mind?” (2016b) defend a strong panpsychism, in the manner of Penrose, Hameroff, and Wheeler, in which quantum measurement, and the subsequent quantum collapse, indicate the presence of mind.

As I have noted, the authors cited above all bring a degree of academic respectability to the discussion. But in recent years the field has also engaged a number of less credentialed writers who have self-published on related topics, particularly animism. Websites and blog posts are particularly popular, though they often lack the careful research and argumentation of the more professional writers. As always, one must be aware of the source. As a general conclusion, it can certainly be stated that there seems to be a growing awareness of and interest in panpsychism, both within academic philosophy and among the public at large. Whether this portends a fundamental shift in outlook remains to be seen.

9.4 Other Thoughts, Pro and Con

Despite the many sources cited throughout the present work, panpsychism has been, and remains, a decidedly minority view in academia. Philosophical debate on the topic has historically been rare. Its supporters have written defenses, but few have been willing or able to refute them. There was a minor flurry of articles in the early years of the twentieth century, but they had limited effect.^8 The general feeling appears to have been that panpsychism was such a minority view that it could be safely dismissed with a brief comment, or conveniently ignored.

One relatively substantial critique, published in 1922, was Yale philosopher Charles Bennett’s review of Perceval Frutiger’s book Volonte et Conscience. Frutiger advocated a panpsychist metaphysical system that he called “spiritual monism.” Bennett (1922: 89) questioned “the general value of a theory of panpsychism” such as Frutiger proposed, and in doing so touched on the pragmatic and utilitarian worth of any such theory:

Frutiger contends that in a universe so interpreted, morality and religion can breathe more freely; but he has overlooked a most serious objection. The value of … “dead matter” surrounding us is that it gives us a world indefinitely plastic, indefinitely usable. … Put me in a world where all is in some sense (however obscure) spirit, … and you embarrass me strangely. Now I no longer feel free to treat any part of the material world merely as means. The coal for the furnace, the stone that goes into our houses, the steel that goes into our machines—these are now, after some mysterious fashion, my own kith and kin. I must treat them differently now. But how? To that question the panpsychist gives no answer—in which case I have been robbed of a vitally important conception of matter; or else he defines the amount of freedom and spontaneity in the material world so that it is always less than the amount required to make any practical difference … .

Two points stand out here. First, Bennett assumes that panpsychism must have some tangible, practical consequence to be meaningful—something that is arguably untrue. He is looking for mechanistic implications, when it is just such a mechanistic mindset that panpsychism is challenging. He gives no credence to it simply as a metaphysical theory of mind. Second, he inadvertently touches on what we may call the ecological issue: Panpsychism strongly implies a revaluation of the natural world. In that sense, it does in fact have meaningful implications in the sphere of human action, though they are not entailed by it. A new-found sensitivity, respect, and empathy toward natural things have been, for many philosophers, natural corollaries to the panpsychist view. Bennett complains that he may no longer employ the stuff of nature as mere means to human ends—which of course is exactly the point. In the pre-environmentalism era of the 1920s, crude anthropocentrism clearly was the philosophical order of the day.

In the 1950s, Wittgenstein gave short shrift to the view. In the posthumously published Philosophical Investigations he asked “Can anyone imagine a stone’s having consciousness?” From an analytical perspective, “such image-mongery is of no interest to us” (1953: 119). But apart from such incidental comments, panpsychism went largely undebated in the first half of the twentieth century.^9

The relative silence of critics was broken in 1967 with the initial publication of the Encyclopedia of Philosophy.^10 The general editor, Paul Edwards, had assigned himself to write the putatively objective entry on panpsychism. In one of the more astounding examples of biased writing in modern philosophy, Edwards ridicules the topic at every turn. He portrays panpsychist philosophers as fools, charlatans, or mystics incapable of grasping even the most basic elements of common sense. He calls panpsychism “unintelligible” and a “meaningless doctrine.” He makes ludicrous arguments centered on “the ‘inner’ nature of a tennis ball.” Sneering at any supposed consequences of the view—“Is a bricklayer who has been converted to panpsychism going to lay bricks more efficiently?” (1967b/1972: 30)—he likens panpsychism’s adherents to religious fanatics. He gratuitously allows that it may be useful “in a pedagogical sense, [to] help school children to understand what a chemist is talking about.”

Hartshorne (1990: 393) called Edwards’ piece “astonishingly biased” and “only trivially informative.” Griffin (1998: 96) declared it “irresponsible” and took Edwards to task for virtually ignoring the process view of Whitehead and Hartshorne. Unfortunately for intellectual integrity, Edwards’ article served as the official view on panpsychism for more than 30 years, until the 1998 release of the Routledge Encyclopedia of Philosophy.^11 As bad as Edwards’ piece was, it did serve, until recently, as a nominally useful starting point for studies of the field (although it mentioned fewer than half of the relevant philosophers, and distorted the views of those it did mention), and it did present one of the first detailed sets of arguments against panpsychism. Perhaps most significantly, it succeeded in establishing the official stance: Panpsychism was to be slandered and abused at every opportunity. Typical was the view of Madden and Hare (1971); in their discussion of James’ theory of causality, they referred to panpsychism as “an unmitigated disaster in the eyes of a great many contemporary philosophers” (23). Popper took a similar line shortly thereafter, denouncing the view as “fantastic” and “baseless” (1977: 69, 71).

Even environmental philosophers found reason to be critical. Arne Naess, for one, was unimpressed with a Spinozan form of panpsychism: “The range of predicates such as ‘virtuous’ or ‘in harmony with what is rational’ cannot meaningfully be applied to the beings of the mineral kingdom.” (1975: 119) Naess found a compatriot in Ernest Partridge, who was quite dismissive of environmentalists tempted by a “primitive belief” in panpsychism. Preferring the derogatory synonym ‘animism’, he writes:

Believing that nature is alive and sentient, the animist may presume that a cliff “objects” to being reduced to paving stones, or that a tree “objects” to being cut into cordwood. I do not recommend this defense; since few of us believe that rocks or trees have nervous systems or comparable sensory receptors, we are unlikely to be convinced that they are capable of “caring” about their fate. (1984: 105)

Of course, Partridge completely overlooks the fact that nervous systems or sensory receptors are in no way prerequisites for experientiality or subjectivity. He simply presumes this to be true.

In the 1980s and the 1990s, inconsequential and tendentious criticisms continued to appear in the literature. In the midst of a critical analysis of dualism, Geoffrey Madell remarked that

the sense that the mental and the physical are just inexplicably and gratuitously slapped together is hardly allayed by adopting either a panpsychist or a double aspect view of the mind, for neither view has any explanation to offer as to why or how mental properties cohere with physical. (1988: 3)

It is true that most panpsychists take mind as a brute fact of existence. But all metaphysical theories accept certain things as brute; why this counts against panpsychism is unclear.

Gerald Edelman (1992: 212) briefly cites panpsychism as the “most extreme form” of attempts to “make mind and consciousness direct properties of matter.” After noting, somewhat patronizingly, that “some very intelligent people have been attracted to panpsychism,” he is able to cite only William Butler Yeats, of all people, as an example. This whole approach to mind, for Edelman, is “spooky and mystical.” It has no value for a rigorous scientific thinker: “Most good physicists are hardly committed to notions of panpsychism.”

The psychologist Nicholas Humphrey occasionally dabbles in philosophy of mind, and he too is quick to dismiss panpsychism. It is “one of those superficially attractive ideas that crumble to nothing as soon as they are asked to do any sort of explanatory work” (1992: 203). Minds are linked to bodies, he says, and bodies need boundaries.^12 Things like force fields, rainbows, snow storms, and swarms of bees are nebulous and diffuse, and thus are intrinsically incapable of mind. Consciousness, furthermore, is tied to self-interest; thus, “we can rule out icebergs or rubber balls or pocket watches or the moon” because they do not care what happens to them. Mind, Humphrey asserts without evidence, is “limited to higher vertebrates such as mammals and birds, although not necessarily all of these” (205). He is aware of the demand that, within a strictly materialist worldview, consciousness must, at some point, have suddenly and dramatically arisen from an utterly unminded material substrate. Panpsychists, as we saw, view this putative event as an inexplicable miracle. But Humphrey, unfazed, says confidently that “consciousness quite suddenly emerged” at some unknown point in evolutionary history. Indeed, he is willing to designate the time before that monumental event as “BC,” meaning “before consciousness.”

Colin McGinn has repeatedly disparaged panpsychism. He has called it “metaphysically and scientifically outrageous” and then asked “Are we to suppose that rocks actually have thoughts and feelings?” (1997: 34). Elsewhere he has mocked the idea that consciousness is omnipresent by comparing it to the claim that “Elvis is everywhere” (1999: 95) and has asserted that panpsychism entails that “electrons and stars … literally feel pain, see yellow, think about dinner.” It is “very hard to take … the theory seriously,” he has stated, precisely because “it is empty.” More recently McGinn has declared the panpsychist view “a complete myth, a comforting piece of utter balderdash” (2006: 93), adding: “Isn’t there something vaguely hippyish, i.e. stoned, about the doctrine?” To his credit, he has also articulated some precise counter-arguments; I examine them in chapter 10.

Another critic is Daniel Hutto (2000: 79), who calls Russell’s implicit panpsychism “overly liberal.” The thought that “pails of water heated by the sun might be having experiences … is a recognized embarrassment.” Panpsychism is “neither attractive nor credible”; rather, it is “awkward” and even “bizarre.” William Lycan (2011: 363) suggests that panpsychism is “ludicrous” because it implies that “a molybdenum atom has either sensory experiences or intentional states.” After all, what might it be thinking? “Perhaps it wishes it were a silver atom.”

John Searle is another prominent foe. Like many others, he prefers to issue blanket condemnations rather than reasoned critiques. In 1997 he famously called panpsychism “absurd” and “breathtakingly implausible” (48), adding that “there is not the slightest reason to adopt panpsychism” (50). Unrepentant, Searle repeated the same thought some years later, asserting that “consciousness cannot be spread across the universe like a thin veneer of jam” (2013) as if that were the view of current panpsychists. One cannot call the view false, he says; in fact, “it does not even get up to the level of being false. It is strictly speaking meaningless.” Clearly Searle has no understanding of the long history of the subject he is criticizing. The level of ignorance displayed by even prominent philosophers can be striking.

Perhaps the most telling statement, though, came from Nicholas Humphrey in 2011. Unhappy with a critical review of his new book by the noted panpsychist Galen Strawson, Humphrey issued this little diatribe in an online forum:

Strawson has not so far responded to my invitation to retract his review of my book. But it’s clear from messages I’ve received from colleagues in philosophy that they see him as an embarrassment to their profession: not only an intellectual ass but unscholarly and lazy too. His ideas about panpsychism have made him a laughing stock. His attacks on attempts to resolve the problem of consciousness as a scientific issue—such as mine—consign him to the nursery.^13

Well! Clearly we need no longer bother with the topic!

Despite this occasional hostility toward panpsychist theories over the past few decades, a few hardy individuals have continued to offer sympathetic treatments. One of them is Tim Sprigge. In 1983 he published Vindication of Absolute Idealism, arguing somewhat obtusely for an idealist form of panpsychism. He has been one of the few recent philosophers to regularly and sympathetically address panpsychism (see his 1984, 1991a, 1991b, 1998a pieces), but overall his theory seems not to have engaged discussion to the degree that, for example, the traditional process view has. On the negative side, his theory may be seen as perpetuating the mistaken view that panpsychism is necessarily a form of idealism.

Of greater consequence has been the work of the prominent analytic philosopher Thomas Nagel. His 1979 book Mortal Questions includes a chapter entitled “Panpsychism” in which he writes that “panpsychism appears to follow from a few simple premises, each of which is more plausible than its denial” (181). The premises he cites are these:

(1) physical reality consists solely of rearrangeable particles of matter
(2) mental states are neither reducible to, nor entailed by, physical states
(3) mental states are real
(4) there are no truly emergent properties.

In effect, this is a more sophisticated version of the Non-Emergence argument. It constitutes perhaps the first formally analytic argument on behalf of panpsychism, and the first in at least a hundred years to arrive at it deductively. Most of the prominent positions of the twentieth century, including those of Whitehead and Teilhard, were based on initial, radical metaphysical conjectures rather than commonly accepted premises.

Following Feigl and Koestler, and despite the force of his own argument, Nagel equivocates. On the one hand he finds the four premises individually compelling. However, after some discussion he concludes “I … believe that panpsychism should be added to the current list of mutually incompatible and hopelessly unacceptable solutions to the mind-body problem.” (193) And yet at the end of the chapter he suggests that a form of panpsychism in which the “[material] components out of which a point of view is constructed would not in themselves have to have points of view” (194) might be viable. In other words, atoms may somehow carry with them “proto-mental properties” which, though not mental, combine to create experience and points of view—a kind of atomistic parallelism that recalls Clifford’s mind-stuff theory. Nagel thus leaves the door open, but offers no positive theory as to how proto-mental panpsychism might be realized.

Nagel continued to be sympathetic to panpsychism in The View from Nowhere (1986), though without significantly developing his ideas. In that book he notes in the introduction that “the general basis of this [mental] aspect of reality is not local, but must be presumed to inhere in the general constituents of the universe and the laws that govern them” (8). In a nod to the philosophical viability of such an “extreme” notion as panpsychism, Nagel remarks that “nothing but radical speculation gives us a hope of coming up with any candidates for the truth” (10) about mind and body. He advocates a neutral monist, dual-aspect theory of mind that is necessarily close to the panpsychist view. In a short section titled “Panpsychism and Mental Unity” he acknowledges this affinity but then adds that the combination problem—the problem of accounting for mental unity—is a major concern. He leaves it at that.

Nagel addresses the topic a third time in Concealment and Exposure (2002). That book includes the essay “The Psychophysical Nexus,” in which he argues for the irreducibility of consciousness. After rejecting both substance dualism and property dualism, Nagel explores alternative solutions that would account for the “necessary connection” between mind and body. His preferred solution—a kind of non-reductive, dual-aspect neutral monism—again appears amenable to a panpsychist interpretation. He notes similarities to the work of Spinoza and Russell, observing that the latter “holds that physics contains nothing incompatible with the possibility that all physical events, in brains or not, have an intrinsic nature of the same general type” (2002: 209). Near the end of the essay Nagel tackles the sticky issue of how far down, below the level of the brain, one might be able to push this dual mind-matter relation. He notes that the brain must consist of numerous conscious subsystems that somehow combine to form the complex, unified whole, and that, because of this fact, we are logically compelled to consider pushing the mind-matter duality down to the lowest levels of matter:

[T]he active brain is the scene of a system of subpersonal processes that combine to constitute both its total behavioral and its phenomenological character. … This differs from traditional functionalism … in that the “realization” here envisioned is not to be merely physiological but in some sense mental all the way down … . (230)

But he declines to elaborate:

I leave aside the question of how far down these states might go. Perhaps they are emergent, relative to the properties of atoms or molecules. If so, this view would imply that what emerges are states that are in themselves necessarily both physical and mental. … If, on the other hand, they are not emergent, this view would imply that the fundamental constituents of the world, out of which everything is composed, are neither physical nor mental but something more basic. (231)

This might appear suggestive of panpsychism, but Nagel immediately denies the possibility: “This position is not equivalent to panpsychism. Panpsychism is, in effect, dualism all the way down. This is monism all the way down.” Yet it is clear that there are many forms of dual-aspect monism that are panpsychist, and thus simply labeling panpsychism as “dualism” doesn’t negate the possibility that Nagel’s own system could consistently be conceived as a form of panpsychism. The most that he will allow is that all matter may have “mental potentialities” that are “completely inert in all but very special circumstances” (234). Whether the concept of “universal inert mental potentiality” qualifies as a form of panpsychism is open to debate.

Finally, in Mind and Cosmos (2012), Nagel suggests that we should re-conceive our basic metaphysical assumptions. Perhaps experientiality and the corresponding subjectivity do not emerge, but are intrinsic parts of reality. Perhaps all of reality is experiential in some sense. “Perhaps,” he writes, “the basis for this identity [of the mental and the physical] pervades the world.” (42) Indeed, a complete explanation of reality “may have to be something more than physical all the way down” (53). Again showing no awareness of its lengthy philosophical pedigree, Nagel cautiously sneaks up on panpsychism, tentatively suggesting that it has promise. “So this reductive [monist] account can also be described as a form of panpsychism: all the elements of the physical world are also mental.” (57) Unfortunately, he continues to vacillate on the subject:

Without something unimaginably more systematic in the way of a reduction, panpsychism does not provide a new, more basic resting place in the search for intelligibility. … It offers only the form of an explanation without any content, and therefore doesn’t seem to be much of an advance on the emergent alternative. (62)

But he immediately adds that “the proposal is not empty,” because it is amenable to naturalistic reductive options that have proved successful in the past. “On the other hand,” he states a few lines later, “the idea of reducing the mind to elementary mental events or particles seems unnatural in a way that physical atomism doesn’t.” One can be excused for not knowing where Nagel comes down on this issue.

A related issue then arises: Are there any outward signs of the inner mental life of inanimate structures? Nagel thinks there would have to be. Just as the mental lives of humans correlate with behavioral action, “something analogous must be true at the micro level” (63) if panpsychism is true. Thus, “the protomental will have behavior implications.” This presumption is debatable, but we have some recent evidence of such behavioral implications: an attribution of free will to quantum action in the work of Conway and Kochen (2006, 2009). Dyson and Bohm, as was explained above, also offered interpretations that suggest at least some basis for the “behavioral implications” that Nagel calls for. The case for behavioral evidence is stronger than Nagel suspects.

9.5 Dynamical Systems Theory

In the 1890s, Peirce observed that cellular protoplasm was remarkably sensitive to external stimulation, and speculated that this sensitivity was related to mental states, feelings, and perhaps even consciousness^14: “Feeling may be supposed to exist, wherever a nerve-cell is in an excited condition.” (1891/1992: 292) In his five Monist essays, Peirce repeatedly examines the dynamical nature of physical systems and the general issue of chance, randomness, and predictability in the universe. He notes that, in a formally mechanistic universe, all future events could be determined by knowing “the positions and velocities of the particles at any one instant” (1892a/1992: 309). But feeling, consciousness, and mind have an innate spontaneity that circumvent any such predictability, and thus “necessitarianism” cannot be true. A corresponding theory—tychism—must hold.

The sensitivity of protoplasm is important because it is “nothing but a chemical compound” (1892c/1992: 347); highly sensitive to stimulation, it thus has a correspondingly large degree of feeling. But all matter is sensitive to a degree, and therefore the most likely inference is that all matter feels in proportion to its degree of sensitivity. In fact, in “Man’s Glassy Essence” Peirce anticipates some of the central features of dynamical systems and what would later be called chaos theory:

If, then, we suppose that matter never does obey its ideal laws with absolute precision, but that there are almost insensible fortuitous departures from regularity, these will produce, in general, equally minute effects. But protoplasm is in an excessively unstable condition; and it is the characteristic of unstable equilibrium that near that point excessively minute causes may produce startlingly large effects. … Now, this breaking up of habit and renewed fortuitous spontaneity will, according to the law of mind, be accompanied by an intensification of feeling. The nerve-protoplasm is, without doubt, in the most unstable condition of any kind of matter; and consequently there the resulting feeling is the most manifest. (348)

His conclusion is that “wherever chance-spontaneity is found, there, in the same proportion, feeling exists.” And that is everywhere. Peirce thus initiates a new argument for panpsychism, based on the universal sensitivity of matter to external stimulation. Stimulated response, he says, he always accompanied by a degree of feeling. In chapter 6, I called this the Argument from Dynamic Sensitivity.

Theories about dynamical systems were, of course, very primitive in Peirce’s time. Henri Poincaré was just conducting his work on the three-body gravitational problem that suggested chaotic dynamics, but Pierce had no knowledge of this. And it would be decades before mathematical theory would develop to the point that chaos theory would become an established discipline. Nonetheless, Peirce’s intuition was significant: that mind or consciousness was something intrinsically unpredictable, and that wherever unpredictability was found, there we must also see the presence of mind.

Present-day chaos theory is often described as deterministic, which means that a given system is governed by ordinary non-linear differential equations but yet its evolution over time is inherently unpredictable. This occurs because such a system is highly sensitive to small changes in its environment. Weather is a classic example: Owing to the non-linear dynamics involved with temperature, pressure, humidity, and solar heating, there are fundamental limitations on our ability to precisely predict the weather in the future. Biological systems, from cells up to brains, are also non-linear dynamical systems. Their changes in state over time cannot be predicted in detail. Most generally, all physical systems are subject to non-linear dynamics; this is self-evidently true, given that the fundamental forces of nature—gravity, strong, weak, and electromagnetic—are all non-linear. As such, all physical objects and systems are subject to chaotic dynamics. They are all sensitive, at some level, to small environmental changes.^15

Peirce simply speculated that dynamic sensitivity was correlated with mind. But in fact the argument is stronger than he could have known. Chaos theory describes neural system dynamics in a way that offers a satisfying account of many aspects of the mind, including the unity of consciousness, the nature of qualia, and the concept of the personality. This all suggests that chaotic dynamics are a marker for mental processes.

I was one of the first (after Peirce) to make a connection between dynamical systems concepts and the ubiquity of the mind. In a talk given in 1993 (published in 1994 as “Participatory Chaos: An Analytic Model of Consciousness”), I argued that chaotic dynamics were a key to understanding the human mind, and that they implied a natural extension of the mind to all systems in nature. Independently following the approach of Churchland (1986), I proposed that the brain be viewed as a single interconnected feedback system that is describable by a classical mathematical technique known as state-space (or phase-space) analysis. One particular aspect of this analysis has proved particularly useful: The state of any system, at any moment in time, can be depicted as a single point in a multi-dimensional state space. As the physical system changes, the point moves in state space. Thus any dynamical system, no matter how complex, can be depicted in its entirety by the movement of a single point in a multi-dimensional mathematical space. This is an established scientific tool, and it is employed in a number of technical areas.^16

In the case of the brain, I proposed—as did Churchland (1997)—that the synapse voltage serves as the primary element in defining the state space, and that it captures essential energy dynamics at a level appropriate for grasping something of the mind-brain relationship. The physical brain state is thus defined as the instantaneous, simultaneous value of all synapse voltages. These myriad voltages are represented by a single point in state space, which depicts the dynamically changing states of the brain. As the neural voltages change in real time, the state-space point moves correspondingly through a multi-dimensional space.

I then conjectured that this point be associated with the “unity point” of consciousness. This leads to a number of striking correlations between state-space dynamics—in particular, the nature of the so-called strange attractor—and common-sense notions about the behavior of mind. For example, it helps to explain how the processes of mind can be unpredictable in detail and yet demonstrate long-term stability—as shown in the notion of personality. It suggests a novel reading of the notion of causality between mind and brain.^17 It offers one of the first concrete definitions of qualia: Different regions of state space would correspond to different qualitative experiences. In the end, it provides a reasonable accounting for both “mental unities’: that of our instantaneous unified conscious experience and that of our singular, quasi-stable personality. More important for the present study, it naturally leads to a system of panpsychism. Since all physical systems are describable in terms of the motion of a point in state space, and if this point is to be interpreted as the consciousness or mental unity of the system, then clearly all physical systems—i.e., all real objects and collections of objects—possess a mind in an analogical sense. Mind is thus viewed as existing in a parallel, non-physical mental space—described in terms of state space—that is proportional in size and complexity to that of the corresponding physical system. This conception, in turn, suggests a new reading of the dynamics of the mind, one that is compatible with panpsychism.

I am suggesting, in other words, that the state space of physical systems be reinterpreted as a “mind space” in which specific regions correspond to specific qualia or experiential states. As a system or an object changes its physical state, so too does it, in parallel, change its mental state—as indicated by the state-space point. All physical changes have corresponding mental changes. This is not a causal relationship, but simply a parallel evolution through time.

Another facet of the situation is that of the unity of the object in question. Objecthood, or systemhood, is clearly an ambiguous concept. And yet the state-space (“mind”) point is always distinct. This suggest that all objects and systems, no matter how diffuse, still possess a unitary point of consciousness. And it implies that myriad levels of mind overlap with one another in a simultaneous but non-interfering manner. This has far-reaching implications for our conception of the mind.

To take a concrete example, consider a small piece of sandstone consisting of millions of grains of sand held together by a silica-based cement. It appears to us as a single object because the grains are held tightly together in a persistent state, relatively unchanged. We may then make a state-space analysis that corresponds to the force particles (photons) exchanged between the grains of sand.^18 The grains are held continuously in place, and strongly so, and therefore there must be an ongoing and high degree of exchange of photons at the atomic level. The rushing exchange of billions of inter-grain photons maps over to state (mind) space as a single point: the mind of the stone. But owing to the high stability of the relationship between the grains (they scarcely move at all, relative to one another) the state-space point is confined to a very small region. But it does move somewhat, as a result of changes in temperature of the stone, sunlight or rain falling on it, someone touching it, and so on. The stone experiences different qualitative states, different qualia, depending on the environmental conditions it is subject to.

Now take the same number of grains of sand, but form them into a loose pile on a tabletop. As the pile sits there, unmoving, the grains again exchange photons—but this time, far fewer, and far less energetically, given that the grains are just sitting on one another and not tightly fused together with silica. In the corresponding state/mind space, there exists another single point—the mind of the heap. But this mind is much simpler than the stone’s: lower in dimension and less energetic, owing to the different photon exchange. We might say that the pile is less “conscious” or less “aware” than the stone, even though both have the same number of particles and roughly the same mass.

Next, gently vibrate the table. The pile will slowly diffuse as the grains spread out. Continue vibrating until no grains are in direct physical contact. We no longer have a pile, but we do still have a “system” of grains. Therefore we still have a mind-space point. But now it is much less intense than even with the pile. The grains exchange few photons—perhaps mostly infrared energy, owing to their temperature—and none that correspond to direct physical pressure. The mind of the system is simpler, less intense, and of lower dimensionality than that of the heap or that of the stone.

Finally, scatter the grains across the room. Now we see no heap, no “system,” perhaps not even a single grain. And yet the system still exists; the grains still interact, albeit at an extremely low level—if only via incredibly weak graviton exchange. And if the system exists, so too does its corresponding state-space point. The mind of such a system exists, even if at a very low level, and even if subsumed by myriad other mental systems in the vicinity.

Under such a view—which I call hylonoism—the physical universe has a vast, hierarchical system of minds that exists simultaneously in a parallel mental space. On this view, all systems or objects are enminded, and all participate in countless other systemic minds. The physical universe, which is a vast, interconnected network of energy, has a corresponding mental universe, which is a vast, interconnected network of minds or mental states. Although such a “pan-relational” scheme may seem counterintuitive, in fact it aligns with many historical conceptions of mind and panpsychism, and it promises to resolve many open issues of the mind. (For an elaboration, see Skrbina 2009b.)

Another recent connection between dynamical systems and panpsychism was made by Neil Theise and Menas Kafatos. In their articles “Sentience Everywhere” (2013) and “Fundamental Awareness” (2016) they argue that complex systems, in interacting with the world and processing information, experience the world in a mental sense, which Theise and Kafatos call sentience or awareness. Since complexity theory applies uniformly at all levels of material existence, this suggests that a complexity-based awareness exists throughout the universe. In the 2013 article, they state that “a complexity approach shifts autopoetic theory from an emergentist to a panpsychist position, and shows that sentience must be inherent in all structures of existence across all levels of scale” (2013: 378). In the 2016 essay, they change the terminology somewhat, arguing that “a monistic, non-dual field of pure awareness” is at the base of physical reality. They suggest that three guiding principles—complementarity, process, and recusion—operate at all levels of existence, accounting for the hierarchical (or holarchic) structure of the material world. They add that “leading panpsychist approaches” (such as Hameroff’s) “may likewise be seen as specifications of processes and mechanisms within the overall framework of Fundamental Awareness.”

9.6 Recent Developments in Process Philosophy

An important development occurred in 1988 with the publication of The Reenchantment of Science, David Ray Griffin’s compilation of articles on “constructive postmodernism” in science. Griffin himself contributed two of the more significant entries: “Introduction: The Reenchantment of Science” and “Of Minds and Molecules.” The former presents a series of arguments showing that the modernist ontologies of materialism and dualism are both unintelligible and that they have led to the disenchantment of both science and the natural world. The latter article offers up the concept of panexperientialism as a new postmodern paradigm. Some years later, Griffin published another significant article—“Panexperientialist Physicalism and the Mind-Body Problem” (1997)—and then a major milestone in panpsychist philosophy: the 1998 book Unsnarling the World-Knot.

In Unsnarling the World-Knot, Griffin gives a full and scholarly exposition of the process view of panexperientialism. Along the way he provides a detailed critique of both materialism and dualism, observing that panpsychist approaches have the potential to resolve a number of otherwise intractable problems. Even though the emphasis throughout is on process philosophy, much of Griffin’s analysis applies to panpsychism generally. As the first book-length treatment of panpsychism, Unsnarling the World-Knot is a significant event in the history of the subject.

Following Leibniz, Whitehead, and Hartshorne, Griffin offers an updated reading of the process theory of mind and its panpsychist implications, with a focus on the meaning of the compound individual and the nature of freedom. ‘Compound individual’, a term coined by Hartshorne, refers to an “organism containing organisms” (1936/1972: 54)—that is, a sentient individual composed of lower-order individuals such as cells, molecules, atoms, and at the lowest level, “occasions of experience.” This, of course, recalls the issue of aggregates, as elaborated in the previous discussions on Leibniz and Hartshorne. As we saw, the earlier aggregationists had to make unsatisfying metaphysical assertions to account for the restricted appearance of the dominant monad and its unifying power. Griffin attempts to further illuminate the matter, though with arguable success. Ultimately he runs up against the aggregationists’ double bind: (1) How do low-order experiences sum up, in certain select objects, to form a single, complex, high-order experience (i.e., the combination problem)? (2) What is ontologically unique about mere aggregates that differentiates them from true individuals?

First take the combination problem: On the process view, occasions begin in a subjective or experiential mode, exist for a short period of time, and then pass away into an objective state. The objective mode is, in turn, the ground or basis for the next moment of subjectivity. Somehow, one (or one series) of these occasions becomes dominant and serves as the integrator of the other sub-experiences. This dominant experience is taken as the consciousness or mind of the person. Specifically, Griffin relates the mind to the experiences of the neurons:

The brain at any moment is composed of billions of neuronic occasions of experience, whereas our conscious experience at any moment belongs to a “dominant” occasion of experience, which is a new higher-level “one” that is created out of the “many” neuronic experiences … . (1998: 179)

The unification occurs only after the neuronal occasions are completed and exist in their objective state of being. Then the dominant experience comes along and unifies the many objective modes into a single high-level moment of conscious experience. It is, Griffin says, “only in the objective mode that they are a ‘many becoming one’” (180). The whole process is repeated endlessly, at very short time intervals: neuronic experiences, becoming objective modes, becoming unified by a dominant experience into a single conscious moment.^19 The string of conscious moments accounts for our colloquial “stream of consciousness.”

We don’t know much about this dominant experience, other than that it, unlike the Leibnizian monads, is subject to causal influence. It is both caused by the antecedent objective modes of the neurons and causal on them in its power to unify. This two-way causality between the dominant experience (or mind) and the sub-experiences of the brain is the basis for Griffin’s interpretation of freedom. And yet we don’t have much in the way of theoretical explanation about how or why this happens. The originator of this idea, Whitehead, provided little definitive elaboration.

Then there is the second and more problematic part of the bind: Why don’t all collections of occasions have unified experiences? From a theoretical basis there appears to be no clear reason why only certain systems come to possess a dominant experience. Griffin implies that there is no theoretical basis for determining this a priori. Following Hartshorne, he believes that it is strictly an “empirical question” (186). Apparently this distinction between aggregates and true individuals, which Griffin describes as “crucial,” is simply a brute fact of existence. And yet nothing of importance seems to turn on that fact. What if all aggregates possessed dominant experiences? What if the nature of this dominant experience was determined by the nature and dynamics of the aggregate—by such factors as the complexity of its hierarchy, the speed at which it interacted, and the quantity of internal sub-experiences? Would we think less of our own minds, or of the theory itself? Again, this whole distinction seems entirely too ad hoc; it comes off as a convenient way to deny mind to things that “obviously” do not have it. If there is no theoretical basis for denying this power of unification to all aggregates (and there is nothing in Leibniz or Whitehead that indicates so), then it would seem most reasonable to accept the full implications of the theory.

In the end, Griffin does an outstanding job of elaborating the traditional process theory of mind and the general case for panexperientialism, though he is bound by the inherent limitations of that view. More broadly he succeeds in presenting the case for panpsychism with respect to materialism and Cartesian dualism, capturing many aspects of the contemporary debate.

Following the appearance of Griffin’s book were two other notable works: Christian De Quincey’s Radical Nature (2002) and David Clarke’s Panpsychism and the Religious Attitude (2003).^20

De Quincey gives a concise reading of panpsychism throughout history, relating it at many points to the insights of Whitehead and Hartshorne. Radical Nature tackles many issues relating to the origins of the panpsychist worldview, and gives the most readable and thorough accounting of it since Paulsen’s History of Philosophy (1892). It offers an effective overview of the phenomenon of panpsychism in the West.

Clarke, by contrast, presents an abbreviated overview of the concept of panpsychism and seeks to identify it as “the most plausible justification that can be given of religious belief in the eternality of mentality” (2003: 6). Taking a hard Whiteheadian line, Clarke denies the intelligibility of non-process forms of panpsychism, virtually relegating them to non-existence; he claims, unjustifiably, that “the principal figures in the panpsychist tradition have been careful to exclude such aggregate objects as planets, rocks, and artifacts” (3). In view of his very cursory treatment of all panpsychists before Leibniz and his quick leap to the twentieth-century figures of the process school, Clarke’s statement is perhaps to be expected.

9.7 Galen Strawson

Among recent developments in philosophy of mind, and in attitudes toward panpsychism in particular, surely the most significant event has been the public endorsement of the panpsychist view by the prominent analytic philosopher Galen Strawson. The evolution in his thinking, culminating in a landmark 2006 essay, is a remarkable story; it has altered the entire philosophical landscape on the subject at hand.

Strawson took tentative first steps toward panpsychism as early as 1994, when he argued in the book Mental Reality that to be a “real” materialist one must accept that “at least some experiential properties [are] fundamental physical properties, like electric charge” (60). This would place mind or experientiality as one of perhaps several fundamental qualities of matter. But precisely where it would be manifest was left unstated, and in any case such a view is far from panpsychism. At the time, Strawson was rather unsympathetic to it, seeing it as a rather desperate move that was potentially justified only because of the inherent difficulties in understanding the nature of conscious experience. He allowed that one version of panpsychism (“experience-realizing”), in which material reality is primary to experiential reality, “seems coherent enough” (76), but evidently not enough so to warrant further discussion.

Strawson further developed his argument in his essay “Real Materialism” (2003a). Real materialism—the view that every real, concrete phenomenon is physical—demands, obviously, that experience, consciousness, and mind also be physical. This, after all, is common sense, unless one is an eliminativist about the mind. Therefore, on the standard view, there exist both experiential physical being and non-experiential physical being. In fact, physics assumes that nearly all of material reality is non-experiential. But, as Strawson points out, that is purely an assumption; indeed, “we have no good reason to believe [it]” (70). At bottom, we do not know that there is any non-experiential being. The only reality that we know—our own minds—is purely and entirely experiential. This we know for certain. Anything beyond it is pure conjecture. Be that as it may, such a philosophical inquiry should be undertaken, Strawson adds, “with a respectful attitude to panpsychism” (75). Once again, highly suggestive but something less than an endorsement. The same sentiment appeared in another essay published in the same year. In a revealing footnote, Strawson writes:

If some form of panpsychism is, as I think, the most plausible, parsimonious, “hard-nosed” option for materialists, the way now lies open for a spectacular Aufhebung (makeover, takeover) of Dennett’s apparently reductionist, consciousness-denying account of consciousness as “just” “cerebral celebrity” or “fame in the brain” into a fully realist, genuinely consciousness-affirming account of consciousness. This, however, is a story for another time. (2003b: 313)

“Another time” would come in 2006, with the publication of the essay “Realistic Monism: Why Physicalism Entails Panpsychism.”^21 In that remarkable essay, Strawson finally elaborates on the panpsychist implications of his real materialism. Now preferring the term ‘physicalism’ to ‘materialism’, he reiterates his view that everything concrete is physical, and that experience—at least in the human case—is an intrinsic aspect of physicality. If everything possesses this dual-aspect nature, then a version of panpsychism must obtain:

If everything that concretely exists is intrinsically experience-involving, well, that is what the physical turns out to be; it is what energy (another name for physical stuff) turns out to be. This view does not stand out as particularly strange against the background of present-day science, and is in no way incompatible with it. (2006a: 8)

In other words, “it’s already time to admit that in my understanding real physicalism doesn’t even rule out panpsychism—which I take to be the view that the existence of every real concrete thing involves experiential being even if it also involves non-experiential being.” Strawson immediately clarifies his position in the strongest of terms: “something akin to panpsychism is not merely one possible form of realistic physicalism, real physicalism, but the only possible form, and, hence, the only possible form of physicalism tout court” (9).

The central argument for such a panpsychist physicalism lies in the inconceivability of the emergence of mind. Strawson reminds us that most physicalists are emergentists who hold that physical matter is wholly and utterly non-experiential. But they also believe that experience is a real, concrete, physical phenomenon. In other words, they hold that the physical phenomenon of mind emerged, in a brute sense, from some non-mental yet still physical stuff. For Strawson that view is sheer nonsense:

I think that it is very, very hard to understand what [this kind of emergence] is supposed to involve. I think that it is incoherent, in fact, and that this general way of talking of emergence has acquired an air of plausibility (or at least possibility) for some simply because it has been appealed to many times in the face of a seeming mystery. (12)

Strawson’s anti-emergence argument recalls that of Nagel (1979), but with an emphasis on the supposed dependency of the mental on the physical. If mind emerges from the non-mental physical, it must do so under a condition of “total dependence.” This condition of dependency, combined with the assumption of a completely physical universe, entails that mind must be an intrinsic quality of the physical. The physical must be, at least, proto-experiential, in which case it has in fact a mental aspect—and hence, panpsychism is true. Any “radical kind” emergence of mind is impossible because it is inconceivable. “Emergence cannot be brute,” because “brutality rules out nothing” (18–19). Reminiscent of the remark by Sewall Wright quoted in chapter 8 above, Strawson observes that any supposed brute emergence is in fact “not emergence at all, it is magic” (21).

Addressing the conventional physicalist philosopher who holds that the universe is almost entirely composed of non-experiential matter, Strawson asks:

Why on earth commit oneself to [a non-experiential reality]? Why insist that physical stuff in itself, in its basic nature, is essentially non-experiential, thereby taking on (a) a commitment to something … for which there is absolutely no evidence whatever, along with (b) the wholly unnecessary (and incoherent) burden of brute emergence, otherwise known as magic?

For Strawson, a panpsychist worldview clearly involves a conceptual leap—a leap he is at last prepared to make:

So now I can say that physicalism, i.e. real physicalism, entails panexperientialism or panpsychism. All physical stuff is energy, in one form or another, and all energy, I trow, is an experience-involving phenomenon. This sounded crazy to me for a long time, but I am quite used to it now that I know that there is no alternative short of “substance dualism,” a view for which (as Arnauld saw) there has never been any good argument. Real physicalism, realistic physicalism, entails panpsychism, and whatever problems are raised by this fact are problems a real physicalist must face. (25–26)

Among the more serious concerns is the combination problem. “In general, we will have to wonder how macroexperientiality arises from microexperientiality.” (26) He defers on an answer, but he clearly suggests that this is neither fatal nor insurmountable.

The same issue of the Journal of Consciousness Studies that contains “Realistic Monism” also includes a substantial follow-up essay—more than three times the length of the lead article—in which Strawson adds considerable detail to his argument, responds to critics, and defends a view he calls “equal-status fundamental-duality (ESFD) monism.” It is a sort of dual-aspectism in which “all reality is experiential and all reality is non-experiential” (2006b: 241). Such a view “is the only option short of pure panpsychism [in which ‘all being is experiential being’] and radical eliminativism.” Later in the piece Strawson sketches out a theory of the subject (or “sesmet”)^22 and addresses the question of causality; notably, he argues that under the condition of panpsychism “the causal effect of anything on anything will have an experiential aspect, [and] will indeed be experiential” (260). For those concerned that all such talk “seems like uncontrolled speculation,” he adds that “a hard (and genuinely naturalistic) nose for reality obliges one to endorse some sort of panpsychism long before any wild speculation has taken place” (262). Panpsychism is rational, naturalistic, compatible with physics, and fully coherent with our direct experience of the world. All in all, a remarkable pair of essays.

Strawson has continued to comment on panpsychism, though usually as a corollary to other topics. For example, his essay “Nietzsche’s Metaphysics” (2015b) touches on Nietzsche’s probable endorsement of panpsychism. More significant is a short postscript at the end of “Real Materialism” (2015a) in which Strawson modifies his view of 2006, now preferring the pure panpsychist option: “With Eddington, Whitehead, and others, I think that pure panpsychism / panexperientialism is on balance the most plausible form of materialism, the most scientifically ‘hard-nosed,’ theoretically elegant, theoretically parsimonious form of materialism.” (202) Adopting something of a “Russellian” stance (see below), Strawson notes that physics addresses mass and energy only extrinsically. On his view, energy has an intrinsic nature that is “wholly a matter of experientiality,” and is completely independent of the extrinsic reality described by science. There is no clash between panpsychism and physics.

The postscript to “Real Materialism” closes with a strikingly powerful statement: that panpsychism should be the default view in metaphysics, and that it is the non-panpsychist theories that bear the burden of proof, should one wish to defend them. “Even if one can’t go all the way [to pure panpsychism],” Strawson writes, “one should, I believe, endorse the thesis of the theoretical primacy of panpsychism.” In other words, “unprejudiced consideration … obliges us to favor some version of panpsychism … over all other positive substantive theories” of mind. Most notable is the strong form of this primacy:

[T]he thesis is not just that it would take extraordinarily hard work to justify preferring any substantive metaphysical position that isn’t panpsychist. … It’s rather that it can’t be done. It can’t be done because it requires that one assume the existence of things whose existence one has no reason to assume. … [T]here is no evidence—there is precisely zero evidence—for the existence of non-experiential reality. Nor can there ever be any. (2015a: 203–204)

The ordinary physicalist stance is that there exists (almost exclusively) non-experiential reality. But this standpoint “confers no theoretical advantages at all, and … creates some extremely severe—arguably insurmountable—theoretical difficulties.” No truly rational thinker would knowingly place himself in such a situation.

The implications of Strawson’s words are clear: Not only is panpsychism not “absurd,” “crackpot,” or “a laughing stock,” but it is the most rational, most compelling, and most logical approach to the mind. To hold any other view is to adopt unsupportable assumptions, to believe in sheer magic, or to maintain an anti-rationalist, quasi-religious faith in non-experiential reality. One could hardly make a stronger endorsement.

9.8 Russellian Monism

In the 1920s, Bertrand Russell made an important—though not original—observation about the physical world: that we know it only in an abstract, theoretical, and “external” manner. We can describe forces and motions mathematically, and we have certain scientific devices that give us readings or measurements about physical events. We can, in other words, know the structural content of the material world. But that’s all. What matter and energy are in themselves, intrinsically, escapes us. “Physics is mathematical, not because we know so much about the physical world, but because we know so little: it is only its mathematical properties that we can discover. For the rest, our knowledge is negative.” (1927b: 125) But extrinsic knowledge is incomplete, because material reality must have a deeper, intrinsic nature to it; it cannot be simply relation, structure, and function.

There are some entities in the physical world, however, that we do know intrinsically: our own minds and their corresponding mental states. These things we know directly and immediately, simply by experiencing them. Correspondingly, there is little or nothing “objective” or measureable about our qualitative mental states. Our minds seem to be utterly nonmathematical, nonstructural. This is a striking and revealing contrast.

Thus stated, we have little more than an updated form of Cartesian dualism: of a res extensa and a res cogitans. But Russell ultimately went one step further, positing that some form of monism was true. A monistic world presents us with an important metaphysical question: What is the relationship between the physical world, which we know only structurally and extrinsically, and the mental world, which we know only qualitatively and intrinsically? Generally speaking, there seems to be three main possibilities: that the intrinsic are more fundamental and thus ground the extrinsic, that the extrinsic are fundamental and ground the intrinsic, and that something else grounds both the extrinsic and intrinsic. These three positions yield, respectively, idealism, physicalism, and neutral monism.

I won’t recount the evolution of Russell’s thought here, but he generally defended a neutral monist position in which “sensations” or “percepts” were the underlying stuff of reality. This is problematic, of course, because either term seems to be mental, and thus not really neutral after all. In any case, the net result, as I explained in chapter 7, was arguably a form of panpsychism—or at least a strong sympathy with it.

During the past two decades or so, philosophers have taken to referring the system broadly sketched out above as “Russellian monism.” Here I roughly define this as the view that (1) we have only structural, extrinsic knowledge about the physical world at large, (2) our mental states are uniquely known intrinsically, (3) there exists a deeper, monistic basis of both physical and mental reality, and (4) this ultimate basis is either mental or proto-mental in nature. This is not a consensus view, and it seems that every philosopher conceives of Russellian monism in a slightly different way.^23 Stubenberg (2015: 63) refers to the “astonishing flexibility” of the concept, given that it conceivably encompasses monism, dualism, physicalism, idealism, neutral monism, and panpsychism.

Beyond this, there is the notable fact that “Russellian monism” is neither truly Russellian (meaning a position that Russell himself held) nor, strictly speaking, a monism. Russell’s own view evolved, and it appears that at no time did he explicitly advocate the fourth point listed above. In fact, “Russellian monism” is doubly non-Russellian: If we accept that we generally name things after their originators, we notice that a number of individuals held to something like Russellian monism before Russell himself did. As was noted in chapter 8 above, Eddington (1920: 200) wrote that physics is “knowledge of structural form, and not knowledge of content” and that “all through the physical world runs that unknown content, which must surely be the stuff of our consciousness”—a statement arguably more Russellian than anything Russell himself ever wrote. Nietzsche had similar intuitions. “The triumphant concept of force,” he wrote, “needs supplementing: it must be ascribed an inner world which I call ‘will to power.’… One must understand all motion, all ‘appearances,’ all ‘laws’ as mere symptoms of inner events … .”^24 Nietzsche also spoke of the “mechanistic senselessness of all that happens” without an inner will or motive force at the center of things.^25

But the premier anticipator of Russellian monism was surely Arthur Schopenhauer. He was the first to understand that science could only ever grasp the external, spatio-temporal characteristics of matter, and that something “intrinsic”—something non-physical—had to constitute the inner essence of things:

[Y]ou think you know a dead matter, that is, one that is completely passive and devoid of properties, because you imagine you really understand everything that you are able to reduce to a mechanical effect. But physical and chemical effects are admittedly incomprehensible to you so long as you are unable to reduce them to mechanical. In precisely the same way, these mechanical effects themselves, and thus the manifestations that result from gravity, impenetrability, cohesion, hardness, rigidity, elasticity, fluidity, and so on, are just as mysterious as are those others, in fact as is thinking in the human head. …

That which is really intelligible in mechanics … does not go beyond the purely mathematical in every explanation and is, therefore, restricted to determinations of space and time. Now these two, together with their whole conformity to law, are known to us a priori; and so they are mere forms of our knowing and belong solely to our representations or mental pictures. Their determinations are, therefore, at bottom subjective and do not concern the purely objective, that which is independent of our knowledge, the thing-in-itself. But as soon as we go, even in mechanics, beyond the purely mathematical; as soon as we come to impenetrability, gravity, rigidity, fluidity, or the gaseous state, we are already face to face with manifestations that to us are just as mysterious as are thinking and willing in man; and thus we are confronted with that which is directly unfathomable; for every force of nature is such.

And so where is that matter of yours which you know and understand so intimately that you try to explain everything from it and to refer everything to it? It is always only the mathematical that is clearly comprehensible and wholly explicable because it is that which is rooted in the subject, in our own representation apparatus.

But as soon as something really objective appears, something not determinable a priori, then, in the last resort, it too is at once unfathomable. What is perceived generally by our senses and understanding is a wholly superficial phenomenon that leaves untouched the true and inner essence of things. …

Consequently, with the objective apprehension of the corporeal world, the intellect from its own resources furnishes all the forms of this world, namely time, space, and causality—and with this also the concept of matter, which is thought in the abstract and is devoid of properties and form and, as such, cannot possibly occur in experience. But as soon as the intellect, by means of and in these forms, notices a real intrinsic property (coming always only from the sensation of the senses), that is to say, something which is independent of its own forms of knowledge and manifests itself not in activity in general but in a definite mode of acting, then it is this that the intellect supposes to be body, that is to say, to be formed and specifically determined matter—such matter thus appearing as something independent of the forms of the intellect, that is, as something absolutely objective. …

All the natural sciences labor under the inevitable disadvantage of comprehending nature exclusively from the objective side and of being indifferent to the subjective. (1851/1974, volume 2: 105–107)

For Schopenhauer, of course, the inner essence is something mental—the will. Thus he can state that “matter is the mere visibility of the will.” Were present-day philosophers true to their own history, they would call the view at hand “Schopenhauerian monism”—a bit awkward, but more accurate.

In past decades a number of philosophers—among them Feigl (1958), Foster (1982), Maxwell (1978), and Lockwood (1989)—have emphasized something like Russellian monism. But the explicit connection to panpsychism was first spelled out by David Chalmers. In his 1995 article “Facing Up to the Problem of Consciousness” Chalmers offers an outline of a nonreductive, dual-aspect theory of mind based on a Batesonian reading of the concept of information. Broadly interpreted, he argues that information consists of any change in a physical system, and would thus appear to be omnipresent (“information is everywhere”). “An obvious question,” he adds, “is whether all information has a phenomenal [i.e. mental] aspect.” (217) The answer, he implies, is Yes. Without mentioning panpsychism by name, he cautiously suggests that “experience is much more widespread than we might have believed.” The panpsychist conclusion is “counterintuitive at first, but on reflection … the position gains a certain plausibility and elegance.”

Chalmers significantly elaborated his theory in his 1996 book The Conscious Mind, though he retains his ambivalence toward panpsychism. He dedicates several pages (293–301) to the question “Is experience ubiquitous?” His approach is focused on the ancient Continuity argument; he observes that “there does not seem to be much reason to suppose that phenomenology should wink out” (294) as one descends the ladder of physical complexity, concluding that it is reasonable to assign experience and even consciousness to a simple feedback system such as a thermostat. He correctly notes that there are no knockdown arguments against this view: “Someone who finds it ‘crazy’ to suppose that a thermostat might have experiences at least owes us an account of just why it is crazy.” (295) As to even simpler physical systems, like rocks and electrons, Chalmers allows that “if there is experience associated with thermostats, there is probably experience everywhere” (297).

Following in the footsteps of Feigl, Koestler, and Nagel, Chalmers seesaws between endorsing a panpsychist view and hedging his bets. He seems unsure how to label the inner nature of simple physical objects: “I would not quite say that a rock has experiences, or that a rock is conscious. … It may be better to say that a rock contains systems that are conscious: presumably there are many such subsystems.” ‘Mind’ is not the right word either. He further notes that he “[does] not generally use” the term ‘panpsychism’, chiefly because that view (he claims) typically implies a system in which simple and fundamental experiences are summed together to form more complex, higher-level experiences.^26 “With these caveats noted,” Chalmers writes,

it is probably fair to say that the view is a variety of panpsychism. I should note, however, that panpsychism is not at the metaphysical foundation of my view. … Panpsychism is simply one way that [things] might work. … Panpsychism is just one way of working out the details.

Panpsychism is “surprisingly satisfying,” but its viability “seems to be very much open.” It is a position that Chalmers seems to advocate (340), but he is “unsure whether the view is true or false” (357). Yet on any objective reading of the dual-aspect information theory it seems inevitable. In just what other ways, one is tempted to ask, might one reasonably work out the details?^27

Into the 2000s, discussion on the topic continued unabated. Holman (2008) examines the connection between the Russellian view and panpsychism, though he is not optimistic that the former can be meaningfully cast in terms of the latter. Alter and Nagasawa (2012) offer a detailed look at the subject, comparing and contrasting different variations. Goff (2014) touches on Russellian monism in the course of an assessment of the compatibility of panpsychism with property dualism. And most recently we have the anthology by Alter and Nagasawa, Consciousness in the Physical World (2015), which offers a variety of views on the Russellian stance; a number of the pieces, including Stubenberg 2015, Rosenberg 2015, Chalmers 2015, and Kind 2015, examine the panpsychist implications.

Panpsychism is a distinctive metaphysical worldview. As such, it stands in an awkward relationship with conventional positivist, mechanistic thinking. It can seem inconsequential, or even incomprehensible. And yet these are the very hallmarks of new worldviews; anything less would imply a superficial or minor revision to the prevailing view. Panpsychism offers a fundamental challenge to emergentism and mechanism. And, as many have noted, the problems of mind and consciousness are so difficult, so intractable, that “drastic actions”—perhaps even as drastic as panpsychism—are warranted.

The final step, then, is to consider as a whole the arguments for and against panpsychism, assessing each in light of a deeper sensitivity to the nature of metaphysical worldviews. We may then begin to see, and better appreciate, the broader implications of the panpsychic view.

Notes

1. The other main issues, not exclusive to the identity theory, are the meanings of such notoriously vague terms as ‘physical’ and ‘mental’. Feigl spends considerable time examining these particular matters.

2. Feigl also notes that, under the appropriate definition, “there is no doubt that certain types of robots or computers do think” (423).

3. Though the inclusion of teleology is surprising. Claims of goal-directedness in inanimate systems are generally excluded by conventional science. Natural teleology may be, rather, a complement to a panpsychist metaphysics.

4. Globus 1976: 320.

5. This argument is reiterated in Sprigge 1991b.

6. No doubt both Lycan and Searle were dismayed to hear of this conclusion.

7. For all of Wilber’s impressive citation, Sex, Ecology, Spirituality is very light on citing his main predecessors. Cardano appears nowhere, nor does Spinoza, whose dual-aspect panpsychism has much in common. Even Koestler merits only a few brief mentions—surprising, insofar as one of Wilber’s central concepts comes from The Ghost in the Machine.

8. See Bakewell 1904a,b; Bawden 1904; Strong 1904a,b; Prince 1904.

9. One finds a number of scattered references to panpsychism throughout the past 100 years, though most have had little impact. If we survey the field through the 1960s we find such pieces as Salter 1922, Bush 1925, Robinson 1949, Sellars 1960, and Francoeur 1961. In the latter half of the century, we find Bjelland 1982, Kerr-Lawson 1984, and Sharpe 1989. However, not until the advent of consciousness studies, in the 1990s, did panpsychism begin to attract wider attention.

10. The final and more widely available edition was published in 1972, but with the identical entry on panpsychism from 1967.

11. The new entry, written by the panpsychist Timothy Sprigge, is more sympathetic and more balanced, though unfortunately less thorough.

12. The question of the boundedness of subjects is indeed an important open issue. For one treatment of the topic, and the potential panpsychist implications, see Skrbina 2009b.

13. This public statement, originally issued in early 2011, was reprinted in Strawson 2015c.

14. His earliest such acknowledgment came in his essay “A Guess at the Riddle.” See Peirce 1992a: 262–263.

15. Even a rock is dynamic, both at an atomic scale and, more generally, over long periods of time. Nothing about dynamical systems theory stipulates that the dynamics must happen quickly, or at a macro scale.

16. Penrose (1989) nicely elaborates on the universality of state-space analysis. See especially pp. 176–184.

17. On this view, it is incorrect to say either that brain is causal on mind or that mind is causal on brain—both of which views, incidentally, are fraught with philosophical problems. Rather, this theory suggests something approaching a form of parallelism or causal nihilism, in that nothing like the classical notion of causation is advocated.

18. I presume that the dominant force at the atomic level within the sand is electromagnetic. But there would also be an exchange of gravitons (albeit at a very low level, owing to the low mass of atoms).

19. This unification of objective modes seems problematic. How can the unification of multiple objective modes result in a collective subjective experience? The process philosophers have yet to offer a satisfactory account of this.

20. Clarke’s book was accompanied by a small anthology, Panpsychism: Past and Selected Readings (2004). This is a moderately helpful collection, though with some questionable inclusions and many notable omissions.

21. Presented in conferences as early as 2004.

22. For an elaboration, see Strawson 2009: 57–65.

23. For a few competing definitions, see Chalmers 2002: 265; Alter and Nagasawa 2012: 70–71, Rosenberg 2015: 224; Alter and Howell 2015: 277; Kind 2015: 404; Chalmers 2015: 261–262.

24. Nietzsche 2003: 26.

25. Nietzsche 1887/1996: 59.

26. Without supplying specifics, Chalmers says that “complex experiences are [perhaps] determined more holistically than this” (299).

27. Chalmers’ view of mind is closely affiliated with the panpsychism of Spinoza, Bateson, and Bohm; but he doesn’t seem to have been aware of these links.

10 Toward a Panpsychist Worldview

10.1 An Assessment of the Arguments: Opposing Views

Let me reiterate a point I made at the beginning of this book: Panpsychism is a meta-theory of mind, a theory about theories. It is a statement about theories of mind, not a theory of mind in itself. It claims only that all things, however defined, possess some mind-like quality; it says nothing, per se, about the nature of that mind, or of the specific relationship between matter and mind. This point lies behind many of the criticisms directed at panpsychist philosophies. The view that panpsychism “crumbles to nothing” (Humphrey) when pressed to do explanatory work is a consequence of the lack of an understanding of what it is. It doesn’t claim, and it has no obligation, to provide a positive theory of mind. Therefore it cannot be criticized on that account. Of course, a full and complete conception of the mind would do precisely that, and it should always be our ultimate goal. But arguments for panpsychism stand or fall on their own merits, whether or not accompanied by a detailed thesis of the mind. And I emphasize that any articulation of panpsychism, even if incomplete, has value in itself; any such view carries with it broad metaphysical and axiological implications.

Serious opposing arguments have been, historically, very rare. Perhaps the first philosophical counter-argument came from Thomas Aquinas circa 1260 AD. As I discussed in chapter 2, Aquinas argued against hylozoism by redefining the concept of life. For him life was the power of self-generating motion, something that only plants and animals possessed. Clearly, of course, one can rule out hylozoism or panpsychism by appropriate definition, but to do so is to avoid the issue by failing to address those lifelike or mind-like properties that may be shared by all things.

From Aquinas we must jump some 500 years to Kant’s Critique of Judgment (1790). The passage cited in chapter 4 demonstrates that Kant ultimately rejected hylozoism. He claimed that “the possibility of living matter cannot even be thought; its concept involves a contradiction, because lifelessness (inertia) constitutes the essential character of matter.” Kant too dodged the issue, relying on the etymological definition of inertia as inactivity. He appears to have viewed matter’s inability to internally change its “quantity of motion” as indicative of a lack of vital power. As to something more akin to panpsychism, Kant’s suggestive comment in the Critique of Pure Reason leaves open—but unresolved—the possibility of a panpsychist ontology. One might therefore conclude that his opposition to hylozoism was stronger than his opposition to a form of panpsychism.

Apart from the few remarks cited above, one struggles to find cogent critiques of panpsychism from historical figures. Panpsychism was generally viewed sympathetically, and few saw a need to issue detailed criticisms. When they did, it was typically in the form of a passing condemnation or incidental disparaging comment. Even today, we frequently find trivial or inconsequential critiques that lack all pretense of serious argumentation. However, once we set aside the jokes, superficial remarks, and ad hominem attacks,^1 we can distinguish at least seven serious counter-arguments to panpsychism: the combination problem, brute emergence, inconclusive analogy, supervenience, epiphenomenalism, and irrelevance. Below I offer a relatively detailed discussion of the first one—the combination problem—and then cite some representative views for the others.

The Combination Problem

For centuries it has been recognized that there is a potentially serious problem if one considers the possibility that mind exists simultaneously at both higher and lower scales of being. If, for example, the cells that make up an animal are presumed to be sentient or conscious in any fashion, how do the minds of the cells relate to, or perhaps constitute, the mind of the whole organism? If the lesser minds are distinct, why are we not aware of competing subjects within ourselves? If the lesser minds constitute or compose “our” mind, how, exactly, does that work? It seems impossible to imagine, for example, how a billion individually sentient neurons could ever add up to our complex but integrated mentality, or how those same neurons could yield the qualitative sensation of the smell of a rose or the taste of chocolate, or how they could give rise to a singular and unified sense of consciousness at all.

And there are other issues. Our neural cells, for example, are themselves composed of smaller structures, including molecules, atoms, and subatomic particles. Does each level of organization possess its own mind? If so, then any complex being is a nested hierarchy of vast mental complexity. Leibniz’s monadology proposed something very close to this view. Nietzsche also believed this to be the case; he held that “our body is but a social structure composed of many souls.”^2 And furthermore, does the nesting process continue “upward” to higher orders of being, to a social mind, to a global mind, or to a cosmic mind? Is the universe a vast cosmopolis of enminded beings?

Needless to say, such a situation poses, if not a problem, then at least a very large question for any panpsychist. Perhaps the first to recognize the question, and to criticize panpsychism on the basis of it, was Ralph Cudworth. His magnum opus, The True Intellectual System of the Universe (1678), attacked the materialist “hylozoick atheists” of the day, among whom Spinoza was the leading culprit:

[T]his hylozoick atheism was long since, and in the first emersion thereof, solidly confuted by the atomic atheists, after this manner: if matter as such had life, perception, and understanding belonging to it, then of necessity must every atom or smallish particle thereof, be a distinct percipient by itself. From whence it will follow that there could not possibly be any such men and animals as now are, compounded out of them, but every man and animal would be a heap of innumerable percipients, and have innumerable perceptions and intellections. Whereas it is plain that there is but one life and understanding, one soul or mind, one perceiver or thinker in everyone.

And to say that these innumerable particles of matter do all confederate together—that is to make every man and animal, to be a multitude or commonwealth of percipients and persons, as it were, clubbing together—is a thing so absurd and ridiculous, that one would wonder, the Hylozoists should not choose to recant that their fundamental error of the life of matter, than seek shelter and sanctuary for the same, under such a Proteus.

For though voluntary agents and persons, may many of them, resign up their wills to one, and by that means have all but as it were one artificial will, yet can they not possibly resign up their sense and understanding too, so as to have all but one artificial life, sense, and understanding. Much less could this be done by senseless atoms, or particles of matter supposed to be devoid of all consciousness or animality.^3

Less than a century later, Denis Diderot acknowledged the problem but found it to be no real obstacle to establishing the existence of a collective mind. Referring to a swarm of bees, he wrote that “the cluster is a being, an individual, an animal of sorts.” Tight interaction—“continual action and reaction”—is sufficient to establish the unity of the collective mass. “It seems to me that contact, in itself, is enough.”^4

In one of his early writings, Kant made a passing reference to the combination problem. Reflecting on Leibniz’s panpsychism, he wrote:

Everybody recognizes [that] even if a power of obscure conception [i.e. perception or intelligence] is conceded to … matter, it does not follow thence that matter itself possesses power of conception, because many substances of that kind, united into a whole, can yet never form a thinking unit. (1766/1900: 54)

The same thought recurs in his Critique of Pure Reason (1781). Anticipating a later and better-known statement by William James, Kant argues that material composites are possible and occur via simple aggregation, but that such aggregation is not possible with mental substances:

Every composite substance is an aggregate of several substances, and the action of a composite, or whatever inheres in it as thus composite, is an aggregate of several actions or accidents, distributed among the plurality of the substances … . But with thoughts, as internal accidents belonging to a thinking being, it is different. For suppose it be the composite that thinks: then every part of it would be a part of the thought, and only all of them taken together would contain the whole thought. But this cannot consistently be maintained. For representations (for instance, the single words of a verse), distributed among different beings, never make up a whole thought (a verse), and it is therefore impossible that a thought should inhere in what is essentially composite. It is therefore possible only in a single substance, which, not being an aggregate of many, is absolutely simple. (A352)

Mental combination, it seems, is impossible, on Kant’s view.

James is well known for addressing the combination problem, and for his evolving opinion of it. Early in his career, he viewed it as an insurmountable problem, at least for any “mind stuff” theory of consciousness. The very notion of lower-order mental subjects, or mind-atoms, compounding into more complex minds is, he says, “logically unintelligible” because such entities would have to combine upon some non-mental substrate.^5 James’ mature thinking, however, reversed that view. In A Pluralistic Universe (1909) he dedicates an entire chapter to “the compounding of consciousness.” In it he recalls his earlier thinking with disdain: “Twelve thoughts, each of a single word, are not the self-same mental thing as one thought of the whole sentence. The higher thoughts, I insisted [earlier], are psychic units, not compounds … . The theory of combination, I was forced to conclude is thus untenable … .” (189) “For many years I held rigorously to this view,” he writes. Now, though, he realizes that it “is almost intolerable” and that it “makes the universe discontinuous.” (206) If analytic logic drives one to believe in isolated minds, “so much the worse for logic.” Hence James’ final view: “[T]he self-compounding of mind in its smaller and more accessible portions seems a certain fact … . Mental facts do function both singly and together, at once.” (292) Composition of minds is an evident truth; any so-called combination problem doesn’t exist.

But the issue retains force even today. Calling it the “derivation problem,” McGinn (2006) argues that, although physical or spatial combination yields many possibilities, “there is no analogous notion of combination for qualia,” and “you can’t put qualia end-to-end” (96). Thus, he says, “we cannot envisage a small number of experiential primitives yielding a rich variety of phenomenologies; we have to postulate richness all the way down, more or less.” And that, McGinn implies, is unacceptable. Lycan makes a similar point: High-level mental properties “must be a function of the mental properties inhering in their subjects’ ultimate components.” But we cannot even imagine how this might work:

In what way could … a mental aggregate consist of a host of smaller mentations? Is it that some of my ultimate components are experiencing some of those very same mental states, and when enough of them do, I myself do? Or are the mental state of my components little, primitive states that somehow together add up to macroscopic states such as the ones I am in? Either alternative is hard to imagine … . (2011: 362)

Perhaps so. But then again, all theories of mind and body yield outcomes that are currently “hard to imagine.” It is true that the panpsychist needs to explain the emergence of complex mind from simpler mind. But, as I stated earlier, this emergence problem is much more tractable than the miraculous, brute emergence of mind from no-mind. Our current concepts in physics, in fact, give us some models by which to conceive panpsychist emergence—for example, field theory, in which distinct fields combine, overlap, and sum up to larger, more complex fields. Dynamical systems theory, with its notions of deterministic chaos and attractor patterns, may also be useful here. And quantum physics may provide yet other options, including superposition. Any of these is preferable to imagining the unimaginable: mind, consciousness, and experience emerging from that which is utterly mindless.

Brute Emergence

Is brute emergence so inconceivable after all? To this most difficult question, Edwards (1972) has a “simple answer”—essentially, reductive materialism combined with epiphenomenalism. The strong or brute emergentist need simply claim that matter, at some sufficient level of complexity, causes the sudden appearance of mind, but that this same mind has no causal effect on the material substrate from which it arose. “Granting that awareness is not a physical phenomenon, it does not follow that it cannot be produced by conditions that are purely physical.” (Edwards 1972: 27) But Edwards doesn’t say what these special and unique conditions are. And his theory naturally implies that human minds are epiphenomenal as well—something that few philosophers seem willing to accept.

Popper (1977) also accepts brute emergence. Solidity, he says, radically emerges when a liquid is cooled. Hence radical emergence is no miracle at all. And when a child grows into a adult, its mind correspondingly grows in complexity, but this doesn’t imply that the food the child eats, and uses to build its brain, is itself enminded or proto-mental. The unminded food particles, when properly integrated into a nervous system, do in fact yield consciousness. Hence, once again, brute emergence is clearly possible. But of course, all this is just an assertion: It must happen, and therefore it does. This is question-begging to the extreme.

As I noted in chapter 9, Humphrey too accepts the thesis of radical emergence. Feedback loops, he says, have an all-or-nothing quality, and the nervous system is a kind of complex feedback loop. “Hence, we may guess that, as the sensory loops grew shorter in the course of evolution and their fidelity increased, there must have been a threshold where consciousness quite suddenly emerged.” (1992: 205–206) A “guess,” however, is not a rational argument. It would take much more theorizing, backed by considerable indirect empirical evidence, before such a thesis could be accepted.

Inconclusive Analogy

Also known as the “not mental” objection, this is, in essence, a response to both the Continuity argument and the Russellian argument. It was first raised by Edwards; continuity panpsychists, he says, attempt to make a comparison between organic and inorganic things, but “the analogies are altogether inconclusive” (1972: 28). Edwards grants that such things as atomic structure, hierarchical organization, persistence, and laws of physics may be common to all material objects, but he argues that we have no reason to associate them with mental properties.

A similar argument is discussed by Seager (1995) and Lycan (2011), who cast it in terms of intrinsic natures. Lycan briefly cites two related objections. First, “what grounds the assumption that the ultimate constituents of the physical world must have intrinsic properties at all?” (360) Perhaps, Lycan suggests, extrinsic relationships and properties are all there are to such particles. Second, even if we decide that they must have some intrinsic nature, why should we assume that it is mental, or conscious? The reason, panpsychists would say, is that our own firsthand experience of reality suggests that intrinsic natures are experiential. Mind and experience are the most basic facts of human existence, and physicalism still must account for them. At present, it cannot do so. It is plausible that physicalism is inherently unable to account for mind and experience, since it has access only to the exterior of things—their properties and relationships. And yet we know, on the “inside,” that mind exists. Our inner nature certainly seems to be mental, and it is likely that the same holds for, at least, the higher animals. And since we cannot justify stopping anywhere along the phylogenetic chain, the logical conclusion is that all intrinsic natures are mental.

Not Testable

Edwards states that there can be no empirical evidence for panpsychism, and that therefore it is unverifiable and non-scientific. “It would probably be pointless,” he writes, “to try to ‘prove’ that panpsychism is a meaningless doctrine.” (1972: 28) McGinn (1999: 96–97) concurs, casting it in terms of a “no signs” objection: “regular matter gives no sign of having such mental states: things simply do not behave as if they are in pain or want a drink of water.” Furthermore,

physicists have discovered no reason to attribute sensations and thoughts to atoms and stars. They get on perfectly well without supposing matter in general to have mind ticking away inside it. If electrons have mental properties, these properties make no difference to the laws that govern electrons.

Elsewhere (2006: 94) McGinn reiterates the point: “Do the [experiential] properties of elementary particles (or molecules or cells) contribute to their causal properties? If so, how come physics (and chemistry and biology) never have to take account of their contribution?” Churchland (1997: 213) remarks that “modern atomism’s experimental and explanatory successes” are vast and well documented, whereas the success of panpsychism “is approximately zero.” Modern science can explain a wide range of physical phenomena: chemical elements, the formation of stars, evolution, and the functioning of the nervous system. “At present panpsychism can do none of these things. Not even one. … No pressing explanatory job exists for it to do.” And likewise for Lycan: “panpsychism’s most obvious liability is the absence of scientific evidence” (2011: 361).

In principle, this is little different than arguing that neuro-chemical transactions in the brain are sufficient to explain human behavior, and that we therefore have no need to posit the existence of a human mind.^6 At a physical level, brain action can—theoretically—account for everything we do. In humans, it is unreasonable to demand “tests” or “signs” of subjectivity, yet it exists nonetheless. There is no compelling reason why the same could not hold for all objects in the universe.

Supervenience

McGinn asks “Are the [experiential] properties of particles supervenient on their non-[experiential] properties or not?” This is the standard view of reductive materialism—that mind supervenes on the brain. Either way that a panpsychist answers this question, says McGinn, he runs into trouble. If experiential properties are not supervenient, then two particles could be physically identical and yet have radically different experiential states. But this leads back to the “no signs” problem, and it suggests epiphenomenalism (see below). If particle minds do supervene on their physical properties, “it will be hard to avoid accepting that there is emergence there—that combining the [non-experiential] properties in that way gives rise to the [experiential] properties” (2006: 94–95).

But the panpsychist can reply that there is no true “giving rise” to experientiality at all; it is there all along. The emergence that does occur is the soft variety—that of complex mentality arising from simpler mentality. This much is acknowledged, but it is also a much more tractable theoretical problem than the brute emergence alternative. The supervenience relationship is arguably irrelevant for the panpsychist, particularly in its dual-aspect forms.

Epiphenomenalism

“A more worrying difficulty for the panpsychist,” according to Lycan (2011: 362), “is the threat of epiphenomenalism.” Physics is causally closed, and thus any putative atomic minds have no causal role to play. “They are brought into existence only to do nothing at all.” This is an a priori “no signs” problem—not only are there no signs of mentality, there can never be any such signs. The panpsychist, of course, can simply respond that epiphenomenalism holds for all minds, human and atom alike. This may be distasteful to some, but there is no logical problem in defending such a view. And it finds support in neurochemistry, which seems to have no need for a causal role for the mind.

Or—and this applies to the “not testable” objection as well—there may in fact be signs that we don’t yet recognize or acknowledge. Quantum indeterminacy may be one such sign; chaotic behavior in dynamical systems may be another. Or, as Royce pointed out long ago, the very slow nature of the signs may mislead us into thinking that they do not exist. Mind may have a causal role all throughout nature, and we may simply overlook the form and character of that causality.

Irrelevance

Some ask, What’s the point of positing atomic minds if we do not, and cannot, have any conception whatsoever of what they are like? McGinn (2006: 95) raises a related question: “What kinds of [experiential] properties do particles have?” Presuming that atomic minds somehow contribute to or compose our high-level mental states, “they are going to have to be rich and wide-ranging: not just sensory states but also emotional states, conative states, and cognitive states.” But such things are inconceivable, he says. We cannot simply postulate their existence. “This is a game without rules and without consequences.” Lycan (2011: 363) makes a similar point: “What sorts of mental properties in particular do the smallest things have?” To presume the existence of sensory or intentional states is “ludicrous.” “How could [an atom] see, hear, or smell anything? What would be the contents of its beliefs or desires?”

But once again, we need not be able to characterize or relate to these other mental states in order to believe that they exist. This, of course, was Nagel’s point long ago (1974): that one need have no conception of what it is like to be a bat, and to echo-locate, in order to accept the very high likelihood that there is something it is like to be a bat. What is it like to be a rock, or an atom? Perhaps we can never know. Perhaps we are dealing with fundamental epistemological limitations. But this doesn’t preclude arguing that it may be like something, if unimaginably slight, to be such things.

In sum, these counter-arguments generally raise valid and important concerns, but none of them is insurmountable. In large part, they are calls for details. In order for panpsychism to be more widely accepted, philosophers will have to articulate a clear and complete theory of the mind and justify its universal extent. They will have to delineate precisely which objects are enminded, and in what way, and why. If the process philosophers, for example, seek to deny mentality to aggregates and artificially constructed objects, they will have to have a coherent and comprehensible story of how truly integrated beings come to be, and how this existence entails enmindedness. More generally, panpsychist philosophers will have to clearly demonstrate the philosophic payoff—conceptual, metaphysical, ethical—of accepting the validity of such a view.

Not that all this is a guarantee of success. Some critics seem to be terminally dissatisfied. Either they have ruled out panpsychism a priori, and therefore no case, no matter how compelling, can win them over, or they make outrageous and impossible demands of the thesis. A good example of the latter is Churchland, who closes his short critique as follows:

Unless panpsychism constructs genuinely explicit theoretical proposals and testable hypotheses, and unless it achieves some systematic successes in experimental predictions and technological control, it will continue to appear to be what it probably is—a theoretical hangover from a less knowledgeable time. (1997: 212)

Is it reasonable to demand of any theory (or meta-theory) of mind that it yield “testable hypotheses,” “experimental prediction,” and “technological control”? Surely not. Such things apply only to mechanistic conceptions; if these are prerequisites for acceptable solutions, the space of possibilities becomes absurdly small.

When it comes to the mind, we are faced with an array of difficult propositions. Every theory (or meta-theory) has significant, unresolved problems, open issues, or distasteful implications. This alone is striking, given that the mind is the one thing in this universe with which we are most intimately acquainted—precisely because we are that thing. Matter is much more poorly understood; we know something of its extrinsic, functional, and structural nature, but really nothing more. We presume that there is nothing mental about matter, but this is a baseless presumption. The alleged causal closure of physics says nothing against experiential matter. Matter can follow all its usual deterministic or quantum laws without infringing on experiential or even intentional qualities. Epiphenomenalism may hold after all. Or, as I have argued elsewhere, the causal closure of the physical may be mirrored by the causal closure of the mental (Skrbina 2014: 240). And there are other possibilities.

10.2 Recapitulating the Central Arguments for Panpsychism

In this chapter and the preceding eight chapters I have attempted to demonstrate something of the breadth and depth of panpsychist thought over the past 2,600 years. In the process, I have identified several distinct arguments in support of panpsychism:

Argument by Indwelling Powers

All objects exhibit certain powers or abilities that can plausibly be linked to noetic qualities.

Argument by Continuity

A common principle or substance exists in all things. In humans, it accounts for our soul or mind, and thus by extrapolation it infers mind in all things. This can also be expressed as a rejection of the problem of “drawing a line” somewhere, non-arbitrarily, between enminded and supposedly mindless objects.

Argument by Design

The ordered, complex, and relatively persistent nature of physical things suggests the presence of an inherent mentality.

Argument from Non-Emergence

It is inconceivable that mind should emerge from a world in which no mind existed; therefore mind always existed, in even the simplest of structures. Also expressed as ex nihilo nihil fit, or “nothing in the cause that is not in the effect.” Sometimes called the “genetic” argument.

Theological Argument

God is mind and spirit, and God is omnipresent, therefore mind and spirit are present in all things. Or: All things participate in God and thus have a share in spirit.

Argument from Dynamic Sensitivity

The ability of living systems to feel and to experience derives from their dynamic sensitivity to their environment; this holds true for humans and, empirically, down to the simplest one-celled creatures. By extension, we know that all physical systems are dynamic and interactive, if only at the atomic level, and therefore all, to a corresponding degree, may be said to experience and feel.

Intrinsic Nature (“Russellian”) Argument

Science describes only the external relations of things, and not how they may be on “the inside,” or intrinsically. Firsthand experience of our own bodies suggests that this interior is experiential, and thus mind-like. Continuity among all material objects implies that all have an experiential interior.

The seven arguments listed above constitute the traditional historical cases for panpsychism. In addition, recent philosophical analysis and inquiry has suggested at least five further arguments on its behalf:

Argument from Authority

Not a formal argument per se, but a potentially convincing claim nonetheless. Writers as diverse as Bruno, Clifford, Paulsen, and Hartshorne have cited the large number of major intellectuals throughout history who expressed intuitive or rational belief in some form of panpsychism. And in fact the whole of the present work makes this claim.

Naturalized Mind

If the human mind is not to be considered an eternal mystery or a divine miracle, it must be fully, deeply, and rationally integrated into the natural world. No theory does this better than panpsychism.^7

Last Man Standing

Needless to say, the nature of mind and its relation to the body is generally a very difficult problem, philosophically speaking. Every mind-body theory has major, unresolved problems. But panpsychism is arguably the least problematic, and hence the most plausible (meta-)view.

Theoretical Primacy

Directly attributable to Galen Strawson, who argues that there is, and can be, no evidence of non-mental reality, as assumed by conventional physicalism. Panpsychism, therefore, must serve as the default view of mind, unless and until compelling arguments to the contrary can be derived. This is a kind of “no signs” argument turned against the materialists; the panpsychist places the burden of proof on them to demonstrate that non-experiential matter exists.

Greater Virtue

Panpsychism has a number of beneficial consequences for ethics, the environment, and society generally. It is a positive, generous, and expansive approach to mind. Pragmatically it works to the benefit of all. And unlike (say) religious views, it is eminently rational. Again, not a formal analytic argument but it carries some weight, if only intuitively. Implicitly appealed to by thinkers as diverse as Plato, Campanella, Fechner, Paulsen, and James.

Despite these varied and diverse arguments, conventional materialists can still insist on a “common-sense” standpoint: Humans and certain higher animals are clearly conscious, aware, and enminded, and certain low-level organisms—plants, microbes, and so on—clearly are not (or, at least, these lower creatures act so mechanically that we have no good reason to attribute mind to them). Therefore, materialists say, there must be a dividing line in the organic world, a barrier of sorts, that separates the minded from the mindless. That seems a plausible view until we demand to know precisely where this putative line should be drawn. Clearly it will not suffice to say “somewhere,” and leave it at that. If it is to be a credible view, we need to know precisely where the line is to be drawn, and we must have a rational argument as to why it is to be drawn just there. This is an exceptionally difficult task. Not surprisingly, few philosophers have taken up this challenge.

But some have. Michael Tye tackles the issue head-on while holding to the standard view that “somewhere down the phylogenetic scale phenomenal consciousness ceases” (2000: 171). The Problem of Simple Minds, as Tye calls it, is the problem of finding the place to draw a line, and he believes that problem to be solvable. In his theory, mind resides only in entities that possess inner states displaying Poised, Abstract, Nonconceptual, Intentional Content (PANIC). Plants fail this test (“there is nothing it is like to be a venus flytrap or a morning glory”), as do paramecia (which give only “automatic responses, with no flexibility in behavior”). Nor do the lower insects qualify: “there is no clear reason to suppose that caterpillars are anything more than stimulus-response devices” (173). Fish, however, are different. They “do not typically react in a purely reflexive manner.” They learn by trial and error, and can remember their lessons for substantial periods of time. Fish have “a stored memory representation that has been acquired through the use of sense organs and is available for retrieval” (176), and thus possess inner mental states and are phenomenally conscious. Tye also argues that honey bees—regarded as higher-order insects—have memory-retention capabilities similar to those of fish, and thus are conscious: “honey bees, like fish, are phenomenally conscious: there is something it is like for them” (180).

As to the further line-drawing question regarding which insects are conscious and which are not, Tye defers: “Where exactly in the insect realm phenomenal consciousness ends I shall not try to say.” Whatever the shortcomings of his PANIC theory, Tye is at least willing to acknowledge that, on the standard emergentist view, a line-drawing exercise is demanded, and he makes a brave attempt at it.

When pressed for details, it is clear that the anti-panpsychists have a difficult task at hand. Perhaps the most consistent and parsimonious counterview is the hard-line case: that humans alone have minds and are ontologically unique (perhaps because of their evolutionary status, or their complex neurophysiology, or divine creation) and hence everything else in the cosmos is absolutely mindless. Schopenhauer briefly considered that alternative but declared that it “could be found only in a madhouse” (1819/1995: 37). René Descartes, John Eccles, and John Searle are among the few who attempt to defend such a claim. Apart from them, who will advocate such a view, and make a convincing claim of it?

10.3 Into the Third Millennium

The mechanistic worldview is deeply imbedded in our collective psyche. For several hundred years, the dominant orthodoxy has implicitly assumed that inanimate things, large or small, are fundamentally devoid of mental qualities. That view has become integrated into our science, our literature, and our arts. It has become incorporated into our deepest social values, and thus it is reflected in our collective actions. We treat nature as an impersonal thing or collection of things without spontaneity, without intrinsic value, and without rights of any kind. Natural resources, including plant and animal species, are generally seen as mindless and insentient objects, and thus as deserving no particular respect or moral consideration. With no deeper meaning or value, they exist solely to benefit us.

The great irony, of course, is that in harming nature we harm ourselves. As we deplete the soil, deforest the land, exterminate species, exhaust the seas, and warm the planet, we are paying a high and growing price. With an ever-growing human population, the situation may well turn catastrophic in the coming decades. All this suggests that our mechanistic worldview is in error: that, by treating nature as mindless, we engage in irrational and destructive behavior. Metaphysics has consequences.

The mechanistic worldview once liberated humanity from religious dogma. Now it appears to have outlived its usefulness. It has become its own dogma, more stifling and destructive than the one it usurped. We may be approaching one of those times in history when fundamental assumptions about the world change. Such changes have happened in the past. The Homeric Greeks came into prominence in a mytho-poetic age full of gods and mysteries, but then the first philosophers appeared, and they imposed an order, a logos, on the world, putting reason and rational thinking into a position of preeminence. As they did so, they incorporated many aspects of the older worldview—including the concept of panpsychism, as we have seen. After dominating Western civilization for about 700 years, the Greek logos was superseded by the Christian theological worldview. Once again, the older concepts were absorbed and reconceived in a new framework based on faith and revelation. The psyche of the world was now integrated into the notion of God, and God’s omnipresence ensured a spiritual dimension in all being.

The theological outlook held for several hundred years, until the Renaissance, when principles of reason and logic reasserted themselves once more—this time in a mechanistic and materialistic guise. Copernicus, Galileo, Hobbes, Descartes, and other thinkers articulated a cosmos of pure mechanical laws, devoid of mind and spirit, even as others—Bacon, Kepler, Newton, Leibniz—saw some reason for retaining a panpsychist universe. This new mechanistic worldview was not atheist; God still presided over the grand system, but he was removed from daily involvement. In like fashion, mind and spirit were drained from nature, leaving a cosmos of insentient particles and forces.

Today the mechanistic outlook has three main pillars. The first is that all non-living things, and most living ones, are utterly devoid of sentience and mind. The second is that reality is intrinsically objective, in the sense that a physical and mathematical description is possible for all that is real. The third pillar relates to the human psyche. In earlier times the soul was a God-given and eternal entity that mysteriously interacted with the body and the physical world. Later the soul was replaced by the mind—a mysterious product of organic processes that magically emerged at some point in evolution and that, as before, mysteriously interacted with the body and the physical world. As a consequence of these three pillars, humanity became radically estranged from nature. Humans alone retained intrinsic value, even as nature became commodified. Humans became cosmological misfits.

A successful worldview is one that transcends its predecessor by discarding certain outmoded aspects and building others into the foundation of a new, more integrated, more harmonious cosmological order. Panpsychism may be poised to fill this role. Its emphasis on mind and “spirit” is, in one sense, a return to the spiritual perspective on nature, in counterpoint to mechanistic materialism. But it is a secular spirituality, one that is compatible with a modern rational outlook. In this sense, panpsychism is fully consistent with modern science. Panpsychism has long been advocated by many scientists and other modern thinkers who, nonetheless, have found conventional science very useful in other areas of inquiry. Yet their larger worldview has rejected the fundamental mechanistic belief that lower animals, plants, and non-living material objects are mindless things. Clearly it has been possible for them to incorporate elements of a mechanistic approach to nature while maintaining a deeper view of all things as enminded or ensouled. And to the extent that they have developed positive new theories of mind, they have been able to create new visions of mind and matter and their interrelationship. This outlook strikes at the heart of mechanistic materialism, and thus holds out the promise of rewriting our view of the universe at large.

Several major thinkers were very explicit that they saw panpsychism as the foundation for a fundamentally new outlook on reality. Epicurus advocated an atomistic ontology and yet saw in the panpsychist atomic swerve the basis for human will, and hence for the very possibility of virtuous action. Francis of Assisi and Campanella advocated a theological form of panpsychism that demonstrated the presence of spirit in the world, and consequently served as a basis for moral action. Leibniz was an early contributor to the mechanistic worldview, but his quanta of the universe, the monads, were fundamentally mind-like entities. Newton was willing to consider the possibility that all matter was alive. LaMettrie was a notorious mechanist, but for him mechanism was no cause for concern; on the contrary, a properly vitalistic mechanism was a way of deeply integrating humanity into nature:

Whoever thinks in this way will be wise, just, and tranquil about his fate, and consequently happy. He will await death neither fearing nor desiring it; he will cherish life … ; he will be full of respect, gratitude, affection, and tenderness for nature in proportion to the love and benefits he has received from her; and, finally, happy to know nature and to witness the charming spectacle of the universe, he will certainly never suppress nature in himself or in others. (1747/1994: 75)

Fechner was another who saw panpsychism as the basis for a compassionate understanding of the world. As he said, it “decides many other questions and determines the whole outlook upon nature” (1848/1946: 163). James came to support “a general view of the world almost identical with Fechner’s” (1909/1996: 309), and argued that this “pluralistic panpsychic view of the universe … threatens to short-circuit” the cynical worldview of the mechanists, and to replace it with something greater, higher, and more sympathetic.

In the twentieth century, Bateson warned us of the consequences of the standard worldview. If, he said, you adopt the conventional objectivist materialist view of mind, then “you will logically and naturally see yourself as outside and against the things around you. And as you arrogate all mind to yourself, you will see the world around you as mindless and therefore not entitled to moral or ethical consideration. The environment will seem to be yours to exploit.” (1972: 462) Bateson lived at a time when the current ecological crisis was just becoming apparent. It was clear to him that this situation was rooted in a defective conception of mind. His outlook was shared by Plumwood, Mathews, and others who saw a subtle form of panpsychism as the foundation of a new, more compassionate, less confrontational environmental ethic.

One of the most poetic expressions of the virtues of the panpsychic worldview was also one of the earliest. Recall Empedocles’ beautiful fragment 110, in which panpsychism is seen as the key to revelations about the true nature of the world:

If thou shouldst plant these things in thy firm understanding and contemplate them with good will and unclouded attention, they will stand by thee for ever every one, and thou shalt gain many other things from them; … for know that all things have wisdom and a portion of thought.

Here Empedocles demonstrates a reverential, almost mystic belief in the power of the panpsychist worldview. It is, he suggests, simply the most enlightening and virtuous standpoint from which to view the cosmos. It is nothing less than the key to ultimate truth.

These beliefs of Empedocles, Fechner, James, Bateson, and others are striking; they suggest that panpsychism is the superior worldview because it leads to a more integrated, compassionate, and sympathetic cosmos. It is life-affirming and life-enhancing. It leads to positive, sustaining values for humanity. It stands in stark contrast to the cynical, isolating, manipulative values of mechanistic materialism. To the extent that these mechanistic values have contributed to our current environmental and social crises, panpsychist values may begin to reverse this process and heal the damage.

To judge the value of something as far-reaching and fundamental as a metaphysical worldview is a difficult prospect. It takes years, even centuries, for the full effects of a new worldview and its corresponding values to be realized. About 350 years passed before the negative effects of the mechanistic outlook became apparent. Thus, today we are likely to be unable to adequately judge the net worth of a panpsychist worldview. And yet the imperative of the present time calls for change. Mechanism is evidently profoundly defective; in any case, it will not last—something will take its place. This new Weltanschauung must, for our sake and the sake of the planet, be sustainable, holistic, and compassionate. The evidence is encouraging. Of the dozens of panpsychist thinkers examined in the present work, nearly every one has adopted an optimistic, life-affirming, and sympathetic perspective on the world.

Granting all this, the cynical materialist can still ask “Yes, but is it true?” If panpsychism is, in the end, just some happy delusion, we are surely not better off adopting it, or simply pretending it to be true. Agreed. Yet it must be emphasized that truth can be assessed only from within a given worldview. The standard materialist, being fundamentally committed to an anti-panpsychist view, has no unbiased standpoint from which to make a judgment. Thus any ruling of “unintelligible” or “false” is meaningless. Christians have long denounced animism and polytheism as untrue, accusing their adherents of living in a primitive cosmos of omnipresent spirits and ghosts. Likewise, materialists have accused Christians and other theologically minded individuals of buying into a “happy myth” that has no scientific basis. And of course others today blame the materialist mindset as the root cause of many of our present-day social and environmental problems. Objectivity, moral neutrality, and a fundamentally inanimate nature are mechanistic assumptions about the world—presumed but never proven. Mechanistic materialism can thus be seen, like the rest, as a happy myth, one that liberated humanity from stifling theology but which has now reached the end of its useful life.

The evolution of worldviews is one of the great stories of human culture. Worldviews are born, and they are liberating and visionary. They help to define what is true and what is good. They expand to encompass many aspects of society. They undergo gradual evolution and refinement. At some point they grow rigid and inflexible. Ultimately they become self-justifying, self-perpetuating, and finally, self-destructive. Materialism, and the accompanying analytical and logical philosophy, seems to have reached this terminal stage.

Panpsychism—ancient panpsychism—appears able to provide the foundation for a new worldview in a way that deeply addresses the root issues. It is easy to abuse dead, inanimate matter, or unconscious forms of life. The human who alone has mind, or in whom mind is a contradiction or unfathomable mystery, has no sense of being at home in the cosmos. Consequently he is likely to feel alienated, frightened, distressed, angry, or foolish. It need not be so. Philosophers have envisioned alternative views that have equal claim to validity. We as a civilization need only summon our collective wisdom and courage, learn the lessons of history, and transcend present ways of thinking. Thus has it always been so. Transcendence is in the nature of the cosmos, and only transcendent thinking can carry us forward along our great evolutionary journey.

Notes

1. As discussed in chapter 9.

2. Beyond Good and Evil, section 19.

3. Reprinted on page 290 of Uzgalis 2011. Here the punctuation has been modified slightly for readability.

4. Diderot 1769/1937: 67, 76. See discussion in chapter 4 above.

5. See James 1890/1950: 149–155.

6. This is the well-known “problem of other minds”: We cannot even prove the existence of human minds other than our own. As Russell pointed out long ago, the best we can do is make plausible inferences from analogical behavior.

7. Attributable to Hartshorne, Griffin, and other process philosophers.